<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-03-12T09:42:54+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Infermuse</title><subtitle>Practical wisdom from studies, experiments and books</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Bringing awe into our lives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bringing-awe-into-to-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bringing awe into our lives" /><published>2023-03-12T08:00:05+05:30</published><updated>2023-03-12T08:00:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bringing-awe-into-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bringing-awe-into-to-life/"><![CDATA[<p>Awe is a type of emotion that has many affable qualities. Dacher Keltner’s book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Awe-Science-Everyday-Wonder-Transform/dp/B09YMNCBQD/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=awe+the+new+science+of+everyday+wonder&amp;qid=1678590561&amp;sprefix=AWE+%2Caps%2C664&amp;sr=8-1">Awe</a> talks about the role of awe in our lives and how it can inspire creativity, bring down stress and help us lead the good life. It lists down 8 simple ways we can find awe in our daily life.</p>

<h5 id="the-cool-thing-about-awe">The cool thing about awe</h5>

<p>The most common definition of Awe is the feeling of vastness that we experience when we encounter something that is bigger than us. Music, art, religion, nature, sports are some common conduits of awe. It is usually felt in the presence of something vast that transcends our current understanding of the world. Vastness can be physical, temporal, semantic, about ideas, challenging, destablising, etc.</p>

<p>Awe is contextual. Where we come from affects how we experience awe. For example, how we conceptualise virtue based on our upbriging, cultural experience, religious beliefs, etc affects how we experience moral beauty which in turn affects how we experience awe. Cultural preferences can also affect how we feel awe. Hierarchical cultures like Japan, experience awe in front of an inspiring personality with some element of fear. Cultures and religions that don’t believe in a judgemental God philosophy, experience bliss in encounter with the divine.</p>

<p>Experiencing awe, for example by looking at the skeleton of a T Rex, helps quite down our hyper individualistic self and opens us for collaboration. Our default mode network or DMN - the part of our brain network that is associated with the excesses of our ego, is known quiten down when in presence of something vast. It also helps us make peace with the fact that we are not a 100% control of our lives.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/museum.jpeg" alt="Art is one of the ways we can experience awe" srcset="    /assets/resized/museum-320x213.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/museum-480x320.jpeg 480w,    /assets/resized/museum-800x533.jpeg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/03/museum.jpeg 1200w" /></p>

<p>Awe can also amplify our thinking faculties. Einstein is said to have been awe struck by rainbows and much of the work around refraction and perception was triggered by it.</p>

<h5 id="8-ways-you-can-welcome-awe-into-your-life">8 ways you can welcome awe into your life</h5>

<p>The author calls this section 8 wonders of life. Here are the 8 ways you can experience awe in your life.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Moral beauty - Watching, experiencing or reading about other people’s acts of courage, justice, generosity, etc</li>
  <li>Collective effervescence - moving in unison or participating in shared attention. It is the force people feel when in a collective (sporting events, dance classes, rituals and ceremonies)</li>
  <li>Nature - hikes, spending time in the wild, rock climbing, rafting, etc. merely listening to flowing water is known to improve our attention and provide better ability to discern between urgent and important matters.</li>
  <li>Music - specific musical notes make us feel specific emotions and these emotions are universally similar across cultures. if you like listening to music, you can easily get your daily dose of awe from it.</li>
  <li>Visual design - paintings, buildings, machines, etc. Appreciating actual contours of the geometry can incite certain feelings in us. In visual design, we like familiarity of form and design and it makes us feel comforted.</li>
  <li>Spiritual or religious stories - there are over 4200 active religions in the world today and the mystical awe that originates from it can cause feelings of “vanishing self” or “ego death” that bring awe and are known to make us more curious, creative and altruistic.</li>
  <li>Stories of life and death - thinking about or experiencing birth or death of a close one, can cause us to appreciate the ephemeral nature of life and leave us awestruck.</li>
  <li>Epiphanies - sudden understandings of truths about life. when systems thinking exposes us how the world around us works, awe overtakes us (think Darwin’s voyage to the Galapagos)</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Awe is a type of emotion that has many affable qualities. Dacher Keltner’s book Awe talks about the role of awe in our lives and how it can inspire creativity, bring down stress and help us lead the good life. It lists down 8 simple ways we can find awe in our daily life.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from How to be perfect</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-how-to-be-perfect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from How to be perfect" /><published>2023-03-05T09:04:05+05:30</published><updated>2023-03-05T09:04:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-how-to-be-perfect</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-how-to-be-perfect/"><![CDATA[<p>In his book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Be-Perfect-Correct-Question/dp/B099BZCW7G/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2Q6SKL731H9YY&amp;keywords=how+to+be+perfect&amp;qid=1678001662&amp;sprefix=how+to+be+%2Caps%2C1384&amp;sr=8-1">How to be perfect</a>, Michael Shur, the writer behind shows like The office, Brooklyn Nine-Nine and The Good Place, introduces us to important moral philosophical concepts that help us distinguish right from wrong. Think of it as a 101 moral philosophy course by a really witty and humorous professor.</p>

<p>The book is his condensed understanding of the key moral ideas that have shaped the modern world, ranging from Aristotle’s Golden mean to Kantian Deontology to Bentham’s Utilitarianism to Sartre’s Existentialism. This book will absolutely make you sound smart in a party if you’re into that sort of thing. In this post, I try to summarise the key moral philosophical ideas described in the book.</p>

<h5 id="aristotles-golden-mean">Aristotle’s Golden Mean</h5>

<p>Aristotle’s Golden mean can be summarised in one line as “nothing in excess”. According to Aristotle, we all have capacities for acquiring virtues. The author calls this “being born with a good starter kit”. We need nature, habit and teachings to develop our sense that comes not by nature, but through habituation i.e. practice. It’s like learning to bagpipe (we may have aptitude for it but we get better by doing it under instruction from a good teacher). The Golden mean is the perfectly balanced amount of quality (deficiency v excess). It’s a Goldilocks zone of virtue. The idea is to modulate ones inclinations of our starter kits and practice striking the balance. According to this philosophy most of what is wrong with the world can be described in terms of being excess of something or dearth of something else.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/the_good_place.jpg" alt="Screenshot from The Good Place" srcset="    /assets/resized/the_good_place-320x180.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/the_good_place-480x270.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/the_good_place-800x450.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/02/the_good_place.jpg 832w" /></p>

<h5 id="utilitarianism">Utilitarianism</h5>

<p>Jeremy Bentham’s utilitarianism is the idea that the right thing to do is the thing that maximises the happiness of the most people. This is a simple mathematical idea that upon even the slight deeper inspection starts to show cracks. According to utilatarianism (or consequentialism as it is often called) it would be absolutely ok to kill one person to save two. The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TSH-m5GtrzE">famous trolley problem</a> finds a simple solution according to this philosophy. If you’re on a trolley track and you see a trolley coming towards five people, you can either pull a lever and divert the trolley to a single person or you can do nothing and let the trolley kill five people. According to utilitarianism, you should pull the lever because it maximises the happiness of the most people. This is a very simplistic formula and it doesn’t take into account the fact that the person you’re killing is a person too.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/trolley_problem.jpeg" alt="Screenshot from The Good Place" srcset="    /assets/resized/trolley_problem-320x169.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/trolley_problem-480x254.jpeg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/02/trolley_problem.jpeg 600w" /></p>

<p>J S Mills improved upon this basic idea by adding another condition which prevents us from harming other people. The <em>new and improved</em> utilitarianism thus becomes, we should only do things that maximise the happiness of the most people as long as it doesn’t harm anyone else. It is still a very simplistic formula but at least it doesn’t allow us to kill someone to save others.</p>

<h5 id="kantian-deontology">Kantian Deontology</h5>

<p>According to Kantian Deontology, the right thing to do is the thing that is right in itself, regardless of the consequences. Immanuel Kant forces us to derive universal maxims and ask ourselves if we would want everyone to follow them so things like lying, cheating or stealing are wrong. If you’re doing something that you would not want everyone else in the world to do, then it’s probably not the right thing to do. This idea is called the Categorical Imperative. This is based on the underlying concept that humans are inherently better and they must do the moral thing out of a duty and not a need. Kantian philosophy is rooted in the notion of humans being better than the rest of nature.</p>

<p>There is an adapted version of the categorical imperative that restricts us from using people as means to and end. This is quite a handy maxim and helps us justify not killing or hurting a person to any goal that we may have.</p>

<h5 id="scanlons-contractualism">Scanlon’s Contractualism</h5>

<p>As you can imagine, contemplating if what we’re doing can be treated of as a valid universal maxim is a very difficult and cumbersome thing to do. A somewhat summarised version of this is the theory of Contractualism by T M Scanlon. It suggests that there are simple baseline levels of behavior that we all agree to be reasonable (don’t steal, don’t drive in the emergency lane, etc). Just imagine what can be considered as a reasonable expectation from others and then ask yourself if what you’re doing is something that violates that.</p>

<p>There is a South African philosophy called <em>Ubuntu</em> that loosely translates to <em>living through each other</em>. It can be thought of as “I am, because we are” and it supercharges Scanlon’s contractualism. It says not only do we owe reasonable behavior to each other, we exist through each other. Nelson Mandela once explained Ubuntu as enriching oneself to enrich the community (as opposed to at the expense of).</p>

<h5 id="william-james-pragmatism">William James’ Pragmatism</h5>

<p>Pragmatism dictates that the right thing to do is the thing that works. It’s a very pragmatic approach to morality that focusses on the end and doesn’t worry too much about the way it is achieved. Pragmatism asks us to play referees and blow the whistle if we see some practical differences in the way ends are met. For example if Jeffrey Epstein were to donate to charity to whitewash his name, it would be different from any other person doing it for a little ego massage. While the Kantian would reject both, a pragmatist would allow the latter but reject the former.</p>

<h5 id="sartres-existentialism">Sartre’s Existentialism</h5>

<p>Sartre and Camus were two famous French existentialist philosophers of the post war times. Sartre’s Existentialism describes that there is no structure or meaning before we are born. After we materialise it is upto us to define ourselves with our actions. It is thought to have given rise to these two somewhat contradictory ideas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>There is no God and all we have are ourselves to hold ourselves accountable</li>
  <li>We humans should hold ourselves accountable to a model behavior without guidance from any other theory</li>
</ol>

<p>Camus explains that humans desire meaning from the universe which it denies. We’re a lot of nothingness and all life is made absurd by our desire to get meaning from the world. Camus says Sisyphus is actually happy as he doesn’t need to find meaning in his rock task cause he knows it is a punishment in the form of a pointless task.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In his book How to be perfect, Michael Shur, the writer behind shows like The office, Brooklyn Nine-Nine and The Good Place, introduces us to important moral philosophical concepts that help us distinguish right from wrong. Think of it as a 101 moral philosophy course by a really witty and humorous professor.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leadership lessons from Unleashed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/leadership-lessons-from-unleashed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leadership lessons from Unleashed" /><published>2023-02-25T00:40:05+05:30</published><updated>2023-02-25T00:40:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-unleashed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/leadership-lessons-from-unleashed/"><![CDATA[<p>The book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Unleashed-Unapologetic-Leaders-Empowering-Everyone/dp/B089NXGBJR/ref=sr_1_1?crid=KQVCZAWZK97H&amp;keywords=unleashed+frances+frei&amp;qid=1677384772&amp;sprefix=unleashed+frances+fre%2Caps%2C1214&amp;sr=8-1">Unleashed by Frances Frei and Anne Morris</a> is about how to lead by empowering people. Leadership is not about you, it’s about empowering other people around you both in your presence (thro trust, love and belonging) and in your absence (thro strategy and culture). My key takeaways from this book is the practical wisdom related to what I could do myself as an individual to empowerment others around me.</p>

<h5 id="warning-signs-you-make-it-all-about-you">Warning signs you make it all about you</h5>

<p>Before we can empower others, we have to understand leadership is not about us, it is about managing other people’s fear and expectations. Here are 10 ways we often make things all about us.</p>

<ol>
  <li>What other people experience rarely occurs to us - we’re not being curious enough</li>
  <li>We don’t ask very many questions - don’t feel the impulse to feel how other people think or feel</li>
  <li>The most interesting thing about other people is what they feel about us - you don’t have a genuine interest in other people</li>
  <li>We’re constantly keeping a tab on your own weaknesses - your inner critical voice is too loud</li>
  <li>Other people’s abilities bum us out - our primary response on seeing others excel is feeling worse about yourself</li>
  <li>We’re constantly in crisis</li>
  <li>We’re pessimistic about the future - despair is the opposite of leadership</li>
  <li>Don’t feel a sense of wonder and reality has become too tedious</li>
  <li>Apathy and powerlessness are our dominant emotions</li>
  <li>We’re the star of your own show - a leaders mission is to ensure wild success for everyone in their team and not toot their horn</li>
</ol>

<p>This is not to say that as a leader we shouldn’t have aspirations or personal goals but that they all take a backseat to the mission of the team.</p>

<h5 id="what-is-empowerment-leadership">What is empowerment leadership?</h5>

<p>Empowerment leadership is ensuring that people feel empowered to the do the right thing both in your presence and in your absence. The book visualises this as two concentric circles. The inner circle of empowerment involves trust, love and belonging and the outer circle involves strategy and culture.A lot has been written on making strategic changes to promote diversity, psychological safety and establishing a culture of accountability. Colin Doyle’s book <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-culture-code/">The Culture Code</a> addresses some of these issues.  I am going to stick to the inner circle in this post.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Trust - There are three parts to establishing trust with people around you. First is authenticity, i.e. I talk to the real you, second are you logical and third do you empathise with me and have my best interests at heart (think <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-radical-candor-part-i/#guidance">Caring Personally</a> from Radical Candor). Empowerment “wobbles” when any people you’re trying to lead, suspect any one of these as breaking down (your logic of a decision, your lack of empathy, etc). It is important to know your “wobble” and then address it.</li>
</ol>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/standards-devotion-quadrants.jpg" alt="Standards devotion quadrants" srcset="    /assets/resized/standards-devotion-quadrants-320x164.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/standards-devotion-quadrants-480x246.jpg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/02/standards-devotion-quadrants.jpg 659w" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Love - The 4 quadrants of how others experience us is shown below. On the x axis we have the devotion people feel from us towards their well being and on the y axis is the standards they feel we have set for them. Justice is the most empowering quadrant as it is the only quadrant where people feel both loved and held to high standards. People in this quadrant excel in our presence. Neglect is the worst as these are people whom we have written off and are not being challenged sufficiently. Severity is the second worst as people feel we are holding them to high standards but don’t care about them. Fidelity is when over protect people but don’t lead them to excellence by setting higher standards. The key point is we have the ability to be a leader who can both hold people to high standards and care for them deeply. Our goal as leaders should be to try and move as many people as possible from neglect, severity and fidelity to the justice quadrant.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Belonging - Building a place where bring their complete multidimensional selves to work is super hard. The scale of belonging starts from feeling safe to feeling welcome to feeling celebrated to finally the promised land of feeling cherished. There are some simple things that can be done to make a more inclusive organisation. Bring in clarity around promotions and make the criteria objective. This is especially helpful as marginalised groups often feel that there are artificial critieria that are used for majority folks. Anonymity can also often break trust. Instead of anonymous 360 degree feedback, bring it out of the shadows so there’s clear context around feedback.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h5 id="10-ways-to-raise-the-bar">10 ways to raise the bar</h5>

<p>The part I loved about this list is all this can be done in the next 24 hours by us in any organisation we work in.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Kick off a group project - Raise the collective standards and explain why the standards are what they are</li>
  <li>Celebrate a win publicly with specific praise to people who made it happen</li>
  <li>Treat someone like their better future self - Engage with the new and improved version even if they’re not there yet (may be even assign that stretch assignment you’re holding back)</li>
  <li>Put your high performers to work - Goad them to coach others</li>
  <li>Convene an after action review (AAR) - What could have been done better</li>
  <li>Set better goals - SMART or OKR</li>
  <li>Broadcast your ambitions - Find a peer or two or three to keep you honest</li>
  <li>Eliminate an inefficiency - Reduce people’s pains (easy wins). Stay humble and curious about what’s draining your team’s time</li>
  <li>Take bold action - Take immediate and meaningful action. Ideally do something you’ve never done before which surprises people who know you</li>
  <li>Be the standard - Model the standards that you want others to adopt</li>
</ol>

<h5 id="10-ways-to-show-your-committment">10 ways to show your committment</h5>

<p>Another list of 10 things we can do to show our commitment to empowering others. Again, as I’ve said before, the list is actionable and achievable in the next 24 hours.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Get rid of your phones (distractions) while in a conversation - Offer your undliuted attention to everyone you talk to</li>
  <li>Get curious about the lives - A simple “tell me about yourself” can go a long way</li>
  <li>Experience their reality - active enquiry into how they experience the world and day to day work</li>
  <li>Ask how you can help - focus on how to make it more meaningful</li>
  <li>Help proactively without expectations for return</li>
  <li>Offer snacks - I know this sounds silly but acknowledging someone’s humanity like this can be a big deal</li>
  <li>Give them a break - Sprints need time for recovery</li>
  <li>Acknowledge their presence outside work - Minimise evening and weekend work</li>
  <li>Sincere gratitude - Clear thank you notes</li>
  <li>Less me and more you - Language matters</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Business" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The book Unleashed by Frances Frei and Anne Morris is about how to lead by empowering people. Leadership is not about you, it’s about empowering other people around you both in your presence (thro trust, love and belonging) and in your absence (thro strategy and culture). My key takeaways from this book is the practical wisdom related to what I could do myself as an individual to empowerment others around me.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from The War of Art</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-the-war-of-art/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from The War of Art" /><published>2023-02-11T00:40:05+05:30</published><updated>2023-02-11T00:40:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-the-war-of-art</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-the-war-of-art/"><![CDATA[<p>The War of Art is a very popular book on creativity and productivity. The book is a collection of thoughts from the author’s experience as a writer and a creative professional. It underscores the importance of a work ethic rather than waiting for inspiration and to “sit down and get started” and sticking to the work even when things get hard. I’m writing this post to share some of the key ideas from the book.</p>

<h5 id="duel-with-resistance">Duel with Resistance</h5>

<p>The core idea of this book is that we’re on a constant battle with Resistance, the force that tries to work against us. We know it as procrastination, laziness, fear, etc. The more true or high our calling, the more resistance will block it. Here are some common ways in which we feel resistance:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Procrastination is the most common type of resistance. It tries to keep us in our comfort zone and avoid the pain of doing the work.</li>
  <li>An interesting angle in which resistance takes shape is the feeling of victimhood. It is the antithesis of doing the work. Victimhood is a way of getting attention without doing the work.</li>
  <li>Resistance often crops up disguising itself as noble or honorable. The feeling that stops us from sharing our thoughts and educating others in the name of coming across as vain or egotistical is also a type of resistance.</li>
  <li>Cheap thrills like doomscrolling, online shopping, eating sugary drinks, etc are also resistance’s work of stopping us from doing our work.</li>
  <li>Resistance doesn’t often appear as fear but as rationalisation. Instead of making us shameful by showing itself as fear, resistance throws up plausible and rational thoughts to dissuade us from doing the work.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="pro-v-amateur">Pro V Amateur</h5>

<p>The book describes in detail the difference between an Amateur and a Pro and its mostly in terms of attitude and work ethic. An Amateur does things like a hobby and out of a moderate amount of love while a Pro does it out of so much love and passion that it becomes her sole vocation. A subtle point here is to remember that the Amateur often recognises oneself too strongly with the art while the Pro knows she is much more than her vocation. The difference mostly comes down to how one reacts to resistance.</p>

<p>Being a Pro means not taking ones failures too seriously. In fact failure in the real world is a <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/bs-detection-101#look-for-assymetries-in-risk">demonstration of skin in the game</a> and knowing that one is after something real. It is like taking a few punches in the arena and not sitting on the sidelines and for that, one needs to be grateful.</p>

<p>Technically the Pro does the work for money but she also does it out of love. Working for money keeps one honest and creates a healthy detachment with the art. Resistance loves pride and this detachment keeps pride at bay.</p>

<blockquote>

  <p>Only when inspiration strikes me but it strikes me everyday at 9 am sharp</p>

  <p>– Sommerset Maugham on being asked if he writes everyday or when inspiration strikes</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A Pro enjoys being miserable, like a marine. The Pro enjoys rejection, ridicule and failure (may be not enjoy but thrives on it). Nothing is as empowering as real world feedback even when its failure.</p>

<p>Pro knows and values the <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/4000-weeks-of-life/#on-the-power-of-patience-and-anxiety">power of patience</a>.</p>

<h5 id="hierarchy-v-territory">Hierarchy V Territory</h5>

<p>In the context of doing creative work, “hierarchy” means playing to the crowds preferences while “territory” refers to being true to one’s own standards. The author underscores the importance of the tradeoffs involved in doing things for the hierarchy or territory. If the act of doing something is satisfying in and of itself then its territorial but if the real satisfaction comes from external rewards, often generated out of the crowd’s reception, it is most likely hierarchical.</p>

<p>Territory has to be earned by putting in the work like hours at the gym, working on a skill, etc. Once earned, the territory gives back. When your cranky and tired self decides to take on resistance and dives into the pool (or sit down to write), an hour later you feel refreshed. This is the territory giving back. This is another interpretation of “the high” people say they feel after running a marathon.</p>

<h5 id="the-muse">The muse</h5>

<p>One other cool idea I could relate to from the book was respecting inspiration as being something external from oneself. The idea comes from “the muse” in Greek mythology. The muses are 7 daughters of Zeus and each of them is responsible for inspiring a specific artform. The muse are supposed to be the creative force and we are just the conduits. It is something that we can’t control and we can only be grateful for it. The idea is to not be too attached to it and not be too disappointed when it doesn’t come. The idea is to be grateful for it when it does come and to be grateful for the work itself when it doesn’t. The <em>invocation of the muse</em> from The Odyssey, specifically the <a href="https://stevenpressfield.com/2019/10/a-prayer-to-the-muse/">TE Lawrence translation</a> is used by the author as a prayer before he starts working everyday.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The War of Art is a very popular book on creativity and productivity. The book is a collection of thoughts from the author’s experience as a writer and a creative professional. It underscores the importance of a work ethic rather than waiting for inspiration and to “sit down and get started” and sticking to the work even when things get hard. I’m writing this post to share some of the key ideas from the book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4000 weeks of life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/4000-weeks-of-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4000 weeks of life" /><published>2023-01-21T11:40:05+05:30</published><updated>2023-01-21T11:40:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/4000-weeks-of-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/4000-weeks-of-life/"><![CDATA[<p>In his book, “4000 weeks”, Oliver Burkeman questions our desperation behind thinking of time as a resource external to our being. The ideas in the book challenged me to think about the insecurity that comes from trying to live an ultra productive life and what fuels it. In this post I try and describe my key takeaways from this book.</p>

<h5 id="time-as-a-conveyer-belt">Time as a conveyer belt</h5>

<p>There are various analogies of time in the book but the one that stuck with me was that of a conveyer belt which is constantly running with containers that we must fill with activities. Those containers that pass us by empty are a loss. A medieval peasant was less a slave to time than us. He milked the cows when they needed milking, woke up and slept with the sun, watched a cockfight when there was one and so on. There was no external schedule to keep up with and they lived in “timelessness”.</p>

<p>The biggest problem this creates is that we think every moment is an investment for a future goal. According to the ancient Greek philosophers, accepting our “finitude” (limitations of our existence) forms the basis of living life which loosely translates to making choices knowing full well we can’t achieve everything we want in our lifetime. In other words, choosing to miss out on some things is what makes our choices meaningful.</p>

<h5 id="the-efficiency-trap">The efficiency trap</h5>

<p>There is simply no reason to try and control time as work and aspirations and needs expand to fill available time. By trying to make every passing moment productive, we only end up creating more need to be more productive. The reality of todays world is that we can never catch up with Joneses nor keep our inboxes 0 for long nor fulfill all our needs as all these goal posts keep shifting.</p>

<p>Another side effect of becoming more efficient is more people come to use us as their reliable go to person. This automatically means we get more less important or low quality stuff on our plate, which we have to weed through to get to the important stuff.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/4000-weeks-book-cover.jpeg" alt="Book cover of the book - 4000 weeks" srcset="    /assets/resized/4000-weeks-book-cover-320x491.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/4000-weeks-book-cover-480x737.jpeg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/01/4000-weeks-book-cover.jpeg 600w" /></p>

<p>Not making our peace of mind dependent on trying to be ruthlessly efficient is actually a better way to find peace of mind. For what it’s worth, I am still trying to make peace with this rather radical idea of not constantly trying to be more efficient and in fact seeking out boredom and idleness.</p>

<p>A related point that I found quite intriguing, was that of the “convenience trap”. It is when we “save time” that would have otherwise gone into a chore, through a use of a clever app or on-demand workforce, etc. This all very well but the original experience, the one that was more inconvenient or painful, was somehow more meaningful. Startups that aim to understand “pain points” or “inconvenience” and then remove them from our lives or make them easy, can often make things less meaningful.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When we render a process more convenient, we drain it of its meaning</p>
</blockquote>

<h5 id="always-settle">Always settle</h5>

<p>This was my favourite part of the book. <em>We are essentially always settling - either in choosing an option (settling for an option while a better one may be out there) or continuing to seek a better option (settling to use your limited time in pursuit of a better option rather than do something else with it)</em>. The reason we must never be afraid of settling is because it is a given. Only in our fantasy life do we find that we do our best or find the most ideal flawless partner or spend money most optimally, etc. In reality everything is finite and flawed so in comparison to our fantasy we will always fall short or fail. This should ideally liberate us 🙂</p>

<h5 id="egocentricity-bias-and-cosmic-insignificance">Egocentricity bias and cosmic insignificance</h5>

<p>Egocentricity bias is when we believe what we do is supremely more important than regular stuff that others do. It is thinking that our 4000 or so weeks are somehow instrumental and the years before were leading up to this. The reality is the univserse just doesn’t give a 💩 about us. In the larger scheme of things the whole human history happened in the blink of an eye. Taking the time to make peace with this is called the <em>Cosmic Insignificance Theory</em>. Once we make peace with the fact that we are perhaps not likely to change the world, we can find meaning in some of the things that we already do, like taking care of a relative, parenting, dog sitting for a friend, teaching the elderly couple next door how to use their new iphone, etc.</p>

<h5 id="on-the-power-of-patience-and-anxiety">On the power of patience and anxiety</h5>

<p>Anxiety comes from our urge to feel secure about future. The reason we obsess exessively over travel plans or worry about relationships is that we want certainity in these things.</p>

<p>Anxiety, however, never dies as when we finally encounter the future (imagine reaching the terminal on time and cooling your shoes) the anxiety is all in the past and new anxiety about the new impending future (will the flight reach on time, will i find a taxi cab, etc) strikes. Relief from anxiety comes from knowing that there is absolutely no assurance that the future will pan out in the one we like.</p>

<p>Patience is about exploring what lies on the other end of the loss of control over how fast things are going around us. In that sense, patience has the power to alleviate anxiety. Taking the time to let reality unfold at its own speed allows solutions to present themselves.</p>

<p>The author describes three simple ways to harness patience</p>

<ol>
  <li>Embrace having problems - life devoid of problems is meaningless. A problem is something that demands we address ourselves to it and that helps us grow.</li>
  <li>Embrace radical incrementalism - don’t ignore the impact of improving oneself in small incremements.</li>
  <li>Originality lies on the other side of unoriginality - stay on the course of learning and accumulating skills by copying and redoing what others have done. Our original work almost always arrives once we’re ready for it.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In his book, “4000 weeks”, Oliver Burkeman questions our desperation behind thinking of time as a resource external to our being. The ideas in the book challenged me to think about the insecurity that comes from trying to live an ultra productive life and what fuels it. In this post I try and describe my key takeaways from this book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wrapping up your year on Obsidian</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wrapping-up-year-obsidian/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wrapping up your year on Obsidian" /><published>2022-12-31T11:40:05+05:30</published><updated>2022-12-31T11:40:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wrapping-up-your-year-obsidian</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wrapping-up-year-obsidian/"><![CDATA[<p>The easiest way to keep oneself motivated and on track is to have some sort of visual markers that depict how far we’ve come. In this post, I try to describe a method I use to keep track of my year in Obsidian. It is inspired by the ACCESS method of organising knowledge developed by Nick Milo. I don’t follow it to the T but I use the “Atlas” concept (A in ACCESS) described by Nick, as a way to visualise my year.</p>

<h5 id="organising-notes">Organising notes</h5>

<p>There is obviously no one way to organise notes. It comes down to ones personal preferences and the kinds of notes one usually takes. I have come across two methods that seemed to make a lot of sense. The PARA method described by Tiago Forte in his book <a href="https://www.buildingasecondbrain.com/">Building a second brain</a> and the ACCESS method by <a href="https://www.linkingyourthinking.com/">Nick Milo</a>. I have tried both with varrying degrees of success. Over the last few months, I found a truncated and modified version of ACCESS method works best for me. I describe the two methods below and then go on and explain how I borrowed the concept of Atlas from Nick’s method and use it to visualise my year. Basically, both the methods are sort of ways to organise notes into some kind of a hierarchy that may help you get to what you’re looking for faster and in a way that makes sense to you. You are always essentially answering this question - this note I am writing, what folder should it go into, what other file it must link to, what tag should it carry and so on? The two methods are just different ways to answer these questions.</p>

<h6 id="para-and-access-methods">PARA and ACCESS methods</h6>

<p>The PARA method stands for</p>
<ul>
  <li><em>Projects</em> - the project this note is filed under -&gt; think projects like “Applied AI”, “VSCode extension”, “My amateur table top game” etc. If you take up a lot of side projects, organising information into projects is a good way to keep track of them.</li>
  <li><em>Area</em> - if not project, then which area -&gt; think “Notekeeping”, “ML Research”, “Bioinformatics”, etc</li>
  <li><em>Resources</em> - all external links -&gt; youtube links, articles or files</li>
  <li><em>Archive</em> - stuff completed or on hold -&gt; Archive is a good place to keep notes that you don’t want to delete but don’t want to see in your daily workflow.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/history-moc.jpg" alt="Map of contents for my History notes" srcset="    /assets/resized/history-moc-320x264.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/history-moc-480x395.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/history-moc-800x659.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/history-moc.jpg 1372w" /></p>

<p>Before I describe the ACCESS method, it makes sense to take a minute to understand the underlying concept of a Map of Contents. An MoC can be thought of as an index note that connects to other notes in the same way an index of information does. An MoC acts both as a starting point of reference (an index) and as a hub of information where related notes are available in one place. Each topic of note I take, be it a new book I am reading or a new side project I am tinkering with, has its own MoC (like the MoC for the book “Building a second brain” or my new hacking project about “Learning Elixir”) which connects to all the related notes (in case of book notes these would be individual concepts of the book or in case of a hacking side project the various elements like design spec, references, tutorials, etc).</p>

<p>Now let’s jump to the The ACCESS method.</p>
<ul>
  <li><em>Atlas</em> - map of contents or dashboards -&gt; The Atlas is a map of contents that connects to all the other MoC’s. Think of it as a meta MoC that can be used as a way to see what you’ve done in the year.</li>
  <li><em>Calendar</em> - time based information -&gt; daily notes, journals, etc</li>
  <li><em>Cards</em> - atomic notes -&gt; basically all your information should be in small atomic notes that contain nothing but the specific information you want to capture and it should connect to as many other notes as possible.</li>
  <li><em>Extra</em> - support material -&gt; attachments, templates, etc</li>
  <li><em>Sources</em> - external links -&gt; Articles, books, podcasts, etc</li>
  <li><em>Spaces</em> - big top level spaces -&gt; personal, work, school, etc</li>
</ul>

<p>Both the methods are abstractions that help you think about your information in a specific way.</p>

<h5 id="my-atlas">My Atlas</h5>

<p>I really liked the “Atlas” idea of the ACCESS method and I have adopted that to keep track of my various goals and activities through the year. Here’s how I go about it.</p>

<p>At the top level I have a folder in my vault called Atlas which has folder for every year. The 2022 folder, as shown below, contains the various maps of contents.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-folder-structure.jpg" alt="My Atlas folder structure" srcset="    /assets/resized/atlas-folder-structure-320x335.jpg 320w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-folder-structure.jpg 466w" /></p>

<p>My main categories of notes are</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hacking - this corresponds to the various hacking and programing related work I undertake in the year. My many incomplete tinkerings and side projects find their home here.</li>
  <li>History - I am a big history buff and the books I read, podcasts I listen to or documentaries I watch, become notes here.</li>
  <li>Learnings - new habits, skills, ideas, etc that I learn during the year.</li>
  <li>RJ - My son RJ is 2 years old and this keeps track of his antics, memories, activities and plans.</li>
  <li>Sikhi and I - this is where I keep track of my spiritual journey and learnings from Sikh history and religious texts</li>
  <li>Readings - this is where I keep track of the books I read and the lessons from them</li>
</ul>

<p>The 2022 Atlas file is an MoC of all these MoC’s that acts as the main dashboard that helps me keep track of what I’ve done in the year. It looks something like this.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-1.jpg" alt="Atlas file using dashboard and banner extensions" srcset="    /assets/resized/atlas-1-320x230.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/atlas-1-480x344.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/atlas-1-800x574.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-1.jpg 2288w" />
 I use the popular dashboard++ method along with the banner plugin to make it a little more presentable and pleasing to look at. You can watch the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AatZl1Z_n-g">video by Sergio </a> to see how to do it.</p>

<h5 id="automatic-references">Automatic references</h5>

<p>By keeping a track of all my new goals, readings, initiatives, etc in their respective MoC’s, I automatically keep updating my Atlas file which references these MoCs. This way I can see how my year is shaping up and make changes. You can also use the <a href="https://github.com/blacksmithgu/obsidian-dataview">Dataview plugin</a> to automatically bring up specific notes.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-2.jpg" alt="Atlas file with dataview queries" srcset="    /assets/resized/atlas-2-320x192.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/atlas-2-480x288.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/atlas-2-800x480.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-2.jpg 2234w" /></p>

<p>For example I use the #NeedsWork tag on notes that I need to work on and I can then automatically use dataview queries (code snippet below) to have them all in my Atlas file for easy reference to what I need to work on.</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$=dv.list(dv.pages('#NeedsWork').sort(f=&gt;f.file.name,"desc").limit(10).file.link)</code></p>

<p>I also keep track of all my daily reflections in one place in the Atlas so that I know how many days I have kept up this habit in the year thus far.</p>

<p>That’s all I have for now. I hope this helps you in some way. In my next post I will describe my method of keeping track of my daily reflections and how I use them to keep myself motivated and on track.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The easiest way to keep oneself motivated and on track is to have some sort of visual markers that depict how far we’ve come. In this post, I try to describe a method I use to keep track of my year in Obsidian. It is inspired by the ACCESS method of organising knowledge developed by Nick Milo. I don’t follow it to the T but I use the “Atlas” concept (A in ACCESS) described by Nick, as a way to visualise my year.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goldilocks Zones in life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/goldilocks-zones-in-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goldilocks Zones in life" /><published>2022-12-09T22:07:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-12-09T22:07:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/its-goldilocks-everywhere</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/goldilocks-zones-in-life/"><![CDATA[<p>In a Chemistry lab, for specific reactions to take place, we often need just the right kind of conditions. Not too warm, not too cold. Often it is the last drop of the reactive agent that induces the reaction. Our planet Earth too, is said to be in the perfectly right orbit, at the perfectly right distance from the Sun, has just the right chemical composition, the right amount of water, etc, to sustain life. This effect is popularly called the Goldilocks zone (alluding to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goldilocks_and_the_Three_Bears">story of the three bears</a> with three porridges of varrying degree of hotness, of three beds in different sizes, etc). The Goldilocks zone is the range of values that are just right for a particular reaction to take place.</p>

<p>It is amazing how often one comes across this effect in life.</p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-a-good-life">The Goldilocks zone of a good life</h3>

<p>A good life is also a delicate goldilocks zone. In his book The Sweet Spot, Paul Bloom talks about the Goldilocks zone of happiness. Too much of Eudaimonia (seeking a higher purpose or goal in everything we do) and it is likely to make us feel depressed. Too little Hedonia (seeking personal happiness often through material goods) and we’re left sad. We need to balance both, meaning in our pursuits and short term pleasure, for living a truly good life. He calls this <em>motivational pluralism</em> and it highlights the importance of having a variety of goals along with being present to enjoy the everyday small things.</p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-confidence">The Goldilocks zone of confidence</h3>

<p>There is a just right amount of confidence that is good for us. More, and we become jerks and a little less and we are frustrated with our lack of competence. Eric Barker, in his book, Barking up the wrong tree, argues that in theory overconfidence is worse than feeling of being incompetent as incompetent people are generally not posted in positions of power. It is also linked to the Dunning Kruger effect, where people who are incompetent at a task, overestimate their competence (primarily due to their failure in understanding the intricacies of the task).</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence.png" alt="Goldilocks Zone of Confidence" srcset="    /assets/resized/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence-320x118.png 320w,    /assets/resized/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence-480x176.png 480w,    /assets/resized/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence-800x294.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence.png 1846w" /></p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-flow">The Goldilocks zone of Flow</h3>

<p>Flow, the esoteric productivity mirage we all want to enjoy while working, also, unsurprisingly, appears in a just the right set of conditions. To define simply, flow is when you are rapt in work, challenged sufficiently, gaining mastery and making clear progress. It is when work becomes game. It, too, has a Goldilocks zone. Neither too hard nor too boring. Just like a game that is too hard to start or too easy to finish isn’t much fun, flow, too lies in the zone between skill and challenge.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/flow-skill-challenge.jpeg" alt="Flow at the right zone between Skill and Challenge" srcset="    /assets/resized/flow-skill-challenge-320x320.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/flow-skill-challenge-480x480.jpeg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/flow-skill-challenge.jpeg 640w" /></p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-give-and-take">The Goldilocks zone of give and take</h3>

<p>In his book All you have to do is ask, Wayne Baker talks about giving and receiving help. He says being overly giving can be too demanding and also lead to burnout. On the other hand, being overly selfish can lead to loneliness and depression.
Giving and receiving both are shown to be linked to mental well-being so there are benefits to both and ideally, well you guessed it, we should have just the right balance.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/giver-requestors.png" alt="Strive to become a giver requestor" srcset="    /assets/resized/giver-requestors-320x210.png 320w,    /assets/resized/giver-requestors-480x314.png 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/giver-requestors.png 800w" /></p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-an-effective-apology">The Goldilocks zone of an effective apology</h3>

<p>Timing of an apology is one of the most important aspects of it. There is a range of time when issuing an apology is effective and meaningful. One can apologise too quickly or too late. Apologise too quickly and risk being coming across as insincere and robotic. Apologise too slowly and risk coming across as unremorseful. The right time to apologise is when you have had time to reflect on your actions and have a clear understanding of the impact of your actions on the other person but not too much time that it offers little or no value to the other person.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a> about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="Human Psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a Chemistry lab, for specific reactions to take place, we often need just the right kind of conditions. Not too warm, not too cold. Often it is the last drop of the reactive agent that induces the reaction. Our planet Earth too, is said to be in the perfectly right orbit, at the perfectly right distance from the Sun, has just the right chemical composition, the right amount of water, etc, to sustain life. This effect is popularly called the Goldilocks zone (alluding to the story of the three bears with three porridges of varrying degree of hotness, of three beds in different sizes, etc). The Goldilocks zone is the range of values that are just right for a particular reaction to take place.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BS detection 101</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bs-detection-101/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BS detection 101" /><published>2022-11-12T14:07:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-11-12T14:07:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bs-detection-101</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bs-detection-101/"><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I am trying to describe 5 methods I use regularly to avoid being made a sucker. This in no way an exhaustive list, but I hope it will help you in your day to day life.</p>

<h2 id="when-it-doesnt-add-up">When it “doesn’t add up”</h2>

<p>Scott Adams, the man behind the affable Dilbert cartoon, in his book “How to fail at everything”, described his BS detection method as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li>See if what you’re hearing matches your own personal experience.</li>
  <li>Does any scientific data back the claims being made?</li>
  <li>Does your friends’ experience or experience of those you know match the claims being made?</li>
  <li>Does common sense agree with it?</li>
  <li>Finally, what do the experts in the field say about it?</li>
</ol>

<p>Shoot for consistencies across these parameters to evaluate if something is true or fiction. For example, if you read a study that says eating chocolate cake helps in weight loss and your personal experience and friends’ experience suggests otherwise plus common sense that eating high caloric food cannot lead to weight loss, you can say with some surety that it’s BS.</p>

<h2 id="look-for-assymetries-in-risk">Look for assymetries in risk</h2>

<p>This is the easiest strategy to detect BS when it comes to financial matters. Usually comes in handy when you’re being sold financial planning or asset management. If you detect that by conducting the business in the manner presented, the other party stands to risk a lot less (usually 0) in comparison to you, that’s the moment to rethink things.</p>

<p>This is also often called the agency cost, ie. the cost we incur by relying on authority figures or experts who have no “skin in the game” by doing their business (ex: managing our assets). For optimum results, their incentives must be aligned with ours. If you lose money, they should too. If you hurt yourself, they should suffer as well. The technical term for this is “moral hazard”  - where the risk taker is immune to the effects of her actions.</p>

<h2 id="complicated-statistics-or-data">Complicated statistics or data</h2>

<p>In business and in life, always choose simplicity. Whenever you find yourself at the receiving end of a series of complicated statistics, it’s a red flag. The more complicated the data, the more likely it is to be manipulated or cherry picked to suit a particular narrative. Always spend some time going over the data in an open minded fashion while also asking for more data that may be related and that may help you make the decision. Always remember, “what you see is not all there is”.</p>

<h2 id="use-of-compliance-techniques">Use of compliance techniques</h2>

<p>Bob Cialdini, in his seminal book <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-robert-cialdinis-influence/">Influence</a>, described a series of influencing techniques used by people who gain something from getting you to comply to their seemingly inoccuous requests. He called these people “compliance practioners” - you can imagine them all to be car salesmen.</p>

<p>Look out for these 6 techniques.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Pretending to be like you by saying they have friends in the same city or grew up in your part of world. We all like people like us and this gives them an edge.</li>
  <li>Anchoring you to a higher price to move your baseline and getting you to overspend. The most common example is a realtor showing you two bad properties and then the one they want to sell you.</li>
  <li>Offering you free food or samples to trigger your reciprocity drive (it’s way too powerful) and get you to buy something.</li>
  <li>Telling you about other people you know who did business with them and give you social proof that they are reliable and trustworthy.</li>
  <li>Proclaiming support of “experts” (who may not even be real experts or even if they are, they are usually paid to do it). The most common example of this is people pretending to be dentists appearing on toothpaste ads on TV.</li>
  <li>Getting you to create a self image for yourself in your mind. Once a self image is created, you are forced to remain consistent with it by doing things you may not otherwise do. Imagine walking down the street and someone asks you if you care about the environment. You say yes and they pull out a donation form for an environmental charity. You will be forced to donate to the charity.</li>
</ol>

<p>These can all be used in combination as well so be on the lookout for when more than one of them is being employed together.</p>

<h2 id="looking-the-part">Looking the part</h2>

<p>Taleb, in his book, Skin in the game, described how appearances can persuade us. We all want our doctors to “look the part”. They should be refined and polished and should “look like a doctor”. Taleb argues that if looks are so persuasive, then it probably means that we should strive to find a doctor who doesn’t look like a doctor. The logic is that if, they don’t look the part, and yet are still where they are, then they must be really good as they have overcome the bias against them. This is counter intuitive but seems to make sense once you start thinking how biases work and how other people perceive you.</p>

<p>To be honest this one isn’t something I have been able to avoid yet. I still prefer my doctor to look like a polished doctor, my financial advisor to wear a suit and my restaurants by how clean its glass windows are and how well lit it is. But I am trying to be more open minded about this.</p>

<p><em>More on this list as I make more BS detection rules.</em></p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a> about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this post, I am trying to describe 5 methods I use regularly to avoid being made a sucker. This in no way an exhaustive list, but I hope it will help you in your day to day life.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Algorithms for life - 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Algorithms for life - 2" /><published>2022-10-16T12:07:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-10-16T12:07:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-2/"><![CDATA[<p>In my last post <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/algorithms-for-life-part-1/">part 1 of Algorithms for life</a>, I discussed some learnings from the book
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Algorithms-to-Live-By-audiobook/dp/B01D24NAL6/ref=sr_1_1?crid=56G25J7CEAT3&amp;keywords=algorithms+to+live+by&amp;qid=1664875020&amp;qu=eyJxc2MiOiIyLjA0IiwicXNhIjoiMS42MyIsInFzcCI6IjEuNzQifQ%3D%3D&amp;sprefix=algorithms+to+live+by%2Caps%2C1282&amp;sr=8-1">Algorithms to live by</a>. This post is the continuation of the same. Let’s jump right into it.</p>

<h3 id="probability-in-life">Probability in life</h3>

<p>This is one of the meaty parts of the book. Life is filled with probabilistic occurances and those who can navigate uncertainity, generally live a much more fulfilling life. The book discusses Bayes theorem which is about using “priors” or existing knowledge about a given situation to make predictions about the future. I have discussed Baye’s theorem in detail in my post on my post on <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-thinking-fast-slow-part-1/">Thinking fast &amp; slow</a>.</p>

<p>The Laplace’s law can be used to make general predictions after a series of observations. Imagine having to predict the percentage of overall winning tickets in a lottery after seeing how many tickets won in the latest 10 draws. The law states that the probability of a winning ticket is the number of winning tickets in the last 10 draws plus 1, divided by the total number of tickets drawn plus 1.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>(w+1)/(n+1)
where <em>w</em> is the number of winning tickets and <em>n</em> is the total number of tickets drawn.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So if in the first 10 draws, there were 2 winners, the probability of a winning ticket in the next draw is 3/11. This is a very simple example but it can be used to make predictions in a lot of situations.</p>

<p>Another interesting principle to internalise is the Copernican principle (also known as the Lindy effect) which formalises the intuition that old is gold. Something that has been around for x years, is likely to continue to stay around for x more years. This principle was used in World War II to estimate how many tanks the Germans were producing every month by looking at the VIN numbers of the tanks found by the Allies.</p>

<p>Finally, one of the most important concepts in probability is the distributions that surround us. A distribution describes the likelihood of occurances in a group setup. Normal distribution or the bell curve distribution, has more occurances in the centre. You can make average predictions and be right most of the time, for example, someone at the median age is likely to live more than someone who is very near the extremes of the curve. Power law distributions are in which events are not normal and most items are not clustered around the average but lie in some specific extremes. Events like box office earnings, venture capital returns, etc, follow the power law. The book also discusses Erlang distributions which can be thought of as an intermediate between normal and power law distributions, where the tails are fatter than normal but not as fat as power law distributions. In events following erlang distributions the predictions can be constant. For example, the number of people who will show up at a party is likely to be constant or the amount of time people spend on a call is likely to be constant. Erlang distributions are also used in call centres to estimate the number of agents required to handle a given number of calls.</p>

<h3 id="overfitting">Overfitting</h3>

<p>Overfitting is when we try to fit a model to a given situation and end up making it too complex. In life too, we tend to overthink and develop a complicated understanding of what’s happening around us. In reality, truth is often far too simple. Overfitting is a common problem in machine learning and the way to avoid it, is to add a regularisation parameter which penalises the model for being too complex. In life, we can use the same principle to avoid overfitting. We can use the principle of Occam’s razor to avoid overfitting. Occam’s razor states that the simplest explanation is the most likely to be true. This is a very powerful principle to keep in mind. This probably also explains our evolutionary wiring of heuristics and our inhrent fast thinking.</p>

<h3 id="a-bit-of-randomness-goes-a-long-way">A bit of randomness goes a long way</h3>

<p>Taleb has written extensively about how to avoid being fooled by randomness and also how to build yourself to thrive in uncertainity. This book discusses an interesting concept of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simulated_annealing">annealing</a> which is a process of letting a system warm up (introducing randomness) and then cool down (perform optimisations like hill climbing to reach a local maxima) and doing these regularly to hit what seems like a global maxima. This technique was used by the authors of this famous paper to design chips with more transistors than other known techniques of the time.</p>

<p>Introducing a bit of randomness can be used to break stale mates and direct us towards more creative solutions. <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/team-playbook/plays/disruptive-brainstorming#instructions">Disruptive brainstorming</a> sessions, like the one described by Atlassian, are quite popular where random concepts are introduced to direct the participants to incorporate them in their ideas, often leading to novel innovations.</p>

<p>One other advantage of randomness is using it to create algorithms like Bloom filters that us to be somewhat sure of our solution quickly rather than seek out the perfectly optimal solution everytime. Contrary to common belief, this is quite preferable in many situations like cyber security.</p>

<h3 id="game-theory-in-action">Game theory in action</h3>

<p>Game theory is a deep field that studies how people interact in different situations. Looked at through this lens, almost all interactions are games with each player looking to maximise their payoffs. The famous prisoners dillema is a game where two players are put in a situation where they can either cooperate or defect. If both players cooperate, they both get a payoff of 3. If both defect, they both get a payoff of 1. If one player defects and the other cooperates, the defector gets a payoff of 5 and the cooperator gets a payoff of 0. In this situation defecting is the optimal strategy for both players. The book discusses how this game is played in real life and how it can be used to make predictions about how people will behave in different situations.</p>

<p>Price of anarchy is the difference between the payoffs arising due to the “always defect” and “always hold out”, i.e. 100% competitive and 100% cooperative strategies in a prisoners dillemma like game. A low price of anarchy means the system is stable and doesn’t need a managing centralised authority. A high price of anarchy on the other hand, like the one described in the prisoner’s dillema above, requires external intervention. The book discusses how the price of anarchy can be used to predict the stability of a system and also to design mechanisms around us. The classic problem of tragedy of commons. The profits from overgrazing common land accrue to you alone while the losses, get amortized over everyone. This is a classic case of a high price of anarchy.</p>

<p>Mechanism design is the reverse of game theory. It is utilising our knowledge of equilibriums and creating a game where the equilibrium is beneficial for all the players. Imagine in the prisoners dillemma there is a Godfather of a crime syndicate that bans defection in jails (or else the accused sleeps with the fish). This will move the equilibrium from always defect to always hold out.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a> about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my last post part 1 of Algorithms for life, I discussed some learnings from the book Algorithms to live by. This post is the continuation of the same. Let’s jump right into it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Algorithms for life - 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Algorithms for life - 1" /><published>2022-10-04T14:07:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:07:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-1/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Algorithms-to-Live-By-audiobook/dp/B01D24NAL6/ref=sr_1_1?crid=56G25J7CEAT3&amp;keywords=algorithms+to+live+by&amp;qid=1664875020&amp;qu=eyJxc2MiOiIyLjA0IiwicXNhIjoiMS42MyIsInFzcCI6IjEuNzQifQ%3D%3D&amp;sprefix=algorithms+to+live+by%2Caps%2C1282&amp;sr=8-1">Algorithms to live by</a> is the first book that I read again, right after finishing it. It is filled with practical wisdom and connects real life problems with computing and mathematical theory. In this post and the next, I will try to summarise my key takeaways from the book.</p>

<h3 id="knowing-when-to-stop">Knowing when to stop</h3>

<p>We encounter scenarios in life when we don’t know when is the right time to stop looking for solutions. Think situations like driving through a parking lane while looking for a spot. If you stop and park at the first empty stop, you may have to walk a long way but if you keep looking for a stop closer to the destination, you might miss out on a spot altogether. Mathematically speaking, these situations are called <em>optimal stopping</em> problems. The optimal solution of this problem dictates that you can stop after having looked at 37% of your available options and then go with when you find an option that beats all the others you’ve seen before.</p>

<p>For the first 37% of the time or options, you’re only looking and gathering information (creating a baseline). In some cases the available options could be in the form of time you’ve set to look for a parking. So if you plan on spending 10 mins looking for a spot, spend the first 4 minutes simply exploring the lot and then pick the first one that beats all the previous spots (beat here means matches your criteria best).</p>

<h3 id="balancing-searching-and-sorting">Balancing searching and sorting</h3>

<p>Sorting is arranging items in a certain predefined order so it becomes easier to find a specific item. Like with anything, sorting takes effort and time and this time is well spent if we eventually use the sorted dataset to search for an item. In that sense, sorting and searching are tradeoffs on time. Which algorithm to employ to organise your files, wardrobe or pictures, depends on your specific retrieval needs and it makes sense to spend time thinking about organisation as it will save you time in the long run.</p>

<p>Similarly, in nature, a pecking order can be thought of as a sorting algorith. The objective of this ordering is to make it effortless (read: bloodless) to determine who is dominant in any given situation. Even basic societal rules like respecting your elders, nature’s hierarchies in the wild, basic maritime laws like gross tonnage, etc, are ways of managing the same tradeoff of sort v search.</p>

<h3 id="caching-and-memory">Caching and memory</h3>

<p>Just as sorting allows for faster search, our memory is dependent on how information is organised so it can aid faster retrieval. We have infinite capacity for storing memories but can only spend a finite time searching for memories. Forgetting something, is thus, similar to a cache, an organisation problem 🤯</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/folders.jpg" alt="file used recently goes to the left" srcset="    /assets/resized/folders-320x288.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/folders-480x433.jpg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/10/folders.jpg 800w" />
File used recently goes to the leftmost slot</p>

<p>Something recently used is more likely to be used again and thus must be kept closest to us. The weird looking filing trays we see in some offices, may actually be a smart way to prioritise stuff. The file you used most recently goes back to the leftmost tray and the other ones slide right. That’s it. That’s the algorithm right there.</p>

<p>Since you are likely to need something you used most recently, always go for the left most tray to look for it. This is the Noguchi filing system and it is a real world physical adaptation of the least recently used cache.</p>

<h3 id="scheduling-in-real-life">Scheduling in real life</h3>

<p>There are many different metrics to optimise when it comes to what we should work on. Sometimes the goal is to minimise overall lateness (unit - time, like in case of managing your washer and dryer), sometimes it is to minimise the number of late tasks (unit - number, consuming rotting produce in the fridge in some order) and sometimes it is to reduce the overall waiting time for someone blocked on us (clients who have given us several tasks). Each metric demands its own strategy. The goal must be to balance the different kinds of metrics. For example <em>responsiveness</em> and <em>throughput</em>. Your customer support team may need to be responsive so that your engineers can have throughput and so on.</p>

<p>Sometimes it may just be prudent to get the easiest thing done and out of the way and sometimes it may make sense to spend time to pick the most consequential item and do it first (to reduce the wait of the task with the highest importance/time ). This sounds like a good one size fit-most approach for most scheduling problems.</p>

<p>A common problem emanating from this is <em>thrashing</em>. There is always a fixed bookkeeping cost, no matter what kinds of tasks you have on your plate. When a juggler is given one more ball than he can manage, he doesn’t just drop that ball but all other balls. When tasks steal resources from each other or remove the meta work done by another task to do its own meta work, it is called Thrashing.</p>

<p>Another important concept that comes in handy is <em>interrupt coalescing</em>. This is when you wait for similar tasks to accumulate and do them all at once to save time on bookkeeping each individual task of the same kind. It also saves <em>context switching</em>, which is the time and energy that gets spent on moving from one kind of task to another. Imagine getting interrupted to answer a question while you’re in the middle of writing an email to placate a customer. It takes time to think of the answer, actually answer and then get back to writing the email. The idea therefore must be to minimise interruptions, so you can get all the tasks of one kind done in one go and then move on to the next kind.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a> about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Algorithms to live by is the first book that I read again, right after finishing it. It is filled with practical wisdom and connects real life problems with computing and mathematical theory. In this post and the next, I will try to summarise my key takeaways from the book.]]></summary></entry></feed>