<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-12T14:47:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Infermuse</title><subtitle>Practical wisdom from studies, experiments and books</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Different kinds of failures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/different-kinds-of-failures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Different kinds of failures" /><published>2023-12-12T12:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-12-12T12:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/different-kinds-of-failures</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/different-kinds-of-failures/"><![CDATA[<p>The popular Silicon Valley mantra <em>Fail Fast, Fail Often</em> is often misunderstood. The idea is not to repeatedly fail until one gets it right. In fact it alludes to a very specific kind of failure, one that is <em>fast</em> and <em>cheap</em> and reveals something new and interesting. This is the right kind of failure Silicon Valley is obsessed with. In her book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Right-Kind-Wrong-Science-Failing/dp/1982195061/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3DTAOI07DCH1B&amp;keywords=right+kind+of+wrong&amp;qid=1702372354&amp;sprefix=right+kind+of+%2Caps%2C607&amp;sr=8-1">The Right Kind of Wrong</a>, Amy Edmondson, a professor at Harvard Business School, talks about the differences between good failures and bad failures. This is the part one of a two part series on lessons from this book. This post is about the different kinds of failures and why one is better than the other. In the next post, I will talk about how to create a culture of psychological safety that encourages good failures.</p>

<h3 id="basic-failures">Basic failures</h3>

<p>Basic failures are common everyday errors that happen due to oversight, neglect, inattention, forgetfulness, faulty assumptions based on poor logic or scant evidence and distraction that comes with modern life. Basic failures are unproductive, a drain on energy and resources and are the farthest away from the kind of failure we all want to encourage.</p>

<p>At this juncture it is perhaps important to look at failures in a spectrum. The infograhic below talks about a spectrum of failures. The left side of the spectrum is where basic failures lie and the right side is where intelligent failures lie. The failures on the left side are blameworthy while those on the right side are praiseworthy. Worth mentioning that almost all the failures we encounter in our work or personal life lie somewhere in the middle of the spectrum.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/failure_spectrum.jpg" alt="A spectrum of failures" srcset="    /assets/resized/failure_spectrum-320x96.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/failure_spectrum-480x144.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/failure_spectrum-800x240.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/12/failure_spectrum.jpg 2000w" /></p>

<p>Avoiding these kinds of failures is relatively easy and requires processes and systems. Some ways one can avoid basic failures are stated below.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Utilizing Checklists and Standardization: Seasoned professionals, such as pilots, adhere to meticulous checklists and standardized procedures prior to every flight, ensuring the aircraft’s optimal functionality. In Atul Gawande’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Checklist-Manifesto-How-Things-Right-ebook/dp/B0030V0PEW/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3N2TYV0P77ZZ4&amp;keywords=checklist+manifesto&amp;qid=1702372463&amp;s=digital-text&amp;sprefix=checklist+mani%2Cdigital-text%2C290&amp;sr=1-1">Checklist Manifesto</a>, the transformative impact of checklists in the medical field is emphasized, leading to enhanced performance, decreased errors, and lives saved. However, it’s crucial to acknowledge that checklists have their limits.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Cultivating a Safety-Centric Culture: Elevating the pursuit of excellence into a habit entails an unwavering commitment to meticulous attention to detail. By bringing safety front and center, one ensures that all possible precautions are taken to avoid basic failures that could lead to accidents or injuries.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fostering a Culture of Blameless Reporting: Encouraging employees to openly communicate adverse events and issues without fear of repercussions is paramount. Establishing your version of the “Andon Cord,” akin to Toyota’s approach, reinforces transparency as non-punitive and incentivizes the free exchange of information regarding errors and their solutions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Proactive Maintenance: Overcoming the challenge of “Temporal Discounting,” which leads us to prioritize immediate concerns over future potential problems, is essential. Regular, routine maintenance exerts a disproportionately significant impact on the mitigation of fundamental failures.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Mandatory Training Programs: Ensuring that all personnel possess a comprehensive understanding of equipment, coding, or any relevant subject matter is indispensable. Continuously updating training modules based on past errors ensures a state-of-the-art skill set.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Implementing Poka-Yoke Principles: The concept of “poka-yoke,” or error-proofing, involves designing systems to prevent, rectify, or highlight errors as they occur. It’s akin to childproofing your furniture or medicine bottles, effectively eliminating unexpected surprises or blunders.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The reason basic failures are helpful is that they are a good way to practice learning from past mistakes and getting used to the emotional discomfort one feels about failures.</p>

<h3 id="complex-failures">Complex failures</h3>

<p>Cumulative small issues can culminate in complex failures, similar to basic failures, and typically occur in familiar environments. Complex failures are influenced by various internal and external factors, such as increasing distractions and the overconfidence that repetition can bring. Interconnectedness, exemplified during the COVID-19 pandemic, also plays a significant role.</p>

<p>Interactive complexity emerges when multiple systems collaborate, making it challenging to predict the consequences of a minor error or change in one system. Perrow extensively explores this concept in “Normal Accidents.” In today’s world, disasters are more likely to occur when systems are tightly interconnected and their interactions are intricate. The diagram below shows how interactive complexity and tight coupling can lead to complex failures.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/new_perrow.jpg" alt="Perrow described this interconnectedness failure in his book Normal Accidents" srcset="    /assets/resized/new_perrow-320x287.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/new_perrow-480x430.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/new_perrow-800x717.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/12/new_perrow.jpg 908w" /></p>

<p>A way to understand complex failures is the swiss cheese model. Just as in a swiss cheese there are holes which often line up to create a hole that goes through the entire cheese, similarly in complex failures, multiple small failures line up to create a big failure. Visualising a complex system like a piece of swiss cheese reminds us of the role of chance. Error will always be with us but we can design systems that notice them and stop them.</p>

<p>Much like basic failures, mitigating complex failures necessitates a proactive approach and learning from past mistakes. However, the complexity of the systems involves not downplaying the role of chance and luck.</p>

<h3 id="intelligent-failures">Intelligent failures</h3>

<p>An intelligent failure is the kind that all want to encourage as it sheds light on new and interesting things. Intelligent failures or smart failures happen in a setting where there’s a lot of analytical or scientific work involved. In a typical lab, the failure rates could be as high as 70% and only these kinds of failures should be celebrated. Intelligent failure occurs as a part of what you believe to be a meaningful opportunity towards a valued goal and getting the right answer is not the only valued goal.</p>

<p>How to tell if a failure is intelligent? Here are 5 quick questions that can help you arrive at the answer.</p>

<ul>
  <li>New territory - do people already know how to get this done some other way?</li>
  <li>Opportunity driven - is there an opportunity worth pursuing and the goal valuable?</li>
  <li>Informed by prior knowledge - has the required homework been done and a thoughtful hypothesis formulated?</li>
  <li>As cheap as possible - has the risk been mitigated through a well designed experiment?</li>
  <li>Bonus - have all the lessons been mined from the failure and the knowledge shared?</li>
</ul>

<p>One of the key tenets of smart failures is it happens when the team posseses a growth mindset. A growth mindset, defined by Carol Dweck, is the belief that one’s abilities can be developed through dedication and hard work. A fixed mindset, on the other hand, is the belief that one’s abilities are innate and cannot be changed. A growth mindset is characterised by the curiosity to learn what went wrong and a willingness to go through the pain of looking back in the failure to learn. A fixed mindset is characterised by the fear of looking back and the pain of admitting that one was wrong.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Business" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The popular Silicon Valley mantra Fail Fast, Fail Often is often misunderstood. The idea is not to repeatedly fail until one gets it right. In fact it alludes to a very specific kind of failure, one that is fast and cheap and reveals something new and interesting. This is the right kind of failure Silicon Valley is obsessed with. In her book The Right Kind of Wrong, Amy Edmondson, a professor at Harvard Business School, talks about the differences between good failures and bad failures. This is the part one of a two part series on lessons from this book. This post is about the different kinds of failures and why one is better than the other. In the next post, I will talk about how to create a culture of psychological safety that encourages good failures.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How physical craft enriches us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/physical-craft-enriches/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How physical craft enriches us" /><published>2023-11-26T09:17:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-11-26T09:17:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-physical-craft-enriches-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/physical-craft-enriches/"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a collection of lessons from the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Shop-Class-Soulcraft-Inquiry-Value/dp/0143117467/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=shop+class+as+soulcraft&amp;qid=1700973675&amp;sr=8-1">Shop Class as Soulcraft</a>, by Matthew Crawford, on how physical craft enriches us. He defines Craftsmanship as being the desire to do things as well as you can for its own sake and goes on to explain how we have degraded craftsmanship in recent times. It is a fascinating read that underscores that the physical world is not just a distraction from the real world but is the real world. The book reviews the modern day understanding of work and how we, as a society, have come to value certain types of work over others. In this post I try to summarise the key ideas from the book.</p>

<h3 id="useful-arts">Useful arts</h3>

<p>We often associate plumbing, fitting electrical appliances or motorcycle maintenance with something mundane, when in reality these are one of the most useful arts. These are the arts that make the world go round. People practising these useful arts in reality are often leading much more meaningful lives than we would care to accept. Manual work like plumbing needs a lot of systematic encounter with the material world and is cognitively enriching. The fact that old items rust and deteriorate means a repairman needs to apply practical experience along with theoretical guidelines to fix an item (which for ex may break due to rust or simply usage based wear and tear). They don’t simply read a manual and execute a set of instructions as the manual cannot and does not cover every possible scenario. In a way they are the true persuers of knowledge as without learning through hands, the world remains distant and true learning remains at bay.</p>

<p>Manual craftsmen like mechanics or plumbers, often have a more tightly knit social life. They share tools, knowledge, often times even customers. They are also more likely to be self employed and thus have a more direct relationship with their customers. They are also more likely to be in a position to say no to a customer if they don’t like the customer. This is in stark contrast to the modern day office worker who is often a cog in a wheel and has little control over their work.</p>

<h3 id="thinking-vs-doing">Thinking vs doing</h3>

<p>The degradation of manual work began with scientific management which began with Frederik Winslow Taylor’s management theories (whose fans included Stalin and many B school professors). The cognitive parts of manufacturing were slowly moved away from the shop floor to a management office. The primary intention was not efficiency but cost. Once a mechanical activity becomes a piece of a process with little or no cognitive requirement, a skilled worker can be replaced by an unskilled one. Thus, craft knowledge dies out. This is also called the abstraction of labor. This draining off of cognitive requirements from a job isn’t limited to blue collar work, desk jobs, traditionally thought of to be knowledge work, are also going through an abstraction, which the author calls, a rising boats of clerkdom.</p>

<p>In essence, the dichotomy is not between manual work and knowledge work, it is between work that is meaningful and work that isn’t. We have grown to like sitting on a desk and doing work that does not require physical labour but design plans that someone else, often lower down in the hierarchy, will execute. This is a sort of a moral hazard. We have grown to like the idea of being a manager rather than a worker. This is also called the Peter Principle and is best summarised by the quote “In a hierarchy, every employee tends to rise to his level of incompetence”. The world has shifted from production of goods (which has moved elsewhere) to the marketing of brands.</p>

<p>College graduates often look for specific jobs that pay less than blue collar manual jobs, for the sake of looking for “knowledge work”. This can often mean that the college educated are psychically incapable of taking manual jobs and instead prefer taking up paper pushing cubicle jobs that don’t have a clear objective threshold for quality (other than grammar). That we submit our youth to such jobs that are more prone to the overall production of low quality, is unacceptable and detrimental to our long term well being.</p>

<p>Fixing or working on real world things brings intrinsic joy. Good teachers love students and want them to become the best version of theirselves. Similarly, most good mechanics love cars. There is a certain kind of pride that comes with working on a national brand like Rolls Royce but that joy can get diminished if the parts belonging to the car can come from anywhere in the world.</p>

<h3 id="finding-joy-in-fixing-things">Finding joy in fixing things</h3>

<p>Being able to repair things requires of us to think of what a machine needs rather than what we need. In a way, this suspends our narcissistic way of living and consider what the world around us needs. As I wrote before, the dichotomy is not whether a job is manual or not, it is whether a job is meaningful or not. Being self reliant is a liberating feeling and agency driven autonomy is directly linked to happiness. The fact that people want to take up knitting or grow their own mushrooms is in a way descriptive of how further we’ve gone away from our work and how we, in our soul, want to gain some more agency and responsibility of our things.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/iron_man.jpg" alt="Iron Man talks to the tractor like its a person" srcset="    /assets/resized/iron_man-320x177.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/iron_man-480x266.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/iron_man-800x443.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/11/iron_man.jpg 2034w" />
<em>Iron Man in Avengers, talks to a tractor like its a person</em></p>

<p>The reason we don’t fix our own stuff is because of harped on notion of opportunity cost but in reality, the pride we feel after being curious and getting our hands dirty far outweighs the loss in opportunity cost. This opportunity cost nonsense is based on the fungibility of human experience. That any activity can be boiled down in terms of the seconds on the clock, is wrong. To fix ones own car is not to use up time but rather to have a different experience of time, self and car. Things now a days are being made so as to encourage us not to tinker with them. This is driven by economics, globalisation but also by changing behaviours of consumerism. A good example of this is people playing musical instruments far less now and listen to music on stereo more. Instruments require effort to master while stereo makes music instantly available. Art requires human engagement v a device that requires consumption.</p>

<h3 id="ethics-and-cognition">Ethics and cognition</h3>

<p>Degrading of work in the way of not getting things repaired or the economics of factory stuff being cheaper but also of less quality, has directly led to moral degradation. The world now pays less attention to the craft and its economic effects are there for everyone to see. It is quite normal today for one to walk to a garrage and find mechanics spending less time looking for faults or fixing rather than replacing parts. This is because the economics of replacing parts is better than fixing them. This throwaway culture persists because we don’t have the patience to listen to the machine tell us of what ails it. We make snap judgements because we don’t care about the machine enough. This is a moral failure. The author also speaks about the service manual as a social technology and talks about a world where the manuals were pieces of art, written to be read and understood by everyone who wanted to not only use the machine but also to fix it. This is in stark contrast to the modern day manuals that are written more out of legal reasons. This is also a type of moral failure that feeds into the throwaway culture.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="Book Reviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is a collection of lessons from the book Shop Class as Soulcraft, by Matthew Crawford, on how physical craft enriches us. He defines Craftsmanship as being the desire to do things as well as you can for its own sake and goes on to explain how we have degraded craftsmanship in recent times. It is a fascinating read that underscores that the physical world is not just a distraction from the real world but is the real world. The book reviews the modern day understanding of work and how we, as a society, have come to value certain types of work over others. In this post I try to summarise the key ideas from the book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Managing creative blocks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/managing-creative-blocks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing creative blocks" /><published>2023-11-05T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-11-05T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/managing-creative-blocks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/managing-creative-blocks/"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a collection of lessons from the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Anatomy-Breakthrough-Unstuck-When-Matters/dp/B0BDT8K3DC/ref=sr_1_1?crid=7I71RTSJHCQC&amp;keywords=anatomy+of+a+breakthrough&amp;qid=1699159167&amp;sprefix=anatomy+of+a+break%2Caps%2C360&amp;sr=8-1">Anatomy of a Breakthrough</a>, by Adam Alter, on understanding why we get stuck and how to get unstuck. It is a fascinating read that underscores that getting stuck is a virtual certainty in creative endeavours and that there are ways to get unstuck. The book is a collection of stories of breakthroughs and how they came about. It is a great read and I highly recommend it.</p>

<h3 id="why-being-stuck-is-so-common">Why being stuck is so common</h3>

<p>Let’s start by defining what can be considered as “being stuck”. The author says you’re stuck if you find yourself in one or more of these three situations.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Temporarily unable to make progress in a domain that matters to you</li>
  <li>Fixed in place for too long enough to feel psychological discomfort</li>
  <li>Existing habits and strategies aren’t solving the problem</li>
</ol>

<p>One of the most common reasons we get stuck is due to the motiovation problem we encounter near the middle of any pursuit. <em>Clark Hull</em> in the 1930s found that rats in a maze would run faster as they got closer to the goal. The same thing happens with us. Our propensity to quit gradually declines as we get nearer the goal. Often times the rats begin fast, slow down and then speed up as they get to the end. Slowing down or getting stuck near the middle is very common. This is often called the goal gradient effect. One way to counter this middle lull is to break down a larger goal into smaller goals and adopt a <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/notes-from-clearer-closer-better/"><em>Narrow Focus</em></a>. The smaller goals should be somewhat significant themselves like breaking down a 30 mile marathon into 10 chunks of 3 mile each. This way you can celebrate the smaller wins and keep the motivation going.</p>

<p>Transitioning between decades also affect us. 9 ending ages make us more introspective and we tend to evaluate our lives more. The commonly used trope of <em>mid life crisis</em> is real and linked to the point discussed above. Bruce Feiler calls these Lifequakes.</p>

<p>Another common reason we all get stuck is repeated use of same techniques and strategies that have become obsolete or ineffective. Even the best strategies need improvements from time to time. It makes sense to have many irons in the fire so a loss of one or two doesn’t matter all that much but they should be in different stages of germination from a seed to almost a tree.</p>

<p>Finally, we all underestimate persistence. Mental difficulty is a sign of progress. The creative cliff one feels is an illusion and your creative capacity doesn’t erode with time or effort. Persistence is hard primarily because we equate mental difficulty with failure. Creativity is hard because we live and experience the same cultural norms and face the same boundaries and it is difficult to escape those same ideas around us. This is called convergent evolution by which bats, birds and butterflies all evolved to have similar wings structures.</p>

<h3 id="dealing-with-the-emotional-aspect-of-being-stuck">Dealing with the emotional aspect of being stuck</h3>

<p>Being stuck makes you feel anxiety and lonely. Here are 5 ways you can deal with the emotional stress of being stuck.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Framing being stuck as a challenge rather than a threat can bring us out of the rut. Threat seems definitive while challenge can bring out the best of us and also seems to assure us that even if we fail today, we can come out again and  go for it tomorrow.</li>
  <li>Visualising or <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/notes-from-clearer-closer-better/"><em>Materialising</em></a> is important but also radical acceptance, i.e. visualise the worst case of failure and realising there’s a life on that side as well. This is also known to relieve pressure and anxiety.</li>
  <li>Satisficing to make peace with a good enough choice rather than continuing to optimise and chasing perfectionism. Perfectionism is seeking romcom worthy relationships and sitcom worthy friendships. It’s unreal and exhausting.</li>
  <li>Slow down and prepare. Messi prepares his mental map of the field and the players and their strengths and weaknesses in the first few minutes of his game, and its only after the first few minutes of <em>walking the field</em> that he gets into his groove. Sometime getting unstuck is about slowing down rather than speeding up.</li>
  <li>There is an optimum failure rate, a sort of sweet spot of toughness of a problem that makes for best learning. An error rate that is too high will discourage you from carrying on and too low will make you feel disengaged quickly. The optimum failure rate allows you to emotionally fail more easily.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="tips-to-get-unstuck">Tips to get unstuck</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Do a Friction audit to find points of friction as those are likely to get you stuck. Similar to how one finds and fixes drop off points in a customer experience funnel, one must try and find points of friction in life that are likely to get one stuck. For example if its too cold outside, may be you need a treadmill at home to make it easy for you to workout everyday. You can even add friction points like not storing junk food in the fridge to discourage yourself from a habit. This is linked to the idea of <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-atomic-habits/">Environment Design</a> concept discussed in Atomic Habits.</li>
  <li>Use formula based approaches containing predefined structures to get unstuck. For example <a href="https://gizmodo.com/the-22-rules-of-storytelling-according-to-pixar-5916970">Emma Coats’ 22 rules of storytelling</a> lists some ways to get you out of a rut, for ex
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> rule 4 - some templates like once upon a time .. x then x because x and then x
 rule 6 - challenging characters with hardships..
 rule 5 - simplify and lose
 rule 9 - what cannot happen next can lead to some interesting insights
 rule 11 - put it all on paper
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Add more automation to life so as to avoid dissipating mental energies and simplifying things and avoid getting stuck.</li>
  <li>Adding constraints or getting inside the box can also be a simplification technique that helps you get more creative and think differently. It was seen that in a team containing a star player, people often passed the ball to the star player more often than other players and thus the team as a whole became more predictable.</li>
  <li>Recombination or getting inspired by other ideas is a great way to avoid being stuck. Striving to do something entirely original puts immense pressure on you. Success can come from a well placed tweak.</li>
  <li>Pivoting involves <em>Holding an idea like you would a small bird</em>. It should be tight enough that it doesn’t fly away but gentle enough so as not to hurt it. This nimbleness allows you to pivot more freely and be open to more possibilities.</li>
  <li>Ask for help from a diverse set of people or seek out a black sheep. The advise doesn’t need to be competent, it needs to be different.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="habits-that-help-getting-unstuck">Habits that help getting unstuck</h3>

<ol>
  <li>The OODA loop or observe, orient, decide, act can also help one get unstuck. The first step observe is to figure out why you’re stuck. The second step is the most important and requires you to make an action plan personalised for you. The decide step is to exploit the piece of information you got from the 2nd step and the final step is about to act.</li>
  <li>Experimentating multiple pathways or options to pick the one that works best. Forming a habit of experimenting with multiple ideas is known to get more optimal outcomes in the long run. There are generally two ways to setup experiments. First, choose from competing solutions and second, look in the global space of all available options.</li>
  <li>Explore Exploit Tradeoff is creating periods of stasis interleaved with periods of change. An optimal balance of saying yes and no to new opportunities can make all the difference. Your default answer in any given situation should depend your current state of mind (for ex in the face of new career opportunities, if you’re satisfied with your career, you can default to No, while if you’re unsatisfied your default your answer to Yes).</li>
  <li>Being always ready for action when you bump into inspiration. Following, sparks of creativity, with action immediately is the key to getting unstuck. Feelings are nothing if they don’t feed into action. Most musicians swear by picking up the instrument and strumming it leading to new tracks rather than just humming the tunes in their heads.</li>
  <li>Micro-scheduling is when you put on a timer for 60 secs to do just one thing. It eliminates the need to think what else you could be doing right then and paves the way for you to empty your ideas on to the paper/keyboard/etc in front of you. It is also known to be a great way to get started on a task you’ve been putting off for a while.</li>
  <li>Exercise or any kind of movement is known to encourage divergent thinking</li>
  <li>Strategic lowering of standards helps you get started with your version 1s and to get you flowing. It also allows you to “empty your bad ideas” and get to the next one. It also allows you to work on your bad ideas without any mental baggage and gets you moving.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is a collection of lessons from the book Anatomy of a Breakthrough, by Adam Alter, on understanding why we get stuck and how to get unstuck. It is a fascinating read that underscores that getting stuck is a virtual certainty in creative endeavours and that there are ways to get unstuck. The book is a collection of stories of breakthroughs and how they came about. It is a great read and I highly recommend it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 2" /><published>2023-10-26T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-10-26T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-2/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to the second installment of my lessons from Robert Greene’s “48 Laws of Power.” If you missed the initial exploration, you can <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/48-laws-of-power-summarised-1/">catch up on it here</a>. Let’s get on with the next and final 24 laws.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Recreate Yourself: Transform into a persona that exudes power, consciously choosing your role in the grand play of life. Develop an attitude that becomes synonymous with your identity, thereby standing out and leaving a lasting impression on those around you.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Keep Your Hands Clean: Craft an image of virtue and maintain an appearance of civility, all while discreetly handling your affairs. Keep mistakes concealed by diverting attention, and ensure you have a convenient scapegoat at the ready.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Leverage People’s Need to Believe: Harness the power of human gullibility by incorporating innovative technologies or enticing get-rich-quick schemes. Capitalize on the innate desire for something extraordinary and novel.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make Bold Claims and Get Attention: Boldness, when executed with confidence, appears less outrageous and more captivating. Embrace audacity, capturing the attention of those around you who are instinctively drawn to the extraordinary.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Plan All the Way to the End: Strategize meticulously, ensuring your endeavors conclude on a high note. Take credit for successes and prepare for potential setbacks. Recognize the art of timing and know when to halt progress, withdrawing into contemplation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Appear Effortless at Whatever You Do: Embrace “sprezzatura,” an Italian concept denoting a certain nonchalance. Indicate that your capabilities extend far beyond what is seen, concealing the effort invested. Maintain an air of effortlessness to cultivate an aura of mastery.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Control the Options and Control the Cards Others Have to Play: Present choices that align with your objectives, subtly influencing the decisions of those around you. Manipulate the situation to make others feel empowered while ensuring the options favor your agenda.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Play to People’s Fantasies: Cater to the human desire for easy solutions and shortcuts. Package your endeavors as a magical remedy, capturing the imagination of those seeking a way out of their challenges.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Discover Each Man’s Thumbscrew: Engage in active listening to discern the weaknesses and triggers of others. Understanding what drives individuals allows you to navigate relationships with insight and influence.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Way You Carry Yourself Decides How You Will Be Treated: Project an air of regality to elicit corresponding treatment. Consider Columbus, who lacked qualifications but meticulously detailed his vision before embarking on a historic journey. Uphold dignity and cultivate a mindset destined for greatness.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Master the Art of Timing: Avoid haste, compelling others to conform to your pace. Deliberate and strategize, projecting an image of calm assurance.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ignore the Things You Don’t Have: Dismiss minor problems to prevent their escalation. Granting undue attention to trivial matters amplifies their significance. This is also loosely related to the self critical inner voice we all have. I discussed it at length in my book summary of <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/how-to-silence-your-inner-critic/">Chatter</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Create Compelling Spectacles: Make your presence unforgettable by crafting impactful moments. Imprint yourself in the minds of others through experiences that linger long after you’ve departed. Adopting a <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/epic-framework-for-creating-defining-moments/">moment spotting habit</a> can help you identify opportunities to create lasting memories.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Think as You Like but Act Like Others: Navigate against the current discreetly, avoiding unnecessary attention. Standing out invites disdain; blending in fosters a sense of security among peers.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Stir Up Water to Catch Fish: Disrupt your adversaries’ composure to induce irrational actions. By unsettling their equilibrium, you gain a strategic advantage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Despise the Free Lunch: Avoid entanglements involving hidden obligations. Abstain from payment in gratitude, guilt, or deceit, preserving your autonomy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Avoid Stepping in a Great Man’s Shoes: Carve your own path to distinction, avoiding emulation. Shine uniquely, establishing your identity independently.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Strike the Shepherd and the Sheep Will Scatter: Identify and neutralize the core influencer causing discord. By addressing the source, you mitigate the impact on the collective.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Work on the Hearts and Minds of Others: Seduce and engage others at their level, fostering shared aspirations. Powerful leaders build pillars of support rather than creating adversaries by vanquishing the cherished connections of others.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Disarm People by Mirroring: Confound adversaries by mirroring their actions, undermining their sense of uniqueness. This tactic fosters a belief that shared values exist, creating confusion and doubt. Mirroring was also a key tactic of negotiation in <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/10-negotiations-tips-from-never-split-the-difference/">Never Split The Difference</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Preach the Need for Change but in Moderate Amounts: Advocate for change with subtlety, preserving respect for tradition. Gradual modifications maintain a semblance of continuity while embracing progress.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Never Appear Too Perfect: Reveal imperfections strategically, conveying fallibility. This approach discourages envy and fosters relatability.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Don’t Go Too Far: Exercise restraint and discern when to cease advancement. Avoid overextension, preventing the dilution of focus and resources.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Assume Formlessness: Embrace adaptability, recognizing the transience of stability. Understand that rules are malleable, subject to change in the ever-evolving landscape of power dynamics.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>In the intricate tapestry of power dynamics, these laws serve as navigational tools for those seeking mastery but as I said before some of these are too nuanced and can be misused. I would recommend reading the book to understand the context and the examples that Robert Greene uses to explain these laws.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome back to the second installment of my lessons from Robert Greene’s “48 Laws of Power.” If you missed the initial exploration, you can catch up on it here. Let’s get on with the next and final 24 laws.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 1" /><published>2023-10-14T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-10-14T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-1/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently delved into Robert Greene’s influential book, 48 Laws of Power. While the overarching theme might not have immediately resonated with me, the intricate laws it presents have undeniably played a role in shaping power dynamics around me, knowingly or unknowingly. The book, a compilation of historical anecdotes, sheds light on how individuals have employed these laws to secure power. Below, I’ve distilled the first 24 laws into brief sentences. Throughout, I’ve used the term “enemy” interchangeably with counterparts, competitors, or opponents.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Never outshine the master: Show respect and adoration, recognizing the insecurities of superiors. Strive to make them feel powerful while subtly asserting your competence.</li>
  <li>Don’t trust friends too much: Be cautious with favors, as friendship can cloud judgment; turn enemies into passive allies. Maintain a strategic distance to preserve objectivity in decision-making.</li>
  <li>Conceal your true intentions: Keep motives hidden to avoid manipulation; Bismark’s support of Austria illustrates this. Strategic ambiguity allows you to control the narrative and adapt as circumstances change.</li>
  <li>Say less than necessary: Speaking sparingly avoids revealing secrets or turning people off; Andy Warhol mastered this art. Cultivate a sense of mystery to keep others intrigued and engaged.</li>
  <li>Reputation is everything: Strengthen your reputation while poking holes in your enemies’ reputations. Craft an image that is both unassailable and strategically aligns with your goals.</li>
  <li>Court attention at every cost: Stand out, be conspicuous, and maintain an air of mystery. Cultivate a personal brand that captures attention and sets you apart in the minds of others.</li>
  <li>Never do what others can do for you: Delegate, hire talent, and build on the knowledge and insights of others. Recognize the power of collaboration and surround yourself with a team that complements your strengths.</li>
  <li>Make other people come to you: Keep others on the defensive by laying traps and avoiding acting in anger. Strategic patience and the ability to make others come to you give you the upper hand in negotiations.</li>
  <li>Win through actions and not arguments: Yield in arguments, but let actions speak louder to gain respect and followers. Demonstrate competence through tangible results, allowing your accomplishments to be your most persuasive argument.</li>
  <li>Avoid the unhappy and unlucky: Misery attracts misery, and these individuals can bring you down; steer clear. Surround yourself with positive influences to foster a mindset of growth and success.</li>
  <li>Never become redundant: Keep some knowledge exclusive to yourself; side with the weak to become their backbone. Position yourself as indispensable by offering unique skills that others can depend on.</li>
  <li>Use sincere and honest moves strategically: First impressions of honesty and sincerity can be powerful. Leverage authenticity to build trust but strategically reveal vulnerability to create deeper connections.</li>
  <li>Ask for help by appealing to their self-interest: Align your interests with theirs, avoiding direct charity requests. Forge alliances by making others see the mutual benefits of assisting you.</li>
  <li>Ask indirect questions to find out their true nature: Conceal your own personality while encouraging others to talk about themselves. Uncover hidden motivations by creating an environment where people willingly reveal their true selves.</li>
  <li>Crush your enemy totally: Showing mercy can backfire; commit to your course of action to its conclusion. Understand that half measures can lead to future challenges, so decisively eliminate threats when necessary.</li>
  <li>Absence can lead to exclusivity: Scarcity enhances value; make yourself scarce to be more desirable. Balance presence and absence strategically to increase your perceived value.</li>
  <li>Cultivate an air of unpredictability: Keep those around you guessing, making them expend energy trying to understand you. Harness the psychological advantage of being unpredictable to control situations.</li>
  <li>Isolation is dangerous: Circulate to gather necessary information; avoid building a fortress. Strategic networking and information gathering are vital components of effective decision-making. I guess there’s a sweet spot between rule 16 and this one.</li>
  <li>Do not offend the wrong person: Understand who holds real power; keep tabs on decision-makers. Navigate relationships with discernment, recognizing the key players and influencers in any given situation.</li>
  <li>Don’t commit to a side: Remaining neutral prevents loss in conflicts; strong demands, and the weak wears you down. Preserve flexibility by avoiding premature commitments in dynamic situations.</li>
  <li>Play sucker to catch a sucker: Acting less knowledgeable than you are can work to your advantage. Use the perception of naivety strategically to extract valuable information and gain a psychological edge.</li>
  <li>Make surrender a tool of power: Surrender congenially to those who seek a display of authority. Strategic concessions can be a powerful tool, allowing you to control the terms of surrender.</li>
  <li>Concentrate your power: Focus on long-term gains; don’t waste energy on insignificant matters. Identify the areas where your efforts yield the greatest impact and concentrate your resources accordingly.</li>
  <li>Play the perfect courtier: Act as if you have a king to please; avoid boasting about achievements. Adopt a humble demeanor, focusing on serving others and building relationships rather than self-promotion.</li>
</ol>

<p>While some of these rules may seem Machiavellian, adapting them to your personality and setting requires thoughtful consideration. Stay tuned for a future post where I’ll summarize the remaining 24 laws.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently delved into Robert Greene’s influential book, 48 Laws of Power. While the overarching theme might not have immediately resonated with me, the intricate laws it presents have undeniably played a role in shaping power dynamics around me, knowingly or unknowingly. The book, a compilation of historical anecdotes, sheds light on how individuals have employed these laws to secure power. Below, I’ve distilled the first 24 laws into brief sentences. Throughout, I’ve used the term “enemy” interchangeably with counterparts, competitors, or opponents.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing incentives that work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing incentives that work" /><published>2023-10-05T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-10-05T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work/"><![CDATA[<p>As an entrpreneur, product and people manager, I often find myself needing to design incentives that affect people’s behaviors. If you read the last sentence and the image formed in your head was that of a dangling carrot on a stick, i’ll request you to ignore it. I am talking about creating an environment where some really smart people become open to changing their behaviour ever so slightly to achieve larger goals. I wouldn’t blame you for the image that formed in your head though, as incentives are often poorly designed and are counter productive. In his book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mixed-Signals-Incentives-Really-Work/dp/B0BT5SW1RT/ref=sr_1_4?crid=2ZKM6B767T896&amp;keywords=mixed+signals&amp;qid=1696566311&amp;sprefix=mi%2Caps%2C1005&amp;sr=8-4">Mixed Signals</a>, Uri Gneezy, describes in detail how incentives can be used to achieve desired outcomes or mixed signaling be avoided that leads to incentives that aim to improve one thing but focus on another. I have tried to summarise the key learnings from the book below.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/horsecarrot.png" alt="Horse carrot stick by Dall-E" srcset="    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-320x320.png 320w,    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-480x480.png 480w,    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-800x800.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/10/horsecarrot.png 1024w" /> 
<em>Not the image you should have when you think of incentives</em></p>

<h3 id="what-is-signaling">What is signaling?</h3>

<p>Signaling in this context refers to the social cues that we send out to others. Signals are a credible way to indicate your values, abilities, aspirations and preferences. We all indulge in one or the other type of signaling but if the signal is easy to adapt it can be copied and if it is too loud it can come across as inauthentic. A rich person may not want people to know that they want them to know they are rich. Thus enter, Rolexes. The real Biker culture has strong signals like conspicuous tattoos on the neck and arms. This is to identify real bikers and eliminate casual bikers who can also buy bikes &amp; riding gear which are, in comparison, cheap signals.</p>

<p>Through policies we can force a person to send a very strong signal or a weak signal for specific things. Disney World, for example, allows free tickets for kids under 3. People often lie about their kids’ age but if DW began asking children their age directly, two things can happen</p>

<ol>
  <li>Kids will tell their true age and DW will eliminate the problem</li>
  <li>Parents will instruct their kids in advance on lying about their age which will sort of persist the problem to some extent.</li>
</ol>

<p>Notice what is really happening with the second point. Parents are being asked to teach lying to their kids which is a strong signal to the parents that the price of the ticket is worth teaching kids to lie. This is a very strong signal and most parents won’t do it. This is a very crude example but it illustrates the point of how one can design policies and incentives that use the signaling mechanism to achieve desired outcomes.</p>

<h3 id="avoiding-mixed-signaling">Avoiding mixed signaling</h3>

<p>Another important aspect of using signals is avoiding sending mixed signals. It is usually borne out of encouraging something but incentivising another. For instance, encouraging quality of deliverables but giving bonuses for quantity or encouraging long term goal alignment but praising short term milestones.</p>

<p>This is usually sorted out by adding more dimensions to the incentive structures. For instance, adding a rating system for the end user satisfaction along with evaluating people on quantity. This will ensure that people don’t just focus on quantity but also on quality.</p>

<h3 id="self-v-social-signals">Self v Social Signals</h3>

<p>Most signals are social in that they allow one to communicate their values to others. Driving fuel guzzling semis or choosing to go with hybrid cars is a social signal that you care about the environment. In the early days of hybrid cars, they were seen as pricier options with limited comfort and safety features. However, one shining factor set them apart – their eco-friendly nature. Consumers began embracing hybrid vehicles not just for their fuel economy but to send a powerful message to the world: “We care for the environment, and we’re willing to sacrifice some comforts for it.”</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/prius.jpeg" alt="Cool prius as a social signal" srcset="    /assets/resized/prius-320x285.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/prius-480x428.jpeg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/10/prius.jpeg 800w" /></p>

<p>Enter the Toyota Prius and the Honda Civic, both based on existing models. However, the Prius had a distinct and conspicuous look that drew consumers who wanted to stand out and signal their commitment to environmental causes. As a result, Prius won big. The importance of signaling was underscored by a 2007 survey, revealing that a remarkable 57% of Prius owners chose it to make a statement about themselves, far outweighing those who mentioned fuel economy or reduced emissions.</p>

<p>Self signals are signals that you send to yourself. Self signaling allow people to tell themselves that they are a good person or have certain values. Pay what you want coffee shops that are popping up in the US are a good example of self signaling. People readily pay more than the cost of the coffee because they want to feel good about themselves. The same people will not pay more than the cost of the coffee if they were asked to pay a specific amount. This is called the <em>warm glow effect</em>, what we feel when we help, volunteer or donate. The self signaling mechanism is very powerful and can be used to achieve desired outcomes.</p>

<h3 id="mental-accounting">Mental Accounting</h3>

<p>We all have different mental accounts for various expenses. Think about it; we might spend 20 minutes searching for parking deals to save a few bucks but don’t hesitate to splurge on dessert afterward. The money across these accounts is not interchangeable and the story we tell ourselves to justify our choices are entirely different. While saving on parking is a sound financial choice, ending a family meal with a lovely dessert is a way to elevate a moment and make it memorable. To make incentives truly appealing, we must use the right currency that shapes the narrative we want.</p>

<p>Consider the story of a car review site that offered a $450 discount on car purchases. Surprisingly, this incentive didn’t have the positive impact they expected. Why? The $450 discount on a high-value purchase like a car got lost in the documentation and seemed insignificant. However, when they began offering the same $450 discount as “prepaid gas cards” for the same amount, demand improved significantly. Why? $450 is $450. Or is it?</p>

<p>When it comes to incentives, they can often sit in different mental accounts. In the gas card scenario, buyers know they will need gas and the $450 incentive seems to come across as something extra. Moreover, every time buyers filled up their gas tanks using the free card, they felt smart for making a clever buying decision. This simple shift in the perception of value made all the difference.</p>

<h3 id="regret-minimisation">Regret Minimisation</h3>

<p>Regret is caused by comparing what we did v what we could have done. Regret can also be caused by not exploring a new option. In that sense, exploration is it’s own reward. This is related to the <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-thinking-fast-slow-part-2/">loss aversion</a> concept from Thinking Fast &amp; Slow. We love to avoid regret at all costs. This makes regret a great tool for incentives and driving behaviours.</p>

<p>A classic example of this is the case where someone keeps buying a lottery ticket with the exact same numbers cause he thinks if he stopped buying and those numbers came up as winner, he would regret it immensely 🤷. A similar interesting case was of a lottery company that picked a random postcode from where a final winner will be chosen. This forced people in that postcode to think of a scenario in which someone from their address won the lottery but they didn’t. To avoid that regret, people flocked to buy lottery tickets.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As an entrpreneur, product and people manager, I often find myself needing to design incentives that affect people’s behaviors. If you read the last sentence and the image formed in your head was that of a dangling carrot on a stick, i’ll request you to ignore it. I am talking about creating an environment where some really smart people become open to changing their behaviour ever so slightly to achieve larger goals. I wouldn’t blame you for the image that formed in your head though, as incentives are often poorly designed and are counter productive. In his book Mixed Signals, Uri Gneezy, describes in detail how incentives can be used to achieve desired outcomes or mixed signaling be avoided that leads to incentives that aim to improve one thing but focus on another. I have tried to summarise the key learnings from the book below.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How not to argue</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How not to argue" /><published>2023-08-28T12:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-08-28T12:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue/"><![CDATA[<p>I previously wrote <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/how-to-argue/">How to Argue</a> which was a collection of tips on how to have fruitful discussions. This post is a follow up to that post and is inspired by the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Whats-Our-Problem-Self-Help-Societies/dp/B0BVGH6T1Q/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=whats+our+problem&amp;qid=1693216187&amp;sr=8-1">Whats our problem</a> by Tim Urban. My previous post talked about how to get the best out of a discussion by keeping an open mind, this post describes some common pitfalls that can derail a discussion. Before we can jump into what to avoid, it makes sense to understand the higher and the lower mind thesis and the different ways we defend our opinions.</p>

<h3 id="the-higher-mind-and-the-lower-mind">The higher mind and the lower mind</h3>

<p>Tim Urban describes the concept of higher mind (conscious, wise, knows what we should do, etc) and the lower mind (controls our primal behaviours and what we can do). These don’t map exactly to System 1 and 2 of <a href="/lessons-from-thinking-fast-slow-part-1/">Thinking fast and slow</a> but can be thought of as abstractions of them.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/thinking-scales.jpg" alt="Thinking scales by Tim Urban" srcset="    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-320x255.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-480x382.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-800x637.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/thinking-scales.jpg 1740w" /></p>

<p>This high v low terminology segues into the vertical thinking which is an often forgotten dimension of discussions. for ex when we discuss politics, we just think of a linear scale from left to right that describe what you believe in but there is a vertical axis as that describes, how you believe. Higher mind thinks like a scientist (constantly looking to be proven wrong in the short term to get it right in the long term) and often times like a fan (motivated reasoning). The lower mind thinks like an attorney (vehemently defending their beliefs) or a zealot (consider the world as a simple black and white).</p>

<h3 id="framing-a-weak-counterargument-or-strawman">Framing a weak Counterargument or Strawman</h3>

<p>The sign of a weak argument is a weak counterargument. Greatly authored papers always come with a great counter argument. It shows the authors have thought through the problem and have considered the other side of the argument. If people cannot come up with a good counterargument it means their own arguments are flimsy and weak.</p>

<p>A strawman argument is a misrepresentation of an opponent’s argument that is easy to defeat. It is a fallacy because it fails to address the actual arguments that the opponent is making. It is a form of argument that is aims to give the impression of refuting an opponent’s argument, while actually refuting an argument that was not presented by that opponent. One can easily spot a strawman argument when the counterargument is a caricature of the original argument.</p>

<p>Always steelman your counterpart, i.e. address the core issue being discussed and not a caricature of it. This is the only way to have an intellectually honest discussion.</p>

<h3 id="motte-and-bailey">Motte and Bailey</h3>

<p>In ancient times, Bailey was the flat land used for living and cultivation while the Motte was a fortress atop the adjoining hill. When under attack, people living in Bailey ran up to the Mott and held the fort which was far more defensible. This is what people do when their arguments come under fire. They run to the Motte which is easy to defend and has similarities with the original argument however is a different argument.</p>

<p>A simple example would be you defending a specific idea like gun control and you run to the Motte and say something like “I am for protection of freedom at all costs”. This is a classic motte and bailey. The motte is easy to defend and is a weaker version of the original argument.</p>

<p>Always defend your original and exact position, not an abstraction or dilution of it that is obviously easy to defend or not even a point of contention.</p>

<h3 id="discrediting-the-speaker">Discrediting the speaker</h3>

<p>Discrediting the speaker is the easiest way to not address the arguments posed by the speaker. This is also known as ad hominem. When you hear arguments formed in a way that are directed against a person rather than the position they are maintaining, you know they are indulging in ad hominem.</p>

<p>Apart from being unproductive, ad hominem is also a logical fallacy. It is a fallacy because the character, circumstances, or actions of a person do not (in most cases) have a bearing on the truth or falsity of the claim being made (or the quality of the argument being made). Needless to say calling someone names or attacking their character is not a good way to have a fruitful discussion.</p>

<h3 id="esteem-protectiveness">Esteem protectiveness</h3>

<p>The final point is not too get too entangled with your opinions. We all have a tendency to protect our self esteem and our opinions are a part of our identity. When our opinions are challenged, we feel threatened and our lower mind takes over that pushes us to become closed minded. We use the tactics described above because of our confirmation bias and esteem protectiveness. We twist observations into stories we want to hear that validate our already formed beliefs. Nobody wants to look like an idiot who was brainwashed, so we defend our positions like a zealot.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I previously wrote How to Argue which was a collection of tips on how to have fruitful discussions. This post is a follow up to that post and is inspired by the book Whats our problem by Tim Urban. My previous post talked about how to get the best out of a discussion by keeping an open mind, this post describes some common pitfalls that can derail a discussion. Before we can jump into what to avoid, it makes sense to understand the higher and the lower mind thesis and the different ways we defend our opinions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How consumption defines us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-consumption-defines-us/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How consumption defines us" /><published>2023-07-29T09:10:02+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-29T09:10:02+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-consumption-defines-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-consumption-defines-us/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Sum-Small-Things-Theory-Aspirational/dp/0691183171/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2POPBLCGLHVNL&amp;keywords=the+sum+of+small+things&amp;qid=1690606979&amp;sprefix=the+sum+of+small+thi%2Caps%2C349&amp;sr=8-1">The Sum of Small Things</a>, by Elizabeth Currid-Halkett is one of the most thought provoking books i’ve read in a while. It defines the new aspiration class that is defined by a different kind of consumption. The book challenged my understanding of why I consume what I consume and how it defines me. I’ve tried to summarize the book in this post.</p>

<h3 id="what-we-think-consumption-is-v-what-it-really-is">What we think consumption is V what it really is</h3>

<p>We think consumption is always linked to needs or desires but in reality it is a signalling device. It is a way to show others who we are and what we stand for. It is a way to show our identity, values, status, beliefs, personality, aspirations, political leanings, and so much more. It helps us create an idea of us and thereby create an other.</p>

<p>The book talks about conspicuous and inconsipcuous consumption. Conspicuous consumption is the consumption of goods and services that are meant to be seen and noticed by others. Inconspicuous consumption is the consumption of basic goods that are private. The book explains how conspicuous consumption goes beyond the traditional definition of luxury goods and services. Good table manners, for example, are also a type of conspicuous consumption because it takes time to build those habits and is a way to signal your social standing. Same goes for going to a specific school, or having a specific accent, or having a specific taste in music, books, art, fitness, etc.</p>

<p>How or why we consume something is also largely out of our conscious control. The city we live in, the peer group we move about in, our job, our education levels, etc, all play a larger than life role in our consumption patterns. For example, people in New York City spend almost 50% more on fashion than any other city in the US. This is driven by the fact that New York is the fashion capital of the US and people in the city are more likely to be influenced by fashion trends. Similarly, people in San Francisco spend more on fitness than any other city in the US. This is driven by the fact that San Francisco is the tech capital of the US and people in the city are more likely to be influenced by fitness trends than fashion.</p>

<h3 id="aspirational-class">Aspirational class</h3>

<p>The consumer class was defined by conspicuous consumption, generally propelled by economic mobility and income. People in the consumer class showed their wellbeing by consuming specific goods and services (branded luxury goods and memberships to exclusive clubs, etc). These affluent elite were marked by consumption of Veblen goods, goods for which demand increases as the price increases. Veblen goods are typically high-quality goods that are well made, exclusive, and act as status symbols.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The new aspirational class is marked by knowledge and specific societal behaviors like veganism, volunteerism, reading the NY Times, etc, in their attempts to become better humans</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Aspirational class consumption may often be more expensive like buying from the farmers market but it is ultimately not a requirement but rather a means to signal social belonging. The new age conspicuous consumption doesn’t always shy away from capitalism. It in fact, focuses on bringing the production process front and center and allow people to show their status by consumption. In short, the story of the good becomes more important than its quality or price. This is why the aspirational class is happy to pay a dollar for an egg provided they like the way the farmer treats his chicken.</p>

<p>One of the intricacies of the aspirational class or <em>the new elite</em>, is their greed to have a return on their leisure time. When people choose to go to a specific fitness class or buy expensive fitness wear like lululemon, they make a commitment to use their leisure time in a certain way. When they watch a specific show or film or attend an opera, they are signalling a certain taste.</p>

<h3 id="cultural-capital">Cultural Capital</h3>

<p>The rise of the aspirational class is mostly a function of what the author calls <em>post scarcity</em>. The consumption of eco friendly goods and practices are a result of post scarcity environment. The fact that we have the luxury of choice is what allows people to signal their status. In terms of Maslow’s hierarchy of needs, it is in today’s world of plenty that we can self actualise. The aspirational class is not fueled by economic mobility but rather by cultural capital.</p>

<p>Cultural capital is the knowledge and skills required to navigate the world. It is the ability to understand and appreciate the nuances of the world. It is the ability to understand the difference between a $10 wine and a $100 wine, between a $1000 handbag and a $100 handbag, between a handcrafted artisanal product and a mass produced factory item and so on. It is having the wherewithall to both, understand the need to care about the environment and to show that you do.</p>

<p>Going into hole-in-the-wall restaurants or buying tomatoes at the farmers market are both types of cultural capital acquired by reading a specific newspaper or belonging to a certain interest group. The cultural capital is used by the elite to distribute opportunities just as regular capital was used before. What nail polish color to wear, how many books to carry to the classroom, which newspapers to read and discuss are all examples of cultural capital of the form of knowledge acquired by staying in touch with ones peer group or behaving in a certain way. These behaviours appear costless but are actually a result of slugging it out in a certain peer group.</p>

<h3 id="why-judging-others-is-stupid">Why judging others is stupid</h3>

<p>We assume every decision a person makes (esp when it comes to health or parenting) is a moral choice (why is that person fat, why aren’t they culturally more aware, why are they feeding fast food to their kids, etc) but often times these decisions emanate from constraints either financial or time or awareness; which itself is borne out of a lack of investment of time. A working class person cannot afford healthy food for their children who often waste most of the food given to them. They cannot spend time to attend pilate classes or read the new yorker either.  Often times working mothers don’t have the time or energy to breastfeed their children after a 14 hour workdays and so they choose to use formula.</p>

<p>We look up to women taking time off from work to breast feed their children or pursue “attachment therapy”, with sympathy but we look down on an expensive hermes bag, but the reality is that both these actions are,</p>

<ol>
  <li>enabled by resources like time or affluence</li>
  <li>a product of the cultural milieu to which one belongs and in a sense aimed at fitting in or belonging</li>
</ol>

<p>Judging others on the basis of their actions or inactions, but remaining ignorant of their constraints, is therefore stupid.</p>

<p>This books introduced me to the term <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobo_(socio-economic_group)?useskin=vector">Bobos</a> - Bohemian Bourgeois, which probably perfectly sums up quite a lot of my consumption patterns. The term was introduced into the English language by the cultural commentator #DavidBrooks to describe the 1990s descendants of the yuppies in the book Bobos in Paradise (2000). Brooks describes Bobos as “highly educated folk who have one foot in the bohemian world of creativity and another foot in the bourgeois realm of ambition and worldly success. People who spend money to look simple can also be termed as Bobos.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehack" /><category term="Human Psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Sum of Small Things, by Elizabeth Currid-Halkett is one of the most thought provoking books i’ve read in a while. It defines the new aspiration class that is defined by a different kind of consumption. The book challenged my understanding of why I consume what I consume and how it defines me. I’ve tried to summarize the book in this post.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How beliefs are formed and reinforced</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-beliefs-are-formed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How beliefs are formed and reinforced" /><published>2023-07-21T00:00:02+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-21T00:00:02+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-beliefs-are-formed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-beliefs-are-formed/"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s how beliefs are formed -&gt; we believe in certain things based on our genetic disposition to certain personality traits, our upbringing, our parents’ political leanings, our friends’ opinions, our own experiences, our biases, prejudices, fears, desires, hopes, aspirations, goals, etc. In other words a lot of factors, that are not rational or anasytical. What happens after forming a belief is more interesting. The hippocampus, our brain’s storyteller, connects separate, distant events into a single narrative around the belief and why it is true. The purpose is not accuracy but coherency. This is the reason why we can’t change someone’s mind by presenting them with facts as their mind has already weaved a story that reinforces the belief.</p>

<p>In his book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/The-Believing-Brain-Michael-Shermer-audio/dp/B0052FX3XE/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=the+believing+brain+-+michael+shermer&amp;qid=1689916387&amp;sprefix=the+believing+brain%2Caps%2C455&amp;sr=8-1">The Believing Brain</a>, Michael Shermer explains how beliefs are formed and how they are reinforced. In the following sections, I describe the key ideas from the book.</p>

<h3 id="what-you-believe-is-what-you-see">What you believe is what you see</h3>

<p>In an experiment conducted to understand the effectiveness of mental health prognosis, Rosenhan, a senior psychologist conducted several studies that showed the hospital environment can modify our understanding of a specific behaviour which can or cannot be considered abnormal. He said to his students he will be sending a faking patient and that they had to spot him. In reality he sent no fakers but still 40 patients were flagged to be faking out of 200. In a similar study he had 7 faking psychology majors go to the hospital who were never found to be faking and were in fact diagnosed with serious mental illnesses. These experiments showed that the underlying belief system manipulates what we see and how we interpret it.</p>

<h3 id="patternicity-and-agenticity">Patternicity and Agenticity</h3>

<p>We believe things because we see patterns. Patternicity and Agenticity are our evolutionary abilities to spot patterns in noise and assigning them meanings that aren’t really there. Shermer explains how anecdotal learning comes naturally, while science takes effort. We are the descendents of those who could find patterns to survive the dangers that lurked near them. We don’t have a system that overlooks this pattern recognition. Our brain simply runs a cost heuristic - cost of making a false positive error (the bush moving is a tiger) Vs that of the false negative error (its just wind). This is why we make superstitious beliefs, because we cannot distinguish between bad learning and learning.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People believe weird things because of our ability to believe things.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Superstitions are nothing but a type of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operant_conditioning_chamber">B.F. Skinner’s bird box scenario</a>, where we believe a point or a reward comes to us because of something we did but it happened on its own.</p>

<h3 id="goldilocks-zone-of-open-mindedness">Goldilocks zone of open mindedness</h3>

<p>There is a just right amount of “open mindedness” that is healthy. There are thin boundaries between Creativity, which is borne out of the perfect use of patternicity and agenticity; and madness, that comes from an extremely active use of both. If we’re too open to capturing patterns, we see one where there is none, if we too little, we miss out on important observations. Scientists also walk this tightrope of spotting patterns. The author talks about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kary_Mullis">Kary Mullis</a>, a scientist who won the Nobel prize for inventing polymerase chain reaction (<em>PCR</em>), in which a small amount of DNA can be copied in large quantities. He was a creative genius but also had some weird beliefs like his belief in astrology and having witnessed an extra terrestrial glowing racoon.</p>

<p>The point the author makes is that Mullis had a wide angle lens for spotting patterns which ensured many weird and creative ideas got through and made its seat in his head but only a small proportion of these ideas were useful (in the modern day sense of the word).</p>

<h3 id="we-all-differ-so-much">We all differ so much</h3>

<p>Genetics also indirectly play a role in us believing certain things. While genes dont directly contribute to political leanings or religious beliefs, they do play a role in shaping personality traits that in turn make it easy or hard for us to believe certain things.</p>

<p>It is because of these differences that we all have the potential to believe so many different things and make up stories that explain the same observation entirely differently. A realistic vision of the world involves understanding that there are moral constraints. People have potential to be moral as well as amoral. Believing this is important to understand why people do what they do and then creating policies and systems that work with this reality.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehack" /><category term="Human Psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s how beliefs are formed -&gt; we believe in certain things based on our genetic disposition to certain personality traits, our upbringing, our parents’ political leanings, our friends’ opinions, our own experiences, our biases, prejudices, fears, desires, hopes, aspirations, goals, etc. In other words a lot of factors, that are not rational or anasytical. What happens after forming a belief is more interesting. The hippocampus, our brain’s storyteller, connects separate, distant events into a single narrative around the belief and why it is true. The purpose is not accuracy but coherency. This is the reason why we can’t change someone’s mind by presenting them with facts as their mind has already weaved a story that reinforces the belief.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What constitues play and having fun?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/play-and-having-fun/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What constitues play and having fun?" /><published>2023-06-20T00:00:02+05:30</published><updated>2023-06-20T00:00:02+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/play-and-having-fun</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/play-and-having-fun/"><![CDATA[<p>In his book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Play-Anything-Ian-Bogost-audiobook/dp/B01KP45MMG/ref=sr_1_1?crid=26CSPFTJK2GU9&amp;keywords=play+anything&amp;qid=1687667435&amp;sprefix=pla%2Caps%2C1306&amp;sr=8-1">Play Anything</a>, Ian Bogost aims to explain how fun and play are not the same thing. He claims that “fun” is not pleasure but rather the aftereffect of play. This book challenges almost all notions of play, fun, pleasure, boredom and happiness. In this post I try to summarise the key ideas from the book.</p>

<h5 id="what-is-play-and-fun">What is play and fun</h5>

<p>Misery gives way to fun when you take the constraints that aren’t designed for you and then treat it if it were a source of fun. Do something particular with the material you have is playing. The example that Bogost begins with is his trip to the mall with his daughter. He treats this visit to the mall as a chore and is frantically running around to finish the shopping. His daughter, on the other hand, is having fun. He is walking faster than is comfortable for his daughter but she makes the best of it by designing a game of trying to land her feet in tiles in a certain pattern. She is playing with the constraints of the mall.</p>

<p>This is the essence of play. Play is hard and needs work. Playing requires more attention, generosity, ingenuity and creativity than real life does. Play mostly lies on the other side of the disgust that is associated with boredom and in that way boredom is essential to concoct play.</p>

<p>Fun is the aftermath of taking an existing and well defined structure and making it do something different. It requires effort. Golf, for ex is not a good walk spoiled as the old aphorism goes, it is a purposeful manipulation of landscape to provide us fun. Things that usually make life hard are what make it fun. Mary Poppin’s spoonful of sugar is not the right way to derive fun but to accept things as they are and working with them.</p>

<p>It is often taking something visible and making it invisible and taking something omnipresent but not visible and making it conspicuous. Pleasure doesn’t always sneak up on us. Sometimes we seek out repetition of the known.  The “experience of expertise” is also related. The joy of mastery is a type of pleasure that doesn’t surprise but rather offers something recognisable and predictable.</p>

<h5 id="worldfulness-and-everyday-play">Worldfulness and everyday play</h5>

<p>An interesting point that Bogost makes is that, while mindfulness is being comfortable with oneself, “worldfullness” is being comfortable with ourself and the world around us. This allows us to create play. We ignore things around us as we are “busy” and we seek “better things”. The Japanese Shinto philosophy that states every object has a living spirit.</p>

<p>Frustration with everyday things comes from the gap between expectations and reality. When we don’t internalise the world around us, we don’t get frustrated and realise that the world is outside our head and then open ourselves up to embracing the constraints to give life new meanings.</p>

<p>We treat people and objects based on how they make us feel about ourselves. A better way to interact with the world is to work with things around us and appreciate them for what they are. We think of a playground (real one or the one in our mind) as a way to fulfil some objective or exert some control, we drain it of its real fun. This is related to the Buddhist philosophy of expectations/desires being the root of all sorrows and Sikh philosophy that one should yield oneself completely to the one force that flows through all of us. In that sense, real play begins when we compel ourselves to the desires of the swings and slides and the see-saws and do what they need of us.</p>

<p>When you deliberately explore the depths of a boring activity, something magical happens, that magic is what we call “fun”. Bogost also calls it the “solemn appreciation” of something. I run a boring SaaS business and often lose sight of how much fun it really is.</p>

<p>My key takeaway from this book is how solemn appreciation of everyday things like an accounting software or Cheetos can make them as much “fun” as say, an acoustic guitar or a cheese plate.</p>

<h5 id="ironoia">Ironoia</h5>

<p>Irony is saying something while meaning something totally different. Its a sort of get out of jail card that we use to never truly interact with the world. It’s like a sofa cover that at the same time protects the sofa upholstery from damage but also prevents us from ever really experiencing the sofa in the first place. When we walk into a big box retail outlet like Walmart, a bunch of negative emotions greet us - our own consumerist attitude, degradation of aesthetics, encouraging the death of the small mom and pop store and so on. At the same time it is an oasis for those who can afford a certain lifestyle thanks to their prices.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/large-store.jpeg" alt="Walmart can also be thought of as a museum" srcset="    /assets/resized/large-store-320x240.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/large-store-480x360.jpeg 480w,    /assets/resized/large-store-800x600.jpeg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/06/large-store.jpeg 1200w" /></p>

<p>The irony blinds us from seeing Walmart as what it also is, a modern day Cathedral of the various artefacts of human effort like the dora the explorer cherry berry bubble bath, white weed healthy white bread, hard candy nail polish jars, optimus prime pinata, <a href="https://supercenter.tumblr.com/">etc</a> Ironoia, as the author defines, is keeping everything we see around us at an arm’s length in case something better comes along. It is the metaphorical sofa cover that prevents us from ever experiencing the sofa.</p>

<p>Finding play and intrigue in everyday things like a vacuum or going grocery shopping is a good way to live. Randomly browsing things in a Walmart can also be enriching and fun. We musn’t let ironia prevent us from experiencing the world around us.</p>

<h5 id="the-power-of-constraints">The power of constraints</h5>

<p>Bringing the number of available options down makes satisficing easy and can lead to overall satisfaction. Schwartz called this the paradox of choice. In theory, choice makes us happy but too much choice adds cognitive load that can take away the joy from pursuing anything. 
Suppression of choice can also lead to a more meaningful interaction with the environment. When we silent our phones while eating, we are suppressing a choice which makes the meal more enjoyable. There are pleasures in both having too many choices and having fewer choices.</p>

<p>Limitations create playgrounds within which exploration can take place. Poetry with its meter, everyday things like the door knob with its rotation mechanism, our business goals with the constraints, are all examples of everyday games that make life fun. Dr Zeuss’s Cat and Hat and Green Eggs and Ham books use less than 50 words and have sold millions of copies. This is also an example of how constraints, that are often hidden from us, create wonderful experiences.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehack" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In his book, Play Anything, Ian Bogost aims to explain how fun and play are not the same thing. He claims that “fun” is not pleasure but rather the aftereffect of play. This book challenges almost all notions of play, fun, pleasure, boredom and happiness. In this post I try to summarise the key ideas from the book.]]></summary></entry></feed>