<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-14T11:12:35+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Infermuse</title><subtitle>Practical wisdom from studies, experiments and books</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Wrapping up your year on Obsidian</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wrapping-up-year-obsidian/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wrapping up your year on Obsidian" /><published>2022-12-31T11:40:05+05:30</published><updated>2022-12-31T11:40:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wrapping-up-your-year-obsidian</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wrapping-up-year-obsidian/"><![CDATA[<p>The easiest way to keep oneself motivated and on track is to have some sort of visual markers that depict how far we’ve come. In this post, I try to describe a method I use to keep track of my year in Obsidian. It is inspired by the ACCESS method of organising knowledge developed by Nick Milo. I don’t follow it to the T but I use the “Atlas” concept (A in ACCESS) described by Nick, as a way to visualise my year.</p>

<h5 id="organising-notes">Organising notes</h5>

<p>There is obviously no one way to organise notes. It comes down to ones personal preferences and the kinds of notes one usually takes. I have come across two methods that seemed to make a lot of sense. The PARA method described by Tiago Forte in his book <a href="https://www.buildingasecondbrain.com/">Building a second brain</a> and the ACCESS method by <a href="https://www.linkingyourthinking.com/">Nick Milo</a>. I have tried both with varrying degrees of success. Over the last few months, I found a truncated and modified version of ACCESS method works best for me. I describe the two methods below and then go on and explain how I borrowed the concept of Atlas from Nick’s method and use it to visualise my year. Basically, both the methods are sort of ways to organise notes into some kind of a hierarchy that may help you get to what you’re looking for faster and in a way that makes sense to you. You are always essentially answering this question - this note I am writing, what folder should it go into, what other file it must link to, what tag should it carry and so on? The two methods are just different ways to answer these questions.</p>

<h6 id="para-and-access-methods">PARA and ACCESS methods</h6>

<p>The PARA method stands for</p>
<ul>
  <li><em>Projects</em> - the project this note is filed under -&gt; think projects like “Applied AI”, “VSCode extension”, “My amateur table top game” etc. If you take up a lot of side projects, organising information into projects is a good way to keep track of them.</li>
  <li><em>Area</em> - if not project, then which area -&gt; think “Notekeeping”, “ML Research”, “Bioinformatics”, etc</li>
  <li><em>Resources</em> - all external links -&gt; youtube links, articles or files</li>
  <li><em>Archive</em> - stuff completed or on hold -&gt; Archive is a good place to keep notes that you don’t want to delete but don’t want to see in your daily workflow.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/history-moc.jpg" alt="Map of contents for my History notes" srcset="    /assets/resized/history-moc-320x264.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/history-moc-480x395.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/history-moc-800x659.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/history-moc.jpg 1372w" /></p>

<p>Before I describe the ACCESS method, it makes sense to take a minute to understand the underlying concept of a Map of Contents. An MoC can be thought of as an index note that connects to other notes in the same way an index of information does. An MoC acts both as a starting point of reference (an index) and as a hub of information where related notes are available in one place. Each topic of note I take, be it a new book I am reading or a new side project I am tinkering with, has its own MoC (like the MoC for the book “Building a second brain” or my new hacking project about “Learning Elixir”) which connects to all the related notes (in case of book notes these would be individual concepts of the book or in case of a hacking side project the various elements like design spec, references, tutorials, etc).</p>

<p>Now let’s jump to the The ACCESS method.</p>
<ul>
  <li><em>Atlas</em> - map of contents or dashboards -&gt; The Atlas is a map of contents that connects to all the other MoC’s. Think of it as a meta MoC that can be used as a way to see what you’ve done in the year.</li>
  <li><em>Calendar</em> - time based information -&gt; daily notes, journals, etc</li>
  <li><em>Cards</em> - atomic notes -&gt; basically all your information should be in small atomic notes that contain nothing but the specific information you want to capture and it should connect to as many other notes as possible.</li>
  <li><em>Extra</em> - support material -&gt; attachments, templates, etc</li>
  <li><em>Sources</em> - external links -&gt; Articles, books, podcasts, etc</li>
  <li><em>Spaces</em> - big top level spaces -&gt; personal, work, school, etc</li>
</ul>

<p>Both the methods are abstractions that help you think about your information in a specific way.</p>

<h5 id="my-atlas">My Atlas</h5>

<p>I really liked the “Atlas” idea of the ACCESS method and I have adopted that to keep track of my various goals and activities through the year. Here’s how I go about it.</p>

<p>At the top level I have a folder in my vault called Atlas which has folder for every year. The 2022 folder, as shown below, contains the various maps of contents.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-folder-structure.jpg" alt="My Atlas folder structure" srcset="    /assets/resized/atlas-folder-structure-320x335.jpg 320w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-folder-structure.jpg 466w" /></p>

<p>My main categories of notes are</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hacking - this corresponds to the various hacking and programing related work I undertake in the year. My many incomplete tinkerings and side projects find their home here.</li>
  <li>History - I am a big history buff and the books I read, podcasts I listen to or documentaries I watch, become notes here.</li>
  <li>Learnings - new habits, skills, ideas, etc that I learn during the year.</li>
  <li>RJ - My son RJ is 2 years old and this keeps track of his antics, memories, activities and plans.</li>
  <li>Sikhi and I - this is where I keep track of my spiritual journey and learnings from Sikh history and religious texts</li>
  <li>Readings - this is where I keep track of the books I read and the lessons from them</li>
</ul>

<p>The 2022 Atlas file is an MoC of all these MoC’s that acts as the main dashboard that helps me keep track of what I’ve done in the year. It looks something like this.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-1.jpg" alt="Atlas file using dashboard and banner extensions" srcset="    /assets/resized/atlas-1-320x230.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/atlas-1-480x344.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/atlas-1-800x574.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-1.jpg 2288w" />
 I use the popular dashboard++ method along with the banner plugin to make it a little more presentable and pleasing to look at. You can watch the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AatZl1Z_n-g">video by Sergio </a> to see how to do it.</p>

<h5 id="automatic-references">Automatic references</h5>

<p>By keeping a track of all my new goals, readings, initiatives, etc in their respective MoC’s, I automatically keep updating my Atlas file which references these MoCs. This way I can see how my year is shaping up and make changes. You can also use the <a href="https://github.com/blacksmithgu/obsidian-dataview">Dataview plugin</a> to automatically bring up specific notes.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-2.jpg" alt="Atlas file with dataview queries" srcset="    /assets/resized/atlas-2-320x192.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/atlas-2-480x288.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/atlas-2-800x480.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/atlas-2.jpg 2234w" /></p>

<p>For example I use the #NeedsWork tag on notes that I need to work on and I can then automatically use dataview queries (code snippet below) to have them all in my Atlas file for easy reference to what I need to work on.</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$=dv.list(dv.pages('#NeedsWork').sort(f=&gt;f.file.name,"desc").limit(10).file.link)</code></p>

<p>I also keep track of all my daily reflections in one place in the Atlas so that I know how many days I have kept up this habit in the year thus far.</p>

<p>That’s all I have for now. I hope this helps you in some way. In my next post I will describe my method of keeping track of my daily reflections and how I use them to keep myself motivated and on track.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The easiest way to keep oneself motivated and on track is to have some sort of visual markers that depict how far we’ve come. In this post, I try to describe a method I use to keep track of my year in Obsidian. It is inspired by the ACCESS method of organising knowledge developed by Nick Milo. I don’t follow it to the T but I use the “Atlas” concept (A in ACCESS) described by Nick, as a way to visualise my year.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goldilocks Zones in life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/goldilocks-zones-in-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goldilocks Zones in life" /><published>2022-12-09T22:07:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-12-09T22:07:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/its-goldilocks-everywhere</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/goldilocks-zones-in-life/"><![CDATA[<p>In a Chemistry lab, for specific reactions to take place, we often need just the right kind of conditions. Not too warm, not too cold. Often it is the last drop of the reactive agent that induces the reaction. Our planet Earth too, is said to be in the perfectly right orbit, at the perfectly right distance from the Sun, has just the right chemical composition, the right amount of water, etc, to sustain life. This effect is popularly called the Goldilocks zone (alluding to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goldilocks_and_the_Three_Bears">story of the three bears</a> with three porridges of varrying degree of hotness, of three beds in different sizes, etc). The Goldilocks zone is the range of values that are just right for a particular reaction to take place.</p>

<p>It is amazing how often one comes across this effect in life.</p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-a-good-life">The Goldilocks zone of a good life</h3>

<p>A good life is also a delicate goldilocks zone. In his book The Sweet Spot, Paul Bloom talks about the Goldilocks zone of happiness. Too much of Eudaimonia (seeking a higher purpose or goal in everything we do) and it is likely to make us feel depressed. Too little Hedonia (seeking personal happiness often through material goods) and we’re left sad. We need to balance both, meaning in our pursuits and short term pleasure, for living a truly good life. He calls this <em>motivational pluralism</em> and it highlights the importance of having a variety of goals along with being present to enjoy the everyday small things.</p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-confidence">The Goldilocks zone of confidence</h3>

<p>There is a just right amount of confidence that is good for us. More, and we become jerks and a little less and we are frustrated with our lack of competence. Eric Barker, in his book, Barking up the wrong tree, argues that in theory overconfidence is worse than feeling of being incompetent as incompetent people are generally not posted in positions of power. It is also linked to the Dunning Kruger effect, where people who are incompetent at a task, overestimate their competence (primarily due to their failure in understanding the intricacies of the task).</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence.png" alt="Goldilocks Zone of Confidence" srcset="    /assets/resized/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence-320x118.png 320w,    /assets/resized/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence-480x176.png 480w,    /assets/resized/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence-800x294.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/goldilocks-zone-of-confidence.png 1846w" /></p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-flow">The Goldilocks zone of Flow</h3>

<p>Flow, the esoteric productivity mirage we all want to enjoy while working, also, unsurprisingly, appears in a just the right set of conditions. To define simply, flow is when you are rapt in work, challenged sufficiently, gaining mastery and making clear progress. It is when work becomes game. It, too, has a Goldilocks zone. Neither too hard nor too boring. Just like a game that is too hard to start or too easy to finish isn’t much fun, flow, too lies in the zone between skill and challenge.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/flow-skill-challenge.jpeg" alt="Flow at the right zone between Skill and Challenge" srcset="    /assets/resized/flow-skill-challenge-320x320.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/flow-skill-challenge-480x480.jpeg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/flow-skill-challenge.jpeg 640w" /></p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-give-and-take">The Goldilocks zone of give and take</h3>

<p>In his book All you have to do is ask, Wayne Baker talks about giving and receiving help. He says being overly giving can be too demanding and also lead to burnout. On the other hand, being overly selfish can lead to loneliness and depression.
Giving and receiving both are shown to be linked to mental well-being so there are benefits to both and ideally, well you guessed it, we should have just the right balance.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/giver-requestors.png" alt="Strive to become a giver requestor" srcset="    /assets/resized/giver-requestors-320x210.png 320w,    /assets/resized/giver-requestors-480x314.png 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/12/giver-requestors.png 800w" /></p>

<h3 id="the-goldilocks-zone-of-an-effective-apology">The Goldilocks zone of an effective apology</h3>

<p>Timing of an apology is one of the most important aspects of it. There is a range of time when issuing an apology is effective and meaningful. One can apologise too quickly or too late. Apologise too quickly and risk being coming across as insincere and robotic. Apologise too slowly and risk coming across as unremorseful. The right time to apologise is when you have had time to reflect on your actions and have a clear understanding of the impact of your actions on the other person but not too much time that it offers little or no value to the other person.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a> about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="Human Psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a Chemistry lab, for specific reactions to take place, we often need just the right kind of conditions. Not too warm, not too cold. Often it is the last drop of the reactive agent that induces the reaction. Our planet Earth too, is said to be in the perfectly right orbit, at the perfectly right distance from the Sun, has just the right chemical composition, the right amount of water, etc, to sustain life. This effect is popularly called the Goldilocks zone (alluding to the story of the three bears with three porridges of varrying degree of hotness, of three beds in different sizes, etc). The Goldilocks zone is the range of values that are just right for a particular reaction to take place.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BS detection 101</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bs-detection-101/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BS detection 101" /><published>2022-11-12T14:07:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-11-12T14:07:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bs-detection-101</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bs-detection-101/"><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I am trying to describe 5 methods I use regularly to avoid being made a sucker. This in no way an exhaustive list, but I hope it will help you in your day to day life.</p>

<h2 id="when-it-doesnt-add-up">When it “doesn’t add up”</h2>

<p>Scott Adams, the man behind the affable Dilbert cartoon, in his book “How to fail at everything”, described his BS detection method as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li>See if what you’re hearing matches your own personal experience.</li>
  <li>Does any scientific data back the claims being made?</li>
  <li>Does your friends’ experience or experience of those you know match the claims being made?</li>
  <li>Does common sense agree with it?</li>
  <li>Finally, what do the experts in the field say about it?</li>
</ol>

<p>Shoot for consistencies across these parameters to evaluate if something is true or fiction. For example, if you read a study that says eating chocolate cake helps in weight loss and your personal experience and friends’ experience suggests otherwise plus common sense that eating high caloric food cannot lead to weight loss, you can say with some surety that it’s BS.</p>

<h2 id="look-for-assymetries-in-risk">Look for assymetries in risk</h2>

<p>This is the easiest strategy to detect BS when it comes to financial matters. Usually comes in handy when you’re being sold financial planning or asset management. If you detect that by conducting the business in the manner presented, the other party stands to risk a lot less (usually 0) in comparison to you, that’s the moment to rethink things.</p>

<p>This is also often called the agency cost, ie. the cost we incur by relying on authority figures or experts who have no “skin in the game” by doing their business (ex: managing our assets). For optimum results, their incentives must be aligned with ours. If you lose money, they should too. If you hurt yourself, they should suffer as well. The technical term for this is “moral hazard”  - where the risk taker is immune to the effects of her actions.</p>

<h2 id="complicated-statistics-or-data">Complicated statistics or data</h2>

<p>In business and in life, always choose simplicity. Whenever you find yourself at the receiving end of a series of complicated statistics, it’s a red flag. The more complicated the data, the more likely it is to be manipulated or cherry picked to suit a particular narrative. Always spend some time going over the data in an open minded fashion while also asking for more data that may be related and that may help you make the decision. Always remember, “what you see is not all there is”.</p>

<h2 id="use-of-compliance-techniques">Use of compliance techniques</h2>

<p>Bob Cialdini, in his seminal book <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-robert-cialdinis-influence/">Influence</a>, described a series of influencing techniques used by people who gain something from getting you to comply to their seemingly inoccuous requests. He called these people “compliance practioners” - you can imagine them all to be car salesmen.</p>

<p>Look out for these 6 techniques.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Pretending to be like you by saying they have friends in the same city or grew up in your part of world. We all like people like us and this gives them an edge.</li>
  <li>Anchoring you to a higher price to move your baseline and getting you to overspend. The most common example is a realtor showing you two bad properties and then the one they want to sell you.</li>
  <li>Offering you free food or samples to trigger your reciprocity drive (it’s way too powerful) and get you to buy something.</li>
  <li>Telling you about other people you know who did business with them and give you social proof that they are reliable and trustworthy.</li>
  <li>Proclaiming support of “experts” (who may not even be real experts or even if they are, they are usually paid to do it). The most common example of this is people pretending to be dentists appearing on toothpaste ads on TV.</li>
  <li>Getting you to create a self image for yourself in your mind. Once a self image is created, you are forced to remain consistent with it by doing things you may not otherwise do. Imagine walking down the street and someone asks you if you care about the environment. You say yes and they pull out a donation form for an environmental charity. You will be forced to donate to the charity.</li>
</ol>

<p>These can all be used in combination as well so be on the lookout for when more than one of them is being employed together.</p>

<h2 id="looking-the-part">Looking the part</h2>

<p>Taleb, in his book, Skin in the game, described how appearances can persuade us. We all want our doctors to “look the part”. They should be refined and polished and should “look like a doctor”. Taleb argues that if looks are so persuasive, then it probably means that we should strive to find a doctor who doesn’t look like a doctor. The logic is that if, they don’t look the part, and yet are still where they are, then they must be really good as they have overcome the bias against them. This is counter intuitive but seems to make sense once you start thinking how biases work and how other people perceive you.</p>

<p>To be honest this one isn’t something I have been able to avoid yet. I still prefer my doctor to look like a polished doctor, my financial advisor to wear a suit and my restaurants by how clean its glass windows are and how well lit it is. But I am trying to be more open minded about this.</p>

<p><em>More on this list as I make more BS detection rules.</em></p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a> about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this post, I am trying to describe 5 methods I use regularly to avoid being made a sucker. This in no way an exhaustive list, but I hope it will help you in your day to day life.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Algorithms for life - 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Algorithms for life - 2" /><published>2022-10-16T12:07:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-10-16T12:07:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-2/"><![CDATA[<p>In my last post <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/algorithms-for-life-part-1/">part 1 of Algorithms for life</a>, I discussed some learnings from the book
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Algorithms-to-Live-By-audiobook/dp/B01D24NAL6/ref=sr_1_1?crid=56G25J7CEAT3&amp;keywords=algorithms+to+live+by&amp;qid=1664875020&amp;qu=eyJxc2MiOiIyLjA0IiwicXNhIjoiMS42MyIsInFzcCI6IjEuNzQifQ%3D%3D&amp;sprefix=algorithms+to+live+by%2Caps%2C1282&amp;sr=8-1">Algorithms to live by</a>. This post is the continuation of the same. Let’s jump right into it.</p>

<h3 id="probability-in-life">Probability in life</h3>

<p>This is one of the meaty parts of the book. Life is filled with probabilistic occurances and those who can navigate uncertainity, generally live a much more fulfilling life. The book discusses Bayes theorem which is about using “priors” or existing knowledge about a given situation to make predictions about the future. I have discussed Baye’s theorem in detail in my post on my post on <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-thinking-fast-slow-part-1/">Thinking fast &amp; slow</a>.</p>

<p>The Laplace’s law can be used to make general predictions after a series of observations. Imagine having to predict the percentage of overall winning tickets in a lottery after seeing how many tickets won in the latest 10 draws. The law states that the probability of a winning ticket is the number of winning tickets in the last 10 draws plus 1, divided by the total number of tickets drawn plus 1.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>(w+1)/(n+1)
where <em>w</em> is the number of winning tickets and <em>n</em> is the total number of tickets drawn.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So if in the first 10 draws, there were 2 winners, the probability of a winning ticket in the next draw is 3/11. This is a very simple example but it can be used to make predictions in a lot of situations.</p>

<p>Another interesting principle to internalise is the Copernican principle (also known as the Lindy effect) which formalises the intuition that old is gold. Something that has been around for x years, is likely to continue to stay around for x more years. This principle was used in World War II to estimate how many tanks the Germans were producing every month by looking at the VIN numbers of the tanks found by the Allies.</p>

<p>Finally, one of the most important concepts in probability is the distributions that surround us. A distribution describes the likelihood of occurances in a group setup. Normal distribution or the bell curve distribution, has more occurances in the centre. You can make average predictions and be right most of the time, for example, someone at the median age is likely to live more than someone who is very near the extremes of the curve. Power law distributions are in which events are not normal and most items are not clustered around the average but lie in some specific extremes. Events like box office earnings, venture capital returns, etc, follow the power law. The book also discusses Erlang distributions which can be thought of as an intermediate between normal and power law distributions, where the tails are fatter than normal but not as fat as power law distributions. In events following erlang distributions the predictions can be constant. For example, the number of people who will show up at a party is likely to be constant or the amount of time people spend on a call is likely to be constant. Erlang distributions are also used in call centres to estimate the number of agents required to handle a given number of calls.</p>

<h3 id="overfitting">Overfitting</h3>

<p>Overfitting is when we try to fit a model to a given situation and end up making it too complex. In life too, we tend to overthink and develop a complicated understanding of what’s happening around us. In reality, truth is often far too simple. Overfitting is a common problem in machine learning and the way to avoid it, is to add a regularisation parameter which penalises the model for being too complex. In life, we can use the same principle to avoid overfitting. We can use the principle of Occam’s razor to avoid overfitting. Occam’s razor states that the simplest explanation is the most likely to be true. This is a very powerful principle to keep in mind. This probably also explains our evolutionary wiring of heuristics and our inhrent fast thinking.</p>

<h3 id="a-bit-of-randomness-goes-a-long-way">A bit of randomness goes a long way</h3>

<p>Taleb has written extensively about how to avoid being fooled by randomness and also how to build yourself to thrive in uncertainity. This book discusses an interesting concept of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simulated_annealing">annealing</a> which is a process of letting a system warm up (introducing randomness) and then cool down (perform optimisations like hill climbing to reach a local maxima) and doing these regularly to hit what seems like a global maxima. This technique was used by the authors of this famous paper to design chips with more transistors than other known techniques of the time.</p>

<p>Introducing a bit of randomness can be used to break stale mates and direct us towards more creative solutions. <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/team-playbook/plays/disruptive-brainstorming#instructions">Disruptive brainstorming</a> sessions, like the one described by Atlassian, are quite popular where random concepts are introduced to direct the participants to incorporate them in their ideas, often leading to novel innovations.</p>

<p>One other advantage of randomness is using it to create algorithms like Bloom filters that us to be somewhat sure of our solution quickly rather than seek out the perfectly optimal solution everytime. Contrary to common belief, this is quite preferable in many situations like cyber security.</p>

<h3 id="game-theory-in-action">Game theory in action</h3>

<p>Game theory is a deep field that studies how people interact in different situations. Looked at through this lens, almost all interactions are games with each player looking to maximise their payoffs. The famous prisoners dillema is a game where two players are put in a situation where they can either cooperate or defect. If both players cooperate, they both get a payoff of 3. If both defect, they both get a payoff of 1. If one player defects and the other cooperates, the defector gets a payoff of 5 and the cooperator gets a payoff of 0. In this situation defecting is the optimal strategy for both players. The book discusses how this game is played in real life and how it can be used to make predictions about how people will behave in different situations.</p>

<p>Price of anarchy is the difference between the payoffs arising due to the “always defect” and “always hold out”, i.e. 100% competitive and 100% cooperative strategies in a prisoners dillemma like game. A low price of anarchy means the system is stable and doesn’t need a managing centralised authority. A high price of anarchy on the other hand, like the one described in the prisoner’s dillema above, requires external intervention. The book discusses how the price of anarchy can be used to predict the stability of a system and also to design mechanisms around us. The classic problem of tragedy of commons. The profits from overgrazing common land accrue to you alone while the losses, get amortized over everyone. This is a classic case of a high price of anarchy.</p>

<p>Mechanism design is the reverse of game theory. It is utilising our knowledge of equilibriums and creating a game where the equilibrium is beneficial for all the players. Imagine in the prisoners dillemma there is a Godfather of a crime syndicate that bans defection in jails (or else the accused sleeps with the fish). This will move the equilibrium from always defect to always hold out.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a> about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my last post part 1 of Algorithms for life, I discussed some learnings from the book Algorithms to live by. This post is the continuation of the same. Let’s jump right into it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Algorithms for life - 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Algorithms for life - 1" /><published>2022-10-04T14:07:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-10-04T14:07:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/algorithms-for-life-part-1/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Algorithms-to-Live-By-audiobook/dp/B01D24NAL6/ref=sr_1_1?crid=56G25J7CEAT3&amp;keywords=algorithms+to+live+by&amp;qid=1664875020&amp;qu=eyJxc2MiOiIyLjA0IiwicXNhIjoiMS42MyIsInFzcCI6IjEuNzQifQ%3D%3D&amp;sprefix=algorithms+to+live+by%2Caps%2C1282&amp;sr=8-1">Algorithms to live by</a> is the first book that I read again, right after finishing it. It is filled with practical wisdom and connects real life problems with computing and mathematical theory. In this post and the next, I will try to summarise my key takeaways from the book.</p>

<h3 id="knowing-when-to-stop">Knowing when to stop</h3>

<p>We encounter scenarios in life when we don’t know when is the right time to stop looking for solutions. Think situations like driving through a parking lane while looking for a spot. If you stop and park at the first empty stop, you may have to walk a long way but if you keep looking for a stop closer to the destination, you might miss out on a spot altogether. Mathematically speaking, these situations are called <em>optimal stopping</em> problems. The optimal solution of this problem dictates that you can stop after having looked at 37% of your available options and then go with when you find an option that beats all the others you’ve seen before.</p>

<p>For the first 37% of the time or options, you’re only looking and gathering information (creating a baseline). In some cases the available options could be in the form of time you’ve set to look for a parking. So if you plan on spending 10 mins looking for a spot, spend the first 4 minutes simply exploring the lot and then pick the first one that beats all the previous spots (beat here means matches your criteria best).</p>

<h3 id="balancing-searching-and-sorting">Balancing searching and sorting</h3>

<p>Sorting is arranging items in a certain predefined order so it becomes easier to find a specific item. Like with anything, sorting takes effort and time and this time is well spent if we eventually use the sorted dataset to search for an item. In that sense, sorting and searching are tradeoffs on time. Which algorithm to employ to organise your files, wardrobe or pictures, depends on your specific retrieval needs and it makes sense to spend time thinking about organisation as it will save you time in the long run.</p>

<p>Similarly, in nature, a pecking order can be thought of as a sorting algorith. The objective of this ordering is to make it effortless (read: bloodless) to determine who is dominant in any given situation. Even basic societal rules like respecting your elders, nature’s hierarchies in the wild, basic maritime laws like gross tonnage, etc, are ways of managing the same tradeoff of sort v search.</p>

<h3 id="caching-and-memory">Caching and memory</h3>

<p>Just as sorting allows for faster search, our memory is dependent on how information is organised so it can aid faster retrieval. We have infinite capacity for storing memories but can only spend a finite time searching for memories. Forgetting something, is thus, similar to a cache, an organisation problem 🤯</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/folders.jpg" alt="file used recently goes to the left" srcset="    /assets/resized/folders-320x288.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/folders-480x433.jpg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/10/folders.jpg 800w" />
File used recently goes to the leftmost slot</p>

<p>Something recently used is more likely to be used again and thus must be kept closest to us. The weird looking filing trays we see in some offices, may actually be a smart way to prioritise stuff. The file you used most recently goes back to the leftmost tray and the other ones slide right. That’s it. That’s the algorithm right there.</p>

<p>Since you are likely to need something you used most recently, always go for the left most tray to look for it. This is the Noguchi filing system and it is a real world physical adaptation of the least recently used cache.</p>

<h3 id="scheduling-in-real-life">Scheduling in real life</h3>

<p>There are many different metrics to optimise when it comes to what we should work on. Sometimes the goal is to minimise overall lateness (unit - time, like in case of managing your washer and dryer), sometimes it is to minimise the number of late tasks (unit - number, consuming rotting produce in the fridge in some order) and sometimes it is to reduce the overall waiting time for someone blocked on us (clients who have given us several tasks). Each metric demands its own strategy. The goal must be to balance the different kinds of metrics. For example <em>responsiveness</em> and <em>throughput</em>. Your customer support team may need to be responsive so that your engineers can have throughput and so on.</p>

<p>Sometimes it may just be prudent to get the easiest thing done and out of the way and sometimes it may make sense to spend time to pick the most consequential item and do it first (to reduce the wait of the task with the highest importance/time ). This sounds like a good one size fit-most approach for most scheduling problems.</p>

<p>A common problem emanating from this is <em>thrashing</em>. There is always a fixed bookkeeping cost, no matter what kinds of tasks you have on your plate. When a juggler is given one more ball than he can manage, he doesn’t just drop that ball but all other balls. When tasks steal resources from each other or remove the meta work done by another task to do its own meta work, it is called Thrashing.</p>

<p>Another important concept that comes in handy is <em>interrupt coalescing</em>. This is when you wait for similar tasks to accumulate and do them all at once to save time on bookkeeping each individual task of the same kind. It also saves <em>context switching</em>, which is the time and energy that gets spent on moving from one kind of task to another. Imagine getting interrupted to answer a question while you’re in the middle of writing an email to placate a customer. It takes time to think of the answer, actually answer and then get back to writing the email. The idea therefore must be to minimise interruptions, so you can get all the tasks of one kind done in one go and then move on to the next kind.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a> about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Algorithms to live by is the first book that I read again, right after finishing it. It is filled with practical wisdom and connects real life problems with computing and mathematical theory. In this post and the next, I will try to summarise my key takeaways from the book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The value of procrastination</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-value-of-procrastination/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The value of procrastination" /><published>2022-09-08T14:57:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-09-08T14:57:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-value-of-procrastination</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-value-of-procrastination/"><![CDATA[<p>We recently did our company offsite in the beautiful town of Mussoorie, Northern India (view from our balcony below) and when we were arranging the logistics, I bumped into an interesting scenario. We are a remote team and people were coming from 10 different cities. We wanted people to come in within a window of time, which means not just before a specific time but also after a specific time. There are many reasons why we’d want this but the simple ones are 1. we don’t spend extra on their stay or travel and 2. not have them be inconvenienced of waiting alone for others. This is a simple problem but it highlights an important aspect of life, that it is sometimes imperative to do a specific thing just at the right time and not earlier.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DYN00937-1160x773.jpeg" alt="mussoorie you beauty" srcset="    /assets/resized/DYN00937-1160x773-320x213.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/DYN00937-1160x773-480x320.jpeg 480w,    /assets/resized/DYN00937-1160x773-800x533.jpeg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DYN00937-1160x773.jpeg 1160w" /></p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Wait-Science-Delay-Frank-Partnoy/dp/1610392477/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2Z7DP7ICT63VA&amp;keywords=wait+by+frank+partnoy&amp;qid=1662629397&amp;sprefix=w%2Caps%2C1981&amp;sr=8-1">Frank Partnoy’s Wait</a> is an intriguing book that delves into the idea of how procrastination is a boon (when used correctly) and our natural inclination to sit on decisions may actually be an evolutionary feature and not a bug. It also has some practical insights on how simple techniques can wrap our sense of time and prime us into doing things slowly or faster. For example, we can be primed into cramming lessons faster by simply looking at fast food brands’ logos 🤯</p>

<h3 id="slow-reactions-in-a-fast-world">Slow reactions in a fast world</h3>

<p>Our fast thinking system 1 derails a lot of our careful analysis. We want to conserve energy and so following rudimentary heuristics (like if this scares my sense of self, I will defend my thoughts) helps us avoid spending brain cycles (energy) considering many scenarios in detail. We make broad generalisations and assumptions by having a tiny exposure to an event or situation, appropriately called <em>thin slicing</em>. This can not only lead to bad decisions but may even ignite unconscious racism.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Don’t just do something, stand there”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This was a funny exchange with one of the doctors quoted in the book to make the point that when you’re out of your depth, not immediately doing anything and taking the time to process is the best course of action. The book also describes studies on cricketers and how delayed shot selections often lead to better performance over the years. In professional sports and in life, it makes sense to delay actions as long as is possible.</p>

<p>Whenever we find ourselves in a time bound situation, we must</p>

<ol>
  <li>Assess how much time we have at our disposal</li>
  <li>Delay the final decision to as long as is possible</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="structure-of-a-delayed-reaction">Structure of a delayed reaction</h3>

<p>Popularised by Air Force Colonel John Boyd, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OODA_loop">OODA loop</a> is how we may want to react to scenarios in timelines that span minutes.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Observe – gather info</li>
  <li>Orient – process it and put it in perspective</li>
  <li>Decide – what to do</li>
  <li>Act – execute</li>
</ol>

<p>The same steps can however be applicable to split second decisions too. Thin slicing and knee-jerk reactions overrides our decision making apparatus and so this conscious OODA style slow reacting need practice.</p>

<h3 id="timing-is-everything">Timing is everything</h3>

<p>The book has an absorbing section dedicated to how comedians use timing to great effect. They delay and delay and delay the punch line for its optimal impact. This is true for general speech as well where delays can help in emphasising specific points.</p>

<style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style>
<div class="embed-container">    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/aZwIYjOYr44" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>

<p>Another important aspect of life where timing is of the essence is apologies. There is a Goldilocks zone of apologising, meaning you can apologise both too quickly and too late. Too quickly and people think you don’t mean it and don’t regret your actions. Too late and it’s too late to repair the damage.</p>

<h3 id="time-bias">Time bias</h3>

<p>When we value small gratifications now over big ones down the line (think: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanford_marshmallow_experiment#:~:text=The%20Stanford%20marshmallow%20experiment%20was,for%20a%20period%20of%20time.">marshmallow experiments</a>), we are suffering from a kind of time bias. This isn’t a personality quirk, it is an evolutionary coding.</p>

<p>A negative rate of return is applied on things acquired over time, for ex evaluating how much an amount of money is worth 10 years from now, in today’s terms. A 5% discount rate means something will be less valuable to us by x/ 1.05^n, n years down the line. This is exponential discounting where the discount rate remains the same.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hyperbolic.png" alt="hyperbolic discounting" srcset="    /assets/resized/hyperbolic-320x241.png 320w,    /assets/resized/hyperbolic-480x362.png 480w,    /assets/resized/hyperbolic-800x603.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hyperbolic.png 1090w" /></p>

<p>Many psychological studies have demonstrated deviations in instinctive preference from the constant discount rate. As we get older we prefer instant gratification and so the discounts become hyperbolic i.e. the farther the payoff in the future, the higher the mental discounting.</p>

<p>This can also be thought of as a type of procrastination. When we have high discount rates and what we are dealing with is a cost (like spending time to write a paper) -&gt; we procrastinate. When what we are dealing with is a benefit (having another donut) -&gt; we are acting impatiently. You can take a <a href="https://www.thetimeparadox.com/surveys/">time paradox survey</a> to understand how time biases affect you.</p>

<p>To summarise, don’t be so hard on yourself when you realise you’re procrastinating. Understand your time biases and help yourself and others make better decisions by making use of all the time you have at your disposal.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We recently did our company offsite in the beautiful town of Mussoorie, Northern India (view from our balcony below) and when we were arranging the logistics, I bumped into an interesting scenario. We are a remote team and people were coming from 10 different cities. We wanted people to come in within a window of time, which means not just before a specific time but also after a specific time. There are many reasons why we’d want this but the simple ones are 1. we don’t spend extra on their stay or travel and 2. not have them be inconvenienced of waiting alone for others. This is a simple problem but it highlights an important aspect of life, that it is sometimes imperative to do a specific thing just at the right time and not earlier.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where good ideas come from</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/where-good-ideas-come-from/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where good ideas come from" /><published>2022-08-17T13:03:51+05:30</published><updated>2022-08-17T13:03:51+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/where-good-ideas-come-from</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/where-good-ideas-come-from/"><![CDATA[<p>In his remarkable book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Where-Good-Ideas-Come-From-audiobook/dp/B0045BXDAO/ref=sr_1_1?crid=5E941XBSFJ7F&amp;keywords=where+good+ideas+come+from&amp;qid=1660721659&amp;sprefix=wher%2Caps%2C4011&amp;sr=8-1">Where Good Ideas Come From</a>, Steven Johnson, illustrates the important aspects of creating an environment that can lead to birth of good ideas. He uses historical examples to highlight how specific features in the environment, directly led to the rise of world changing ideas like the Gutenberg press, the omnipresent post-it note and many life saving medical innovations. Before we dive into them, it would be best to understand the concept of Fractal patterns.</p>

<h5 id="fractal-patterns">Fractal patterns</h5>

<p>A fractal is a Mathematical curve that is self repeating. We can think of these as patterns that are infinitely repeating as we zoom in or out of anything (see image below).</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fractal.jpeg" alt="Fractal – image courtesy Pinterest.com " srcset="    /assets/resized/fractal-320x240.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/fractal-480x360.jpeg 480w,    /assets/resized/fractal-800x600.jpeg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fractal.jpeg 1024w" /></p>

<p>Most innovation patterns are fractal in nature, i.e. they appear both at super high zoomed out levels, for ex our mega cities and at micro levels, eg our cellular structure. The reason this is probably true is because innovation, much like cellular reproduction depends on similar factors like exponential growth, adaptations, survival, etc, which in turn are affected by similar conditions.</p>

<h5 id="the-adjacent-possible">The Adjacent Possible</h5>

<p>First order innovations or evolutions can often lead to many times more innovative and often unanticipated creations many cycles later. The primordial soup led to the birth of organic life but it began with basic chemicals like Carbon Dioxide, Methane, Ammonia and some amino acids. Formaldehyde was a first order innovation and millions of cycles/years later we had humans walking the earth.</p>

<p>The adjacent possible is often a tiny improvement or evolution that is not remarkable on its own but opens up a new pathway of thinking about things.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>He took a machine designed to get people drunk and turned it into an engine for mass communication</p>
</blockquote>

<h5 id="slow-hunches">Slow Hunches</h5>

<p>Simply put, slow hunches, as the name suggests, are ideas taking shape in our subconscious, slowly. This concept challenges how we think about Eureka moments. Johnson says ideas don’t come to us in flashes but develop in our subconscious slowly. There’s usually no one single Eureka moment; or to say it differently, the Eureka moment takes a long time to build.</p>

<p>The author gives many examples in which ideas didn’t appear fully formed but remained hazy for quite a long period of time, continually alluding to something important. The example that has stayed with me is that of the famous pre-911 Phoenix memos. In the memos an FBI analyst described his hunch of possible terror threats related to aviation, after having come across news of many flight schools reporting suspicious behaviours by foreign nationals. The memo was shot down as being vague and speculative. A few months later, 911 happened.</p>

<p>Environments that want to support innovation need to be slow, support hypothesising, conjecturing, making errors and should not focus on instant gratification. They should also be open enough that slow hunches forming in different individuals can collide amongst each other.</p>

<h5 id="liquid-networks">Liquid Networks</h5>

<p>True to the fractal nature of innovation, liquid networks are found everywhere in nature. Carbon atoms alone couldn’t have made life possible. They needed the primordial soup to enable free combinations of various atoms and molecules. Similarly, our brain is a dense network of neurons that support trillions on synaptic connections, allowing us to explore the intermingling of ideas.</p>

<style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style>
<div class="embed-container">    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/pNeaF0ypnCQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>

<p>Open exchange of ideas is almost directly linked to innovation. It is thus a matter of no wonder that almost all software today in the world is at least in some sense dependent on the work of open source communities that build over and improve existing open source code. The open nature of innovation is often challenged with the question of incentives, i.e. if every innovation is open and available for copying/modification, what incentive is there to innovate. The answer is it’s a tradeoff.</p>

<p>The more open an innovation is, the more likely it is to spread and adapt and evolve. The more closed, patented or walled an innovation is, the less is its impact on producing further innovation. True innovation lies in the delicate balance of free markets and university style academic research. Neither of them stand alone on their own and neither can claim to bring the promised goodness of the said innovation, without the other.</p>

<p>One of the more important aspects of open networks, or rather what supports it, is written notes. Writing down our learnings or experiences is a great way to support both germination of ones own slow hunches, and allowing others to explore the adjacent possible of what we’re dealing with. One of the more prolific note keepers known to us was Charles Darwin whose field notes inspired the theory of evolution. <a href="https://fs.blog/john-locke-common-place-book/#:~:text=The%20object%20to%20Locke's%20%E2%80%9CCommon,initial%20letter%20and%20first%20vowel.">John Locke’s commonplace books</a> were another innovative note keeping technique that made for totally different subjects to be entered in the same page, or succession of pages, allowing easy intermingling of ideas and sparking possible adaptations.</p>

<p><em>If you’re interested in note keeping, I use Obsidian and have written about <a href="https://infermuse.com/obsidian-workflow-for-book-notes/">organising book notes</a> and <a href="https://infermuse.com/daily-planning-with-momentum-devices/">daily planning workflow</a>.</em></p>

<h5 id="errors-lead-to-innovations">Errors lead to innovations</h5>

<p>Just as DNA copying is error prone and leads to interesting innovations and changes, some noise in the environment can act as a catalyst for germination of new ideas. There are countless examples of errors leading upto groundbreaking discoveries. The famous one is that of the triode (vacuum tube) which Lee De Forest invented mistaking it to be something totally different. He was thinking he had discovered gas powered signal tracking but it eventually led to amplification of electrical signal and something that powers almost all our electronic gadgets. An environment that does not shoot down erroneous conclusions stands to gain from the scientific insights that come from failure.</p>

<h5 id="exaptation">Exaptation</h5>

<p>Exaptation is the transformed use of something that evolved or was invented to do something totally different. Assimilating concepts and concocting new alternate ways of using them dates back almost a thousand years. The movable type press invented by Gutenberg was inspired by the screw fix wine making devices that were ubiquitous in the early 15th century in the Rhine area. This is where the importance of variety of experiences come in and why possessing <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Range-Generalists-Triumph-Specialized-World/dp/0735214506/ref=sr_1_1?crid=FVJPR43TBTDZ&amp;keywords=Range&amp;qid=1660724216&amp;sprefix=r%2Caps%2C574&amp;sr=8-1">Range</a> seems to be so important.</p>

<p>We need amalgamation of different contexts and ideas to generate exaptation. A coffee house is known to have encouraged this amalgamation. Open cafeterias and water coolers are a great way to encourage this in your team/organisation.</p>

<hr />

<p>To summarise, in the last 200 years, most of our world changing innovations have come from networks and collaborative efforts. Sole individuals or companies tinkering with things in their labs have had a minute impact on the world.</p>

<p>The key component of an environment that produces innovation is collaboration and open networks. A slow paced culture that encourages slow hunches and inculcates a habit of not being dismayed by errors. Only those ideas that are liberated amount to massive changes. Ideas that are copied, improved, distributed become better and end up changing the world. This is why in recent times mere economic motive doesn’t lead to big innovations as that means protecting ones ideas from the improvements done by ones competition.</p>

<hr />
<p>I run a startup called Harmonize. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, I tweet about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Business &amp;amp; Entrepreneurship" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In his remarkable book Where Good Ideas Come From, Steven Johnson, illustrates the important aspects of creating an environment that can lead to birth of good ideas. He uses historical examples to highlight how specific features in the environment, directly led to the rise of world changing ideas like the Gutenberg press, the omnipresent post-it note and many life saving medical innovations. Before we dive into them, it would be best to understand the concept of Fractal patterns.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Daily planning with momentum devices</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daily-planning-with-momentum-devices/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Daily planning with momentum devices" /><published>2022-07-16T12:24:10+05:30</published><updated>2022-07-16T12:24:10+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daily-planning-with-momentum-devices</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daily-planning-with-momentum-devices/"><![CDATA[<p>Momentum is a great thing to have in any situation. If we have positive momentum, same problems can appear easier than when we are starting with no momentum. I am using the word momentum to loosely refer to <em>some tiny progress in the positive direction</em>. All video games are designed to give us quick instant feedback and easy starts to give us a sense of momentum (and gratification). It is this momentum (and of course other stuff like shots of dopamine) that has us spending hours tackling tough problems while actually “playing”. In this post I expand how I try to leverage momentum in my daily planning.</p>

<h5 id="tiny-progress--starting-from-scratch">Tiny progress &gt;&gt; starting from scratch</h5>

<p>Making tiny progress in the right direction to give ourselves some momentum has incredible effects on our productivity. I’ve come to realise that setting fitness goals like 10k steps a day become doable if I get up on time and do 2k steps by 7am. Doing 2k steps is easy and a much smaller goal in the larger scheme of things and once done, there’s a positive feeling that the goal is not that daunting anymore. I don’t necessarily understand the psychology of this but I suppose it is the opposite of the “what the heck” effect which we feel when what lies ahead of us seems insurmountable.</p>

<p>Similarly, writing is hard, especially a long blog post, so instead, I try to create a skeleton comprising some bullet points to give myself a positive momentum for when I eventually get around to working on it. The same is true for daily planning. If you’ve got a todo list, you know what you are going to do first and it is likely you’ll have a productive day. This point of “making time for traction”, was discussed at length in the book <a href="https://infermuse.com/lessons-from-indistractable/">Indistractable</a> but I think we can take it a step further.</p>

<h5 id="todo-list-">Todo list ++</h5>

<p>Don’t just make a todo list, expand the first few items of your list to make some progress on them so you start your day with positive momentum. To clarify, this isn’t faking progress, but rather getting yourself some scaffolding to have a good start to whatever you’re trying to do.</p>

<p>In the image below, I show a daily note. My daily todo list is basically a set of notes in Obsidian and each daily note is linked to specific notes (so the “Purpose Hunt” and “Range” are notes linked to this daily note). If you use Obsidian, the calendar extension works well for daily planning.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/daily-planning.png" alt="Daily note in obsidian" srcset="    /assets/resized/daily-planning-320x282.png 320w,    /assets/resized/daily-planning-480x424.png 480w,    /assets/resized/daily-planning-800x706.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/daily-planning.png 902w" /></p>

<p>When I plan my todo list, I try to make some progress on some of the items. This could be putting together a rough skeleton of what I want done, collating links (videos, articles) I can use as a starting point, putting down questions I have so I can start by trying to answer them or simply inserting a reusable template (think skeleton) for the specific task.</p>

<h5 id="templates">templates</h5>

<p>The image below shows my template for an app idea. I use this to put some structure to an idea I have. Template notes are a great way to get some quick momentum as they are reusable and give you a starting direction.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/app-idea-template-1160x1132.png" alt="APP idea template" srcset="    /assets/resized/app-idea-template-1160x1132-320x312.png 320w,    /assets/resized/app-idea-template-1160x1132-480x468.png 480w,    /assets/resized/app-idea-template-1160x1132-800x781.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/app-idea-template-1160x1132.png 1160w" /></p>

<p>To summarise, don’t just make a todo list, expand your items to give yourself some momentum. It is imperative to spending time to make early progress on items you will pick up later. The right time to do this is perhaps the planning stage itself or may be scheduling time for “adding momentum” to your long term goals, as separate todo items during the week.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Momentum is a great thing to have in any situation. If we have positive momentum, same problems can appear easier than when we are starting with no momentum. I am using the word momentum to loosely refer to some tiny progress in the positive direction. All video games are designed to give us quick instant feedback and easy starts to give us a sense of momentum (and gratification). It is this momentum (and of course other stuff like shots of dopamine) that has us spending hours tackling tough problems while actually “playing”. In this post I expand how I try to leverage momentum in my daily planning.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to argue</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-argue/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to argue" /><published>2022-06-19T10:58:27+05:30</published><updated>2022-06-19T10:58:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-argue</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-argue/"><![CDATA[<p>I sort of cheated with the title of this post. It’s going to be less “how to argue” and more “with what mindset to walk into a discussion”. Today, we all have super fast access to facts at our finger tips, one would have thought that would bring us all together as we all gravitate towards the truth, but nothing could be further from reality.</p>

<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/s7uHDGT8SoJAQ/giphy.gif" width="60%" align="center" /></p>

<p>The reality is there is no one truth. There are versions of a story that are consistent with our world views. When we hear something that challenges our world views, we feel threatened. This is the same kind of threat our ancestors faced in the wild and it produces nearly an identical flight or fight response. We all have noticed our counterparts flare up and get angry. You can bet nothing fruitful ever emanates from two parties that are dealing with their prehistoric brains in a fight for survival. Here’s a few tips you can keep in mind while walking into an argument.</p>

<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/IgsXOXGPxfT3O/giphy.gif" width="60%" align="center" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>The zeroth law of walking into an argument is to have an open mind and be curious about learning more about your counterparts. You really can’t fake this. The idea of a discussion or a debate should be to expand the combined consciousness of the group and not to “win” the other side over. In short, be curious about the other opinions.</li>
  <li>Start by laying down the points of agreement. Starting with the common ground allows everyone to start on a positive note. Seek out integration instead of pushing your ideas or trying to win.</li>
  <li>Focus on one or two main arguments. When we use many arguments our opponents can get fixated on the weakest one and counter those.</li>
  <li>Beware reactance (when people disagree with what they are being told, despite originally agreeing with it). Fight the urge to correct people. This is especially important as more facts never help. People make opinions aka snap judgements and then once made, don’t let facts get in their way.</li>
  <li>The simplest way to disarming your counterparts is to start by addressing their emotions. You can also use the opportunity to settle them down and make them feel safe by saying you’re not challenging their views or trying to change their opinions. In every discussion we all want to project ourselves in a certain way. Understand that your counterpart is also trying to project some face and let them have it. Acknowledge their status.</li>
  <li>Don’t stick to common scripted arguments. Use novelty as our brains are wired to seek novelty. When you’re interesting, people pay attention to what you’re saying.</li>
  <li>Try to control your anger and emotions. Do not escalate. Only use anger and hostility carefully, rarely, and it should ideally come as a surprise.</li>
</ol>

<p>Most of these tips come from the two books <a href="https://infermuse.com/notes-from-conflicted-by-ian-leslie/">Conflicted</a> and <a href="https://infermuse.com/lessons-from-youre-not-listening/">You’re not listening</a>. I highly recommend both.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I sort of cheated with the title of this post. It’s going to be less “how to argue” and more “with what mindset to walk into a discussion”. Today, we all have super fast access to facts at our finger tips, one would have thought that would bring us all together as we all gravitate towards the truth, but nothing could be further from reality.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Obsidian notes meet OpenAI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/obsidian-notes-meet-openai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Obsidian notes meet OpenAI" /><published>2022-05-30T10:10:05+05:30</published><updated>2022-05-30T10:10:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/obsidian-notes-meet-openai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/obsidian-notes-meet-openai/"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous post, I discussed how my approach to <a href="https://infermuse.com/obsidian-workflow-for-book-notes/">keeping book notes in Obsidian</a> tries to leverage the “mo-connections-mo-retention” aspect of our brain. That idea however, is heavily dependent on how we make connections while taking or making notes. Connecting the dots between notes is a “manual” process. One would argue “connecting” is “synthesis” and it needs to be manual and thought out, but surely we can find a better way 😉</p>

<h5 id="connecting-notes">Connecting notes</h5>

<p>I am writing down three methods you can use to find connections between notes. I use a combination of these three but I feel there’s a smarter approach lurking around somewhere.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Memory – recall something that is connecting to something that you’re working on right now (can be highly erratic based on how well you remember your previous notes)</li>
  <li>Unlinked mentions – you can open up the unlinked mentions of the note to see all the other notes where this note is mentioned but not connected. This relies on keywords in your title (it will literally look for your title in other notes) and is non-fuzzy (for good reason). I use the <a href="https://help.obsidian.md/Advanced+topics/YAML+front+matter">aliases in the frontmatter</a> so the search for unlinked mentioned includes the aliases (so your note titled “How to Argue” with aliases “Forming an argument” or “Argumentative Indians” can have a higher chance of being linked elsewhere) but even that is bound by how creative you can get while assigning aliases to your notes.</li>
  <li>Local graph – visually seek nearby items or items that are connected on nth degree</li>
</ul>

<p>The right way to do this would be to leverage the fast growing Artificial Intelligence or Semantic Search algorithms to help us connect the dots that aren’t easily visible.</p>

<h5 id="enter-open-ai-embeddings">Enter Open AI embeddings</h5>

<p>OpenAI is an AI research lab that is pushing out a lot of ready to use AI models that you can use in your applications. Think things like classifications, semantic search, completions, etc.</p>

<p>An “embedding” is a vector representation (in simple terms it is a list of numbers) of a piece of text’s semantic representation across thousands of parameters (think parameters like category, sub category, genre, gender, voice, etc ). The closer the distance between two vectors, the more semantically close they are to each other.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/download.png" alt="CoSINE similarity between two vectors " srcset="    /assets/resized/download-320x64.png 320w,    /assets/resized/download-480x95.png 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/05/download.png 503w" /></p>

<p>To use OpenAI’s models you need to signup to their waitlist. I recently got in and have been blown away by the possibilities. In the rest of this post, I deep dive into the code that I used to run OpenAI’s embeddings system on my notes to find non-obvious connections between my notes.</p>

<p><em>For the purpose of this exercise, I stuck to finding connections between the book notes of my vault which also helped keep the costs down on OpenAI (you get $18 of free credits to get you started and I intend to stretch it as long as I humanely can</em> 😁<em>).</em></p>

<h5 id="the-setup">The setup</h5>

<p>This is going to be a simple 4 step process</p>

<ol>
  <li>Load up all the notes in a Pandas DataFrame to make it easy to run the computations (also easy to load up and dump data in .CSV format)</li>
  <li>Run embeddings on my notes to generate their vector representations and them dump into another .CSV file</li>
  <li>Find the top 5 semantically similar notes by using an algorithm called cosine similarity (distance between two vectors)</li>
</ol>

<h5 id="the-results">The results</h5>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/notes-1160x482.png" alt="" srcset="    /assets/resized/notes-1160x482-320x133.png 320w,    /assets/resized/notes-1160x482-480x199.png 480w,    /assets/resized/notes-1160x482-800x332.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/05/notes-1160x482.png 1160w" /></p>

<p>The long and short of it is I was able to connect ideas I didn’t originally think were related. My notes on <strong>In group bias</strong> found to be connected to <strong>Echo chambers</strong>, notes on <strong>Tunnel vision</strong> connected with <strong>First Principles</strong>, <strong>Implementation Intention</strong> with <strong>Commitment and Consistency</strong> bias and so on. Some of these seem super obvious now but I given had over 700 notes across 55 books, I wasn’t able to connect and synthesise them when i was originally working on them.</p>

<p>My sense is <strong>a semantically capable AI can act as a wingman of sorts</strong> while you make notes. I am way too occupied in my day to day responsibilities to work on an Obsidian plugin but if someone’s interested they are welcome to use my rough code as a foundation. <a href="https://github.com/ujj/obsidian-notes-meets-openai">Here’s the github repo</a>. Happy Hacking!</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my previous post, I discussed how my approach to keeping book notes in Obsidian tries to leverage the “mo-connections-mo-retention” aspect of our brain. That idea however, is heavily dependent on how we make connections while taking or making notes. Connecting the dots between notes is a “manual” process. One would argue “connecting” is “synthesis” and it needs to be manual and thought out, but surely we can find a better way 😉]]></summary></entry></feed>