<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-03T11:22:59+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Infermuse</title><subtitle>Practical wisdom from studies, experiments and books</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What’s the big deal about rationality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/whats-the-big-deal-about-rationality/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s the big deal about rationality" /><published>2024-02-03T09:07:57+05:30</published><updated>2024-02-03T09:07:57+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/whats-the-big-deal-about-rationality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/whats-the-big-deal-about-rationality/"><![CDATA[<p>We often seek out rational reasons for pursuing a course of action. We believe that rationality is the prized jewel of our mental toolkit that will lead us to the best decisions. But is it really so? If rationality is indeed the most important aspect of our decision making, then why is it that evolution has not made us more rational? Why do we have cognitive biases and why do we fall for them so often? In reality, what we call rationality is those aspects of our behaviors that are much easier explain than others. In this post I am going to describe some behaviors that we think are not rational but actually perfectly sound when we dig deeper.</p>

<h3 id="self-deception-as-an-evolutionary-advantage">Self deception as an evolutionary advantage</h3>

<p>Robert Trevor’s theory of self deception is a fascinating one. Imagine the scenario of a dog chasing a hare. If the hare jumps randomly, it has a higher chance of survival as its body would does not given away subtle cues as to the location of its next jump. If it follow a predefined logic or pattern then the dogs would have evolved to spot these cues and would be able to predict their next jump and catch them. Thus, more self conscious hares, who devise patterns, would have gotten eliminated from the gene pool leaving us with unconscious hares. Same goes with us. Being able to deceive ourselves or keep ourselves in the dark, could be an evolutionary tactic. This is why we don’t have enough self knowledge and don’t have access to our real motivations, instincts or compulsions.</p>

<h3 id="herd-mentality-as-a-survival-tactic">Herd mentality as a survival tactic</h3>

<p>Gerd Gigerenzer came up with the idea of <em>defensive decision making</em>. We often berate people for <em>going with the herd</em> and not applying a rational decision making process, however there is more to it than just laziness. Going with the popular default choice lets you avoid making a decision altogether. This decision, to not make a decision, is not designed to maximise welfare for you but rather to minimise the mental damage in case of a bad outcome.</p>

<p>Take the example of picking between the popular airport JFK and its lesser popular cousin, Newark. If you fly from JFK and your flight gets delayed, you blame the airline but if you fly from Newark and your flight gets delayed you blame your decision to fly from Newark. This is why when you make a decision and choose a not so popular option, you will blame yourself as you made a noticeable decision. Blame unlike credit, always finds a home and nobody ever got fired for booking their boss’s flight from JFK.</p>

<h3 id="not-believing-in-miracles-is-mathematically-unsound">Not believing in miracles is mathematically unsound</h3>

<p>Approximately 15 miracles happen in our lives every year. Here’s a back of the hand math for this. Let’s define a miracle as a one in a million event and us staying awake for 12 hours a day. This translates to 43200 waking seconds or recorded data points every day. This adds up to 15 million data points a year or 15 miracles. Due to sheer volume of things happening around us, things that ought not to happen a lot, happen surprisingly often.</p>

<p>I was blown away by this way of thinking about how our beliefs are reinforced. We place a lot importance on our own experiences in the name of rationality and consolidate beliefs held due to irrational reasons. In his book The Believing Brain, Michael Shermer, goes into detail on how beliefs are formed. He talks about Patternicity and Agenticity. These are our evolutionary abilities to spot patterns in noise and assigning them meanings that aren’t really there. He explains how anecdotal learning comes naturally, while science takes effort. We are the descendents of those who could find patterns to survive the dangers that lurked near them. We don’t have a system that overlooks this pattern recognition. Our brain simply runs a cost heuristic - cost of making a false positive error (the bush moving is a tiger) Vs that of the false negative error (its just wind). This is why we make superstitious beliefs, because we cannot distinguish between bad learning and learning.</p>

<h3 id="meaning-trumps-everything-else">Meaning trumps everything else</h3>

<p>In 19th century Prussia during the Nepoleanic wars, the Royal family of Prussia urged all citizens to exchange their gold jewellery and get iron jewellery in return. Yes you read it right, exchange their gold jewellery for iron jewellery. The gold was needed to fund the war efforts and help protect the fatherland. The iron jewellery people received, bore the inscription Gold gab ich für Eisen (I gave gold for iron). This iron jewellery became a different kind of status symbol. While people owning the more valuable gold jewellery signalled affluence, those owning the iron jewellery signalled being affluent and also generous and patriotic.</p>

<p>Meanings associated with things is often dissociated from its core characteristics. Human beings can derive meaning in owning the basest of metals and oddest of jobs. Meaning is what powers engagement and high engagement is the difference between mediocre and great companies. Human beings find value in different ways and it affects perceptions and value. Costly social signals are a way to show exclusivity. Things like fancy envelopes, advertising, expensive real estate, high quality furniture in stores etc are a way to indicate that you have considerable assets on the line and so what you are selling must be really good.</p>

<h3 id="why-do-we-care-about-brand-names">Why do we care about Brand names</h3>

<p>If someone ever questions your choice of buying goods of a specific brand over a lesser priced similar good of a non name brand, you should tell them that there’s actually perfectly legitimate reasoning behind the trust in Brands. Brand names indicate a reputation to uphold. If Samsung ever finds itself with 1000 faulty televisions, it has no incentive to offload those to their customers as they have a reputation to uphold and protect its line of other products that are likely to be affected if people report faulty televisions sold by them. On the other hand someone who has no reputation, has no such incentive. This is why we trust brands. It’s not just to show off, it’s a way to sleep easy knowing you made a good decision. Instead of asking who can sell me the best TV, you are in effect asking who has the most to lose in case they sell me a dud. This is why relying on brands is a worthwhile strategy.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rationality may not be the prized possession we think it is.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The six step decision making process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/6-step-decision-making-process/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The six step decision making process" /><published>2024-01-13T10:12:27+05:30</published><updated>2024-01-13T10:12:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/6-step-decision-making-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/6-step-decision-making-process/"><![CDATA[<p>‘How to decide’ by Annie Duke is a wholly practical book that helps you make better decisions. It comes with a unique set of tools and exercises that you can do while you’re reading it to imbibe the concepts better. This and her previous book, Thinking in bets, are highly recommended if you’re interested in honing your decision making skills. In this post, I will talk about the six step decision making process she describes. This method is in stark contrast with the flat pros and cons list that we’re used to. The six step decision making process is a living framework that grows with your decisions and helps you better understand the complexity of life.</p>

<p>Before talking about the process, it makes sense to lay the foundation of how decisions should be evaluated. The quality of the decisions have to be evaluated on the basis of the process that led to it. Hindsight bias is when we twist the reality of past events to match our present outcomes and making it appear like it was inevitable. This is also called memory creep when what we know after the fact creeps into the knowledge we had before the fact. Be wary of “I told you so”, “I should’ve known” or “I knew it all along”. These are indications of hindsight bias. This also applies to evaluating a decision someone else has made. Taking the time to figure out what was and was not known at the time of the decision is also empathetic.</p>

<p>Now let’s jump into the decision making process. The decision making process is driven by 3 Ps - Preferences, Payoffs and Probabilities. We employee these 3Ps in the various steps, helping us navigate the decision making process.</p>

<h3 id="step-1-identitying-the-outcomes">Step 1: Identitying the outcomes</h3>

<p>The first step in the decision making process is to identify the possible outcomes and draw a kind of decision tree. In this tree each node is a decision and out of which different outcomes span out and then each of those becomes a sort of timeline. From each decision a separate timeline can emerge more, leading to a decision multiverse (think Avengers Endgame).</p>

<p>Your reality is a function of all the decisions and their outcomes but you live only one timeline but it could have played out in so many different ways. The decision multiverse can help you visualise different decisions playing out differently and help put into perspective our one reality amongst all the possible ones. The key is to start writing down possible decisions, their outcomes and the timelines that emerge from them.</p>

<h3 id="step-2-identifying-the-preferences">Step 2: Identifying the preferences</h3>

<p>In the decision tree you’ve got in the previous step, we start assigning preferences based on the payoffs expected from each decision. Having a clear understanding of the payoffs is important to make a good decision. The payoffs can be monetary or non-monetary. For example, if you’re deciding whether to take a job or not, the payoffs could be monetary (salary, bonus, stock options) or non-monetary (work-life balance, learning opportunities, commute time). The payoffs can be positive or negative. For example, if you’re deciding whether to take a job or not, the payoffs could be positive (salary, bonus, stock options) or negative (work-life balance, learning opportunities, commute time). Once you’ve marked which outcomes are preferred, we move to the next step.</p>

<h3 id="step-3-identifying-the-probabilities">Step 3: Identifying the probabilities</h3>

<p>Estimate the likelihood of each outcome by making an educated guess. It is important to note that almost none of our decisions are made with complete information. The probabilities can be subjective or objective. For example, if you’re deciding whether to take a job or not, the probabilities could be subjective (how much you like the company, how much you like the work) or objective (how much you’ll be paid, how much you’ll learn). Trying to make an educated guess also motivates you to to learn more.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/decision_likelihood.jpg" alt="Estimating the outcome probabilities" srcset="    /assets/resized/decision_likelihood-320x145.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/decision_likelihood-480x217.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/decision_likelihood-800x361.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2024/01/decision_likelihood.jpg 1142w" /></p>

<p>It is important to not fall into the trap of overconfidence that comes with an inside view. The inside view is our limited view of the world, sort of ‘what you see is all there is’ notion. The outside view is the view of the world that takes into account the base rates and the historical data. With the outside view you’re trying to get to the more accurate view of the world by asking “what usually happens in scenarios similar to this” in an unbiased manner after taking some much needed psychological distance.</p>

<p>It also helps to understand that most decisions in life are not 0-1. A good analogy is to think of decision making as a game of darts or archery, you don’t just win points when you hit a bullseye, i.e. get the decision bang on, you also win points when you don’t. Life is closer to a game of darts, than, say, tailing the donkey, where the margin for error is ~0.</p>

<h3 id="step-4-estimate-relative-likelihoods">Step 4: Estimate relative likelihoods</h3>

<p>Estimate the relative likelihood of the outcomes you like vs those you dislike. This step helps you assess if your upside is comparable to the downside. Risk is basically just this, an estimate of your exposure to the downside. This estimation should be a probability range of upper and lower bounds that is based on a reasonable idea of the knowledge you have (and shouldn’t be a broad value that is bound to be right like -inf to +inf).</p>

<p>Assessing risk is also a great way to speed up decision making. The time you spend deciding should depend upon the impact of the decision. We spent an inordinate amount of time thinking about what to eat, wear or watch when in reality these decisions don’t affect our happiness or well being much more than say a few hours. Don’t fret over such decisions that have limited downsides (the author calls these ‘free rolls’). Ask yourself “what’s the worst that could happen?” and if that worst something is something you can live with, consider this a free roll. Decisions in which the different options have more or less the same downside upside asymmetry, don’t need much analysis.</p>

<h3 id="step-5-repeat-steps-1-4">Step 5: Repeat steps 1-4</h3>

<p>Repeat steps 1-4 for each decision in the decision tree. This helps you compare the different decisions and their outcomes. Once you start writing down the decisions and extending your decision tree with the various outcomes and their probabilities, you’ll start to see complexity of life in a completely new light. You’ll start to see how the decisions you make today can have a cascading effect on your future. This is a great way to start thinking about the future and how you can make it better.</p>

<h3 id="step-6-comparing-the-various-options">Step 6: Comparing the various options</h3>

<p>Now that you’ve got the decision tree with the various outcomes and their probabilities, you can start comparing the various options. In reality what you’re trying to achieve is draw a map that gets you to your goals and helps you visualise the various paths and obstacles in your way. Once you get used to seeing things this way, not doing this exercise would appear like you’re flying blind.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/new_information.jpg" alt="Changing your decision basis new information" srcset="    /assets/resized/new_information-320x132.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/new_information-480x198.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/new_information-800x331.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2024/01/new_information.jpg 1306w" /></p>

<p>The final step for every decision is to question yourself if there’s any new piece of information that you can get that can change your decision. If not, you can go ahead and make the decision. If yes, you should make every effort to get that information. This is called the ‘premortem’ and is a great way to avoid the ‘I knew it all along’ hindsight bias.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Business" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="Human Psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[‘How to decide’ by Annie Duke is a wholly practical book that helps you make better decisions. It comes with a unique set of tools and exercises that you can do while you’re reading it to imbibe the concepts better. This and her previous book, Thinking in bets, are highly recommended if you’re interested in honing your decision making skills. In this post, I will talk about the six step decision making process she describes. This method is in stark contrast with the flat pros and cons list that we’re used to. The six step decision making process is a living framework that grows with your decisions and helps you better understand the complexity of life.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to fail well</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-fail-well/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to fail well" /><published>2023-12-16T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-12-16T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-fail-well</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-fail-well/"><![CDATA[<p>This is the part two of a two part series on lessons from Amy Edmondson’s book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Right-Kind-Wrong-Science-Failing/dp/1982195061/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3DTAOI07DCH1B&amp;keywords=right+kind+of+wrong&amp;qid=1702372354&amp;sprefix=right+kind+of+%2Caps%2C607&amp;sr=8-1">The Right Kind of Wrong</a>. In the <a href="/different-kinds-of-failures/">first part</a>, I talked about the different kinds of failures and why one is better than the other. In this post, I will talk about how to create a team that encourages good failures.</p>

<h3 id="psychological-safety">Psychological safety</h3>

<p>Popularised by Google’s project Aristotle which was done to study commonalities between successful teams, psychological safety came through as the key trait. A safe environment for people to bring their whole selves to work, take risks and speak their minds, makes for effective teams and organisations.</p>

<p>Psychological Safety is also linked to failing well. If your team or organisation has psychological safety and high standards then people will strive to fail well but with low standards, people will enjoy the status quo. See the chart below to see how these two factors can play out.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/psvs.jpg" alt="Psychological safety and high standards" srcset="    /assets/resized/psvs-320x249.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/psvs-480x374.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/psvs-800x623.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/12/psvs.jpg 1836w" /></p>

<p>To understand how this works, we need to look at the three main barriers to failing well.</p>

<ol>
  <li>We are averse to failing -  by learning to reframe to build healthy attributions as to why we failed, we can become more open to learning from failing. Being able to reframe a situation is a key skill to have and can be learnt. In <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/notes-from-clearer-closer-better/">Clearer Closer Better</a>, Emily Balcetis discussed this at length.</li>
  <li>We are confused whether the failure was a bad one or a smart one -  need a framework for spotting failure types. We discussed this in the <a href="/different-kinds-of-failures/">first part</a>. In short, intelligent or smart failures happen in a new space, has low risk or costs and is a part of a meaningful opportunity.</li>
  <li>Afraid of failing  - a psychologically safe space encourages experimentation which by definition leads to failures.</li>
</ol>

<p>A psychologically safe space is a supportive environment that enables people to experiment, fail, talk about the failure and then iterate on this process. This is the key to failing well.</p>

<h3 id="capabilities-to-deal-with-failure">Capabilities to Deal with Failure</h3>
<p>An ideal intelligent failure is about failing in a new space with low risk. These three capabilities help one assess various situations and contexts and build the necessary awareness to ensure that the failure is an intelligent one.</p>

<h5 id="contextual-awareness">Contextual Awareness</h5>
<p>The key point about failures is understanding how much is known and what is at stake. The goal is to pause and assess the situation and the level of uncertainty, removing unnecessary anxiety associated with most situations. If the situation operates in an unknown space, then the failure is almost guaranteed, and it’s not even really a failure but the gaining of new knowledge.</p>

<p>Variability and a lack of routine can stump individuals and make a situation appear too consistent, which, in turn, can lead to pressure-free operations. If we regularly operate in a routine and consistent context, we can become overconfident. When such a person finds themselves in a context with a significant amount of variability, basic failures can happen.</p>

<p>When the stakes are high, you want to move carefully and follow protocols. In low-stake situations, you can move quickly, failing quickly with low vigilance. The important thing is to develop the ability to understand the context of the situation and then act accordingly.</p>

<h5 id="situational-awareness">Situational Awareness</h5>
<p>Naive realism is a type of bias that stems from our belief that we see reality itself and not a version of reality. This bias makes us overconfident because of our experience or background and makes us underestimate variability, leading to avoidable mistakes and failures. Basic failures are common in consistent settings, intelligent failures in novel ones, while complex failures take place due to variable settings.</p>

<p>Mixing three types of contexts - consistent, variable, and novel with the three failure types - basic, complex, and intelligent, we get nine combinations of failures occurring in different situations, as shown below:</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/failure_landscape.jpg" alt="The failure landscape" srcset="    /assets/resized/failure_landscape-320x317.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/failure_landscape-480x476.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/failure_landscape-800x793.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/12/failure_landscape.jpg 1172w" /></p>

<h5 id="system-awareness">System Awareness</h5>
<p>Developing a systems thinking approach helps us spot interconnected elements and avoid complex failures. Systems thinking allows us to see beyond isolated components to the intricate web of interconnected elements. It teaches us to recognize how elements work together, often with feedback loops, forming a cohesive system. This holistic view is essential for anticipating potential failures and finding sustainable solutions.</p>

<p>A fascinating example of systems thinking in action is the beer game study. Here, participants are divided into four groups – retailers, wholesalers, distributors, and a factory. The challenge is to manage beer inventory based on fluctuating consumer demands. It’s an eye-opener on how each decision, though rational in isolation, can lead to unintended consequences for the entire system. This simulation vividly illustrates the swings in demand and supply, emphasizing the need for a broader perspective in decision-making.</p>

<p>Systems thinking also sheds light on common pitfalls in managing complex systems:</p>

<p>Downstream Errors: Often, we don’t foresee the future implications of our decisions. Systems thinking encourages us to anticipate and plan for these potential errors.</p>

<p>Quick Fixes vs. Sustainable Solutions: The temptation to implement quick fixes can be counterproductive. By understanding the system as a whole, we can devise more effective, long-term solutions.</p>

<p>Redrawing the Boundaries: Reframing a situation by thinking about boundaries differently can help achieve more impactful interventions. For example, consider the case of a children’s football match. Would you think about it differently if, instead of considering your own feelings, you also considered the feelings of all the other parents involved? What new things would then become more acceptable or unacceptable to you?</p>

<h3 id="practices-to-build-a-relationship-with-failure">Practices to build a relationship with failure</h3>

<p>Follow these three simple practices to develop a healthy relationship with failure</p>

<ol>
  <li>Persistence - develop the muscle to persist for longer durations. Grit plays a large role in failing well. It is the ability to persist in the face of adversity that helps one to approach the same problem from different angles and eventually succeed.</li>
  <li>Accountability - taking the responsibility of your role in the failure allows one to go through the pain of looking back and learning from the failure. On the other hand not listening, not being clear or simply not doing something well enough can lead to basic failures or complex failures that could have been avoided.</li>
  <li>Apologies - an effective apology improves relationships and future chance of doing better together as a team. A good apology has three parts - an expression of regret, an explanation of what went wrong and an offer of repair. A good apology is not about making excuses or blaming others but rather about taking responsibility and making amends.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Business" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the part two of a two part series on lessons from Amy Edmondson’s book The Right Kind of Wrong. In the first part, I talked about the different kinds of failures and why one is better than the other. In this post, I will talk about how to create a team that encourages good failures.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Different kinds of failures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/different-kinds-of-failures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Different kinds of failures" /><published>2023-12-12T12:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-12-12T12:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/different-kinds-of-failures</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/different-kinds-of-failures/"><![CDATA[<p>The popular Silicon Valley mantra <em>Fail Fast, Fail Often</em> is often misunderstood. The idea is not to repeatedly fail until one gets it right. In fact it alludes to a very specific kind of failure, one that is <em>fast</em> and <em>cheap</em> and reveals something new and interesting. This is the right kind of failure Silicon Valley is obsessed with. In her book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Right-Kind-Wrong-Science-Failing/dp/1982195061/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3DTAOI07DCH1B&amp;keywords=right+kind+of+wrong&amp;qid=1702372354&amp;sprefix=right+kind+of+%2Caps%2C607&amp;sr=8-1">The Right Kind of Wrong</a>, Amy Edmondson, a professor at Harvard Business School, talks about the differences between good failures and bad failures. This is the part one of a two part series on lessons from this book. This post is about the different kinds of failures and why one is better than the other. In the next post, I will talk about how to create a culture of psychological safety that encourages good failures.</p>

<h3 id="basic-failures">Basic failures</h3>

<p>Basic failures are common everyday errors that happen due to oversight, neglect, inattention, forgetfulness, faulty assumptions based on poor logic or scant evidence and distraction that comes with modern life. Basic failures are unproductive, a drain on energy and resources and are the farthest away from the kind of failure we all want to encourage.</p>

<p>At this juncture it is perhaps important to look at failures in a spectrum. The infograhic below talks about a spectrum of failures. The left side of the spectrum is where basic failures lie and the right side is where intelligent failures lie. The failures on the left side are blameworthy while those on the right side are praiseworthy. Worth mentioning that almost all the failures we encounter in our work or personal life lie somewhere in the middle of the spectrum.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/failure_spectrum.jpg" alt="A spectrum of failures" srcset="    /assets/resized/failure_spectrum-320x96.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/failure_spectrum-480x144.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/failure_spectrum-800x240.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/12/failure_spectrum.jpg 2000w" /></p>

<p>Avoiding these kinds of failures is relatively easy and requires processes and systems. Some ways one can avoid basic failures are stated below.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Utilizing Checklists and Standardization: Seasoned professionals, such as pilots, adhere to meticulous checklists and standardized procedures prior to every flight, ensuring the aircraft’s optimal functionality. In Atul Gawande’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Checklist-Manifesto-How-Things-Right-ebook/dp/B0030V0PEW/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3N2TYV0P77ZZ4&amp;keywords=checklist+manifesto&amp;qid=1702372463&amp;s=digital-text&amp;sprefix=checklist+mani%2Cdigital-text%2C290&amp;sr=1-1">Checklist Manifesto</a>, the transformative impact of checklists in the medical field is emphasized, leading to enhanced performance, decreased errors, and lives saved. However, it’s crucial to acknowledge that checklists have their limits.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Cultivating a Safety-Centric Culture: Elevating the pursuit of excellence into a habit entails an unwavering commitment to meticulous attention to detail. By bringing safety front and center, one ensures that all possible precautions are taken to avoid basic failures that could lead to accidents or injuries.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fostering a Culture of Blameless Reporting: Encouraging employees to openly communicate adverse events and issues without fear of repercussions is paramount. Establishing your version of the “Andon Cord,” akin to Toyota’s approach, reinforces transparency as non-punitive and incentivizes the free exchange of information regarding errors and their solutions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Proactive Maintenance: Overcoming the challenge of “Temporal Discounting,” which leads us to prioritize immediate concerns over future potential problems, is essential. Regular, routine maintenance exerts a disproportionately significant impact on the mitigation of fundamental failures.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Mandatory Training Programs: Ensuring that all personnel possess a comprehensive understanding of equipment, coding, or any relevant subject matter is indispensable. Continuously updating training modules based on past errors ensures a state-of-the-art skill set.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Implementing Poka-Yoke Principles: The concept of “poka-yoke,” or error-proofing, involves designing systems to prevent, rectify, or highlight errors as they occur. It’s akin to childproofing your furniture or medicine bottles, effectively eliminating unexpected surprises or blunders.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The reason basic failures are helpful is that they are a good way to practice learning from past mistakes and getting used to the emotional discomfort one feels about failures.</p>

<h3 id="complex-failures">Complex failures</h3>

<p>Cumulative small issues can culminate in complex failures, similar to basic failures, and typically occur in familiar environments. Complex failures are influenced by various internal and external factors, such as increasing distractions and the overconfidence that repetition can bring. Interconnectedness, exemplified during the COVID-19 pandemic, also plays a significant role.</p>

<p>Interactive complexity emerges when multiple systems collaborate, making it challenging to predict the consequences of a minor error or change in one system. Perrow extensively explores this concept in “Normal Accidents.” In today’s world, disasters are more likely to occur when systems are tightly interconnected and their interactions are intricate. The diagram below shows how interactive complexity and tight coupling can lead to complex failures.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/new_perrow.jpg" alt="Perrow described this interconnectedness failure in his book Normal Accidents" srcset="    /assets/resized/new_perrow-320x287.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/new_perrow-480x430.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/new_perrow-800x717.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/12/new_perrow.jpg 908w" /></p>

<p>A way to understand complex failures is the swiss cheese model. Just as in a swiss cheese there are holes which often line up to create a hole that goes through the entire cheese, similarly in complex failures, multiple small failures line up to create a big failure. Visualising a complex system like a piece of swiss cheese reminds us of the role of chance. Error will always be with us but we can design systems that notice them and stop them.</p>

<p>Much like basic failures, mitigating complex failures necessitates a proactive approach and learning from past mistakes. However, the complexity of the systems involves not downplaying the role of chance and luck.</p>

<h3 id="intelligent-failures">Intelligent failures</h3>

<p>An intelligent failure is the kind that all want to encourage as it sheds light on new and interesting things. Intelligent failures or smart failures happen in a setting where there’s a lot of analytical or scientific work involved. In a typical lab, the failure rates could be as high as 70% and only these kinds of failures should be celebrated. Intelligent failure occurs as a part of what you believe to be a meaningful opportunity towards a valued goal and getting the right answer is not the only valued goal.</p>

<p>How to tell if a failure is intelligent? Here are 5 quick questions that can help you arrive at the answer.</p>

<ul>
  <li>New territory - do people already know how to get this done some other way?</li>
  <li>Opportunity driven - is there an opportunity worth pursuing and the goal valuable?</li>
  <li>Informed by prior knowledge - has the required homework been done and a thoughtful hypothesis formulated?</li>
  <li>As cheap as possible - has the risk been mitigated through a well designed experiment?</li>
  <li>Bonus - have all the lessons been mined from the failure and the knowledge shared?</li>
</ul>

<p>One of the key tenets of smart failures is it happens when the team posseses a growth mindset. A growth mindset, defined by Carol Dweck, is the belief that one’s abilities can be developed through dedication and hard work. A fixed mindset, on the other hand, is the belief that one’s abilities are innate and cannot be changed. A growth mindset is characterised by the curiosity to learn what went wrong and a willingness to go through the pain of looking back in the failure to learn. A fixed mindset is characterised by the fear of looking back and the pain of admitting that one was wrong.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Business" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The popular Silicon Valley mantra Fail Fast, Fail Often is often misunderstood. The idea is not to repeatedly fail until one gets it right. In fact it alludes to a very specific kind of failure, one that is fast and cheap and reveals something new and interesting. This is the right kind of failure Silicon Valley is obsessed with. In her book The Right Kind of Wrong, Amy Edmondson, a professor at Harvard Business School, talks about the differences between good failures and bad failures. This is the part one of a two part series on lessons from this book. This post is about the different kinds of failures and why one is better than the other. In the next post, I will talk about how to create a culture of psychological safety that encourages good failures.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How physical craft enriches us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/physical-craft-enriches/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How physical craft enriches us" /><published>2023-11-26T09:17:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-11-26T09:17:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-physical-craft-enriches-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/physical-craft-enriches/"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a collection of lessons from the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Shop-Class-Soulcraft-Inquiry-Value/dp/0143117467/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=shop+class+as+soulcraft&amp;qid=1700973675&amp;sr=8-1">Shop Class as Soulcraft</a>, by Matthew Crawford, on how physical craft enriches us. He defines Craftsmanship as being the desire to do things as well as you can for its own sake and goes on to explain how we have degraded craftsmanship in recent times. It is a fascinating read that underscores that the physical world is not just a distraction from the real world but is the real world. The book reviews the modern day understanding of work and how we, as a society, have come to value certain types of work over others. In this post I try to summarise the key ideas from the book.</p>

<h3 id="useful-arts">Useful arts</h3>

<p>We often associate plumbing, fitting electrical appliances or motorcycle maintenance with something mundane, when in reality these are one of the most useful arts. These are the arts that make the world go round. People practising these useful arts in reality are often leading much more meaningful lives than we would care to accept. Manual work like plumbing needs a lot of systematic encounter with the material world and is cognitively enriching. The fact that old items rust and deteriorate means a repairman needs to apply practical experience along with theoretical guidelines to fix an item (which for ex may break due to rust or simply usage based wear and tear). They don’t simply read a manual and execute a set of instructions as the manual cannot and does not cover every possible scenario. In a way they are the true persuers of knowledge as without learning through hands, the world remains distant and true learning remains at bay.</p>

<p>Manual craftsmen like mechanics or plumbers, often have a more tightly knit social life. They share tools, knowledge, often times even customers. They are also more likely to be self employed and thus have a more direct relationship with their customers. They are also more likely to be in a position to say no to a customer if they don’t like the customer. This is in stark contrast to the modern day office worker who is often a cog in a wheel and has little control over their work.</p>

<h3 id="thinking-vs-doing">Thinking vs doing</h3>

<p>The degradation of manual work began with scientific management which began with Frederik Winslow Taylor’s management theories (whose fans included Stalin and many B school professors). The cognitive parts of manufacturing were slowly moved away from the shop floor to a management office. The primary intention was not efficiency but cost. Once a mechanical activity becomes a piece of a process with little or no cognitive requirement, a skilled worker can be replaced by an unskilled one. Thus, craft knowledge dies out. This is also called the abstraction of labor. This draining off of cognitive requirements from a job isn’t limited to blue collar work, desk jobs, traditionally thought of to be knowledge work, are also going through an abstraction, which the author calls, a rising boats of clerkdom.</p>

<p>In essence, the dichotomy is not between manual work and knowledge work, it is between work that is meaningful and work that isn’t. We have grown to like sitting on a desk and doing work that does not require physical labour but design plans that someone else, often lower down in the hierarchy, will execute. This is a sort of a moral hazard. We have grown to like the idea of being a manager rather than a worker. This is also called the Peter Principle and is best summarised by the quote “In a hierarchy, every employee tends to rise to his level of incompetence”. The world has shifted from production of goods (which has moved elsewhere) to the marketing of brands.</p>

<p>College graduates often look for specific jobs that pay less than blue collar manual jobs, for the sake of looking for “knowledge work”. This can often mean that the college educated are psychically incapable of taking manual jobs and instead prefer taking up paper pushing cubicle jobs that don’t have a clear objective threshold for quality (other than grammar). That we submit our youth to such jobs that are more prone to the overall production of low quality, is unacceptable and detrimental to our long term well being.</p>

<p>Fixing or working on real world things brings intrinsic joy. Good teachers love students and want them to become the best version of theirselves. Similarly, most good mechanics love cars. There is a certain kind of pride that comes with working on a national brand like Rolls Royce but that joy can get diminished if the parts belonging to the car can come from anywhere in the world.</p>

<h3 id="finding-joy-in-fixing-things">Finding joy in fixing things</h3>

<p>Being able to repair things requires of us to think of what a machine needs rather than what we need. In a way, this suspends our narcissistic way of living and consider what the world around us needs. As I wrote before, the dichotomy is not whether a job is manual or not, it is whether a job is meaningful or not. Being self reliant is a liberating feeling and agency driven autonomy is directly linked to happiness. The fact that people want to take up knitting or grow their own mushrooms is in a way descriptive of how further we’ve gone away from our work and how we, in our soul, want to gain some more agency and responsibility of our things.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/iron_man.jpg" alt="Iron Man talks to the tractor like its a person" srcset="    /assets/resized/iron_man-320x177.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/iron_man-480x266.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/iron_man-800x443.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/11/iron_man.jpg 2034w" />
<em>Iron Man in Avengers, talks to a tractor like its a person</em></p>

<p>The reason we don’t fix our own stuff is because of harped on notion of opportunity cost but in reality, the pride we feel after being curious and getting our hands dirty far outweighs the loss in opportunity cost. This opportunity cost nonsense is based on the fungibility of human experience. That any activity can be boiled down in terms of the seconds on the clock, is wrong. To fix ones own car is not to use up time but rather to have a different experience of time, self and car. Things now a days are being made so as to encourage us not to tinker with them. This is driven by economics, globalisation but also by changing behaviours of consumerism. A good example of this is people playing musical instruments far less now and listen to music on stereo more. Instruments require effort to master while stereo makes music instantly available. Art requires human engagement v a device that requires consumption.</p>

<h3 id="ethics-and-cognition">Ethics and cognition</h3>

<p>Degrading of work in the way of not getting things repaired or the economics of factory stuff being cheaper but also of less quality, has directly led to moral degradation. The world now pays less attention to the craft and its economic effects are there for everyone to see. It is quite normal today for one to walk to a garrage and find mechanics spending less time looking for faults or fixing rather than replacing parts. This is because the economics of replacing parts is better than fixing them. This throwaway culture persists because we don’t have the patience to listen to the machine tell us of what ails it. We make snap judgements because we don’t care about the machine enough. This is a moral failure. The author also speaks about the service manual as a social technology and talks about a world where the manuals were pieces of art, written to be read and understood by everyone who wanted to not only use the machine but also to fix it. This is in stark contrast to the modern day manuals that are written more out of legal reasons. This is also a type of moral failure that feeds into the throwaway culture.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="Book Reviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is a collection of lessons from the book Shop Class as Soulcraft, by Matthew Crawford, on how physical craft enriches us. He defines Craftsmanship as being the desire to do things as well as you can for its own sake and goes on to explain how we have degraded craftsmanship in recent times. It is a fascinating read that underscores that the physical world is not just a distraction from the real world but is the real world. The book reviews the modern day understanding of work and how we, as a society, have come to value certain types of work over others. In this post I try to summarise the key ideas from the book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Managing creative blocks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/managing-creative-blocks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing creative blocks" /><published>2023-11-05T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-11-05T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/managing-creative-blocks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/managing-creative-blocks/"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a collection of lessons from the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Anatomy-Breakthrough-Unstuck-When-Matters/dp/B0BDT8K3DC/ref=sr_1_1?crid=7I71RTSJHCQC&amp;keywords=anatomy+of+a+breakthrough&amp;qid=1699159167&amp;sprefix=anatomy+of+a+break%2Caps%2C360&amp;sr=8-1">Anatomy of a Breakthrough</a>, by Adam Alter, on understanding why we get stuck and how to get unstuck. It is a fascinating read that underscores that getting stuck is a virtual certainty in creative endeavours and that there are ways to get unstuck. The book is a collection of stories of breakthroughs and how they came about. It is a great read and I highly recommend it.</p>

<h3 id="why-being-stuck-is-so-common">Why being stuck is so common</h3>

<p>Let’s start by defining what can be considered as “being stuck”. The author says you’re stuck if you find yourself in one or more of these three situations.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Temporarily unable to make progress in a domain that matters to you</li>
  <li>Fixed in place for too long enough to feel psychological discomfort</li>
  <li>Existing habits and strategies aren’t solving the problem</li>
</ol>

<p>One of the most common reasons we get stuck is due to the motiovation problem we encounter near the middle of any pursuit. <em>Clark Hull</em> in the 1930s found that rats in a maze would run faster as they got closer to the goal. The same thing happens with us. Our propensity to quit gradually declines as we get nearer the goal. Often times the rats begin fast, slow down and then speed up as they get to the end. Slowing down or getting stuck near the middle is very common. This is often called the goal gradient effect. One way to counter this middle lull is to break down a larger goal into smaller goals and adopt a <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/notes-from-clearer-closer-better/"><em>Narrow Focus</em></a>. The smaller goals should be somewhat significant themselves like breaking down a 30 mile marathon into 10 chunks of 3 mile each. This way you can celebrate the smaller wins and keep the motivation going.</p>

<p>Transitioning between decades also affect us. 9 ending ages make us more introspective and we tend to evaluate our lives more. The commonly used trope of <em>mid life crisis</em> is real and linked to the point discussed above. Bruce Feiler calls these Lifequakes.</p>

<p>Another common reason we all get stuck is repeated use of same techniques and strategies that have become obsolete or ineffective. Even the best strategies need improvements from time to time. It makes sense to have many irons in the fire so a loss of one or two doesn’t matter all that much but they should be in different stages of germination from a seed to almost a tree.</p>

<p>Finally, we all underestimate persistence. Mental difficulty is a sign of progress. The creative cliff one feels is an illusion and your creative capacity doesn’t erode with time or effort. Persistence is hard primarily because we equate mental difficulty with failure. Creativity is hard because we live and experience the same cultural norms and face the same boundaries and it is difficult to escape those same ideas around us. This is called convergent evolution by which bats, birds and butterflies all evolved to have similar wings structures.</p>

<h3 id="dealing-with-the-emotional-aspect-of-being-stuck">Dealing with the emotional aspect of being stuck</h3>

<p>Being stuck makes you feel anxiety and lonely. Here are 5 ways you can deal with the emotional stress of being stuck.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Framing being stuck as a challenge rather than a threat can bring us out of the rut. Threat seems definitive while challenge can bring out the best of us and also seems to assure us that even if we fail today, we can come out again and  go for it tomorrow.</li>
  <li>Visualising or <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/notes-from-clearer-closer-better/"><em>Materialising</em></a> is important but also radical acceptance, i.e. visualise the worst case of failure and realising there’s a life on that side as well. This is also known to relieve pressure and anxiety.</li>
  <li>Satisficing to make peace with a good enough choice rather than continuing to optimise and chasing perfectionism. Perfectionism is seeking romcom worthy relationships and sitcom worthy friendships. It’s unreal and exhausting.</li>
  <li>Slow down and prepare. Messi prepares his mental map of the field and the players and their strengths and weaknesses in the first few minutes of his game, and its only after the first few minutes of <em>walking the field</em> that he gets into his groove. Sometime getting unstuck is about slowing down rather than speeding up.</li>
  <li>There is an optimum failure rate, a sort of sweet spot of toughness of a problem that makes for best learning. An error rate that is too high will discourage you from carrying on and too low will make you feel disengaged quickly. The optimum failure rate allows you to emotionally fail more easily.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="tips-to-get-unstuck">Tips to get unstuck</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Do a Friction audit to find points of friction as those are likely to get you stuck. Similar to how one finds and fixes drop off points in a customer experience funnel, one must try and find points of friction in life that are likely to get one stuck. For example if its too cold outside, may be you need a treadmill at home to make it easy for you to workout everyday. You can even add friction points like not storing junk food in the fridge to discourage yourself from a habit. This is linked to the idea of <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-atomic-habits/">Environment Design</a> concept discussed in Atomic Habits.</li>
  <li>Use formula based approaches containing predefined structures to get unstuck. For example <a href="https://gizmodo.com/the-22-rules-of-storytelling-according-to-pixar-5916970">Emma Coats’ 22 rules of storytelling</a> lists some ways to get you out of a rut, for ex
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> rule 4 - some templates like once upon a time .. x then x because x and then x
 rule 6 - challenging characters with hardships..
 rule 5 - simplify and lose
 rule 9 - what cannot happen next can lead to some interesting insights
 rule 11 - put it all on paper
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Add more automation to life so as to avoid dissipating mental energies and simplifying things and avoid getting stuck.</li>
  <li>Adding constraints or getting inside the box can also be a simplification technique that helps you get more creative and think differently. It was seen that in a team containing a star player, people often passed the ball to the star player more often than other players and thus the team as a whole became more predictable.</li>
  <li>Recombination or getting inspired by other ideas is a great way to avoid being stuck. Striving to do something entirely original puts immense pressure on you. Success can come from a well placed tweak.</li>
  <li>Pivoting involves <em>Holding an idea like you would a small bird</em>. It should be tight enough that it doesn’t fly away but gentle enough so as not to hurt it. This nimbleness allows you to pivot more freely and be open to more possibilities.</li>
  <li>Ask for help from a diverse set of people or seek out a black sheep. The advise doesn’t need to be competent, it needs to be different.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="habits-that-help-getting-unstuck">Habits that help getting unstuck</h3>

<ol>
  <li>The OODA loop or observe, orient, decide, act can also help one get unstuck. The first step observe is to figure out why you’re stuck. The second step is the most important and requires you to make an action plan personalised for you. The decide step is to exploit the piece of information you got from the 2nd step and the final step is about to act.</li>
  <li>Experimentating multiple pathways or options to pick the one that works best. Forming a habit of experimenting with multiple ideas is known to get more optimal outcomes in the long run. There are generally two ways to setup experiments. First, choose from competing solutions and second, look in the global space of all available options.</li>
  <li>Explore Exploit Tradeoff is creating periods of stasis interleaved with periods of change. An optimal balance of saying yes and no to new opportunities can make all the difference. Your default answer in any given situation should depend your current state of mind (for ex in the face of new career opportunities, if you’re satisfied with your career, you can default to No, while if you’re unsatisfied your default your answer to Yes).</li>
  <li>Being always ready for action when you bump into inspiration. Following, sparks of creativity, with action immediately is the key to getting unstuck. Feelings are nothing if they don’t feed into action. Most musicians swear by picking up the instrument and strumming it leading to new tracks rather than just humming the tunes in their heads.</li>
  <li>Micro-scheduling is when you put on a timer for 60 secs to do just one thing. It eliminates the need to think what else you could be doing right then and paves the way for you to empty your ideas on to the paper/keyboard/etc in front of you. It is also known to be a great way to get started on a task you’ve been putting off for a while.</li>
  <li>Exercise or any kind of movement is known to encourage divergent thinking</li>
  <li>Strategic lowering of standards helps you get started with your version 1s and to get you flowing. It also allows you to “empty your bad ideas” and get to the next one. It also allows you to work on your bad ideas without any mental baggage and gets you moving.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is a collection of lessons from the book Anatomy of a Breakthrough, by Adam Alter, on understanding why we get stuck and how to get unstuck. It is a fascinating read that underscores that getting stuck is a virtual certainty in creative endeavours and that there are ways to get unstuck. The book is a collection of stories of breakthroughs and how they came about. It is a great read and I highly recommend it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 2" /><published>2023-10-26T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-10-26T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-2/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to the second installment of my lessons from Robert Greene’s “48 Laws of Power.” If you missed the initial exploration, you can <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/48-laws-of-power-summarised-1/">catch up on it here</a>. Let’s get on with the next and final 24 laws.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Recreate Yourself: Transform into a persona that exudes power, consciously choosing your role in the grand play of life. Develop an attitude that becomes synonymous with your identity, thereby standing out and leaving a lasting impression on those around you.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Keep Your Hands Clean: Craft an image of virtue and maintain an appearance of civility, all while discreetly handling your affairs. Keep mistakes concealed by diverting attention, and ensure you have a convenient scapegoat at the ready.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Leverage People’s Need to Believe: Harness the power of human gullibility by incorporating innovative technologies or enticing get-rich-quick schemes. Capitalize on the innate desire for something extraordinary and novel.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make Bold Claims and Get Attention: Boldness, when executed with confidence, appears less outrageous and more captivating. Embrace audacity, capturing the attention of those around you who are instinctively drawn to the extraordinary.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Plan All the Way to the End: Strategize meticulously, ensuring your endeavors conclude on a high note. Take credit for successes and prepare for potential setbacks. Recognize the art of timing and know when to halt progress, withdrawing into contemplation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Appear Effortless at Whatever You Do: Embrace “sprezzatura,” an Italian concept denoting a certain nonchalance. Indicate that your capabilities extend far beyond what is seen, concealing the effort invested. Maintain an air of effortlessness to cultivate an aura of mastery.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Control the Options and Control the Cards Others Have to Play: Present choices that align with your objectives, subtly influencing the decisions of those around you. Manipulate the situation to make others feel empowered while ensuring the options favor your agenda.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Play to People’s Fantasies: Cater to the human desire for easy solutions and shortcuts. Package your endeavors as a magical remedy, capturing the imagination of those seeking a way out of their challenges.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Discover Each Man’s Thumbscrew: Engage in active listening to discern the weaknesses and triggers of others. Understanding what drives individuals allows you to navigate relationships with insight and influence.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Way You Carry Yourself Decides How You Will Be Treated: Project an air of regality to elicit corresponding treatment. Consider Columbus, who lacked qualifications but meticulously detailed his vision before embarking on a historic journey. Uphold dignity and cultivate a mindset destined for greatness.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Master the Art of Timing: Avoid haste, compelling others to conform to your pace. Deliberate and strategize, projecting an image of calm assurance.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ignore the Things You Don’t Have: Dismiss minor problems to prevent their escalation. Granting undue attention to trivial matters amplifies their significance. This is also loosely related to the self critical inner voice we all have. I discussed it at length in my book summary of <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/how-to-silence-your-inner-critic/">Chatter</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Create Compelling Spectacles: Make your presence unforgettable by crafting impactful moments. Imprint yourself in the minds of others through experiences that linger long after you’ve departed. Adopting a <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/epic-framework-for-creating-defining-moments/">moment spotting habit</a> can help you identify opportunities to create lasting memories.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Think as You Like but Act Like Others: Navigate against the current discreetly, avoiding unnecessary attention. Standing out invites disdain; blending in fosters a sense of security among peers.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Stir Up Water to Catch Fish: Disrupt your adversaries’ composure to induce irrational actions. By unsettling their equilibrium, you gain a strategic advantage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Despise the Free Lunch: Avoid entanglements involving hidden obligations. Abstain from payment in gratitude, guilt, or deceit, preserving your autonomy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Avoid Stepping in a Great Man’s Shoes: Carve your own path to distinction, avoiding emulation. Shine uniquely, establishing your identity independently.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Strike the Shepherd and the Sheep Will Scatter: Identify and neutralize the core influencer causing discord. By addressing the source, you mitigate the impact on the collective.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Work on the Hearts and Minds of Others: Seduce and engage others at their level, fostering shared aspirations. Powerful leaders build pillars of support rather than creating adversaries by vanquishing the cherished connections of others.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Disarm People by Mirroring: Confound adversaries by mirroring their actions, undermining their sense of uniqueness. This tactic fosters a belief that shared values exist, creating confusion and doubt. Mirroring was also a key tactic of negotiation in <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/10-negotiations-tips-from-never-split-the-difference/">Never Split The Difference</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Preach the Need for Change but in Moderate Amounts: Advocate for change with subtlety, preserving respect for tradition. Gradual modifications maintain a semblance of continuity while embracing progress.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Never Appear Too Perfect: Reveal imperfections strategically, conveying fallibility. This approach discourages envy and fosters relatability.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Don’t Go Too Far: Exercise restraint and discern when to cease advancement. Avoid overextension, preventing the dilution of focus and resources.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Assume Formlessness: Embrace adaptability, recognizing the transience of stability. Understand that rules are malleable, subject to change in the ever-evolving landscape of power dynamics.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>In the intricate tapestry of power dynamics, these laws serve as navigational tools for those seeking mastery but as I said before some of these are too nuanced and can be misused. I would recommend reading the book to understand the context and the examples that Robert Greene uses to explain these laws.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome back to the second installment of my lessons from Robert Greene’s “48 Laws of Power.” If you missed the initial exploration, you can catch up on it here. Let’s get on with the next and final 24 laws.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 1" /><published>2023-10-14T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-10-14T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-1/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently delved into Robert Greene’s influential book, 48 Laws of Power. While the overarching theme might not have immediately resonated with me, the intricate laws it presents have undeniably played a role in shaping power dynamics around me, knowingly or unknowingly. The book, a compilation of historical anecdotes, sheds light on how individuals have employed these laws to secure power. Below, I’ve distilled the first 24 laws into brief sentences. Throughout, I’ve used the term “enemy” interchangeably with counterparts, competitors, or opponents.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Never outshine the master: Show respect and adoration, recognizing the insecurities of superiors. Strive to make them feel powerful while subtly asserting your competence.</li>
  <li>Don’t trust friends too much: Be cautious with favors, as friendship can cloud judgment; turn enemies into passive allies. Maintain a strategic distance to preserve objectivity in decision-making.</li>
  <li>Conceal your true intentions: Keep motives hidden to avoid manipulation; Bismark’s support of Austria illustrates this. Strategic ambiguity allows you to control the narrative and adapt as circumstances change.</li>
  <li>Say less than necessary: Speaking sparingly avoids revealing secrets or turning people off; Andy Warhol mastered this art. Cultivate a sense of mystery to keep others intrigued and engaged.</li>
  <li>Reputation is everything: Strengthen your reputation while poking holes in your enemies’ reputations. Craft an image that is both unassailable and strategically aligns with your goals.</li>
  <li>Court attention at every cost: Stand out, be conspicuous, and maintain an air of mystery. Cultivate a personal brand that captures attention and sets you apart in the minds of others.</li>
  <li>Never do what others can do for you: Delegate, hire talent, and build on the knowledge and insights of others. Recognize the power of collaboration and surround yourself with a team that complements your strengths.</li>
  <li>Make other people come to you: Keep others on the defensive by laying traps and avoiding acting in anger. Strategic patience and the ability to make others come to you give you the upper hand in negotiations.</li>
  <li>Win through actions and not arguments: Yield in arguments, but let actions speak louder to gain respect and followers. Demonstrate competence through tangible results, allowing your accomplishments to be your most persuasive argument.</li>
  <li>Avoid the unhappy and unlucky: Misery attracts misery, and these individuals can bring you down; steer clear. Surround yourself with positive influences to foster a mindset of growth and success.</li>
  <li>Never become redundant: Keep some knowledge exclusive to yourself; side with the weak to become their backbone. Position yourself as indispensable by offering unique skills that others can depend on.</li>
  <li>Use sincere and honest moves strategically: First impressions of honesty and sincerity can be powerful. Leverage authenticity to build trust but strategically reveal vulnerability to create deeper connections.</li>
  <li>Ask for help by appealing to their self-interest: Align your interests with theirs, avoiding direct charity requests. Forge alliances by making others see the mutual benefits of assisting you.</li>
  <li>Ask indirect questions to find out their true nature: Conceal your own personality while encouraging others to talk about themselves. Uncover hidden motivations by creating an environment where people willingly reveal their true selves.</li>
  <li>Crush your enemy totally: Showing mercy can backfire; commit to your course of action to its conclusion. Understand that half measures can lead to future challenges, so decisively eliminate threats when necessary.</li>
  <li>Absence can lead to exclusivity: Scarcity enhances value; make yourself scarce to be more desirable. Balance presence and absence strategically to increase your perceived value.</li>
  <li>Cultivate an air of unpredictability: Keep those around you guessing, making them expend energy trying to understand you. Harness the psychological advantage of being unpredictable to control situations.</li>
  <li>Isolation is dangerous: Circulate to gather necessary information; avoid building a fortress. Strategic networking and information gathering are vital components of effective decision-making. I guess there’s a sweet spot between rule 16 and this one.</li>
  <li>Do not offend the wrong person: Understand who holds real power; keep tabs on decision-makers. Navigate relationships with discernment, recognizing the key players and influencers in any given situation.</li>
  <li>Don’t commit to a side: Remaining neutral prevents loss in conflicts; strong demands, and the weak wears you down. Preserve flexibility by avoiding premature commitments in dynamic situations.</li>
  <li>Play sucker to catch a sucker: Acting less knowledgeable than you are can work to your advantage. Use the perception of naivety strategically to extract valuable information and gain a psychological edge.</li>
  <li>Make surrender a tool of power: Surrender congenially to those who seek a display of authority. Strategic concessions can be a powerful tool, allowing you to control the terms of surrender.</li>
  <li>Concentrate your power: Focus on long-term gains; don’t waste energy on insignificant matters. Identify the areas where your efforts yield the greatest impact and concentrate your resources accordingly.</li>
  <li>Play the perfect courtier: Act as if you have a king to please; avoid boasting about achievements. Adopt a humble demeanor, focusing on serving others and building relationships rather than self-promotion.</li>
</ol>

<p>While some of these rules may seem Machiavellian, adapting them to your personality and setting requires thoughtful consideration. Stay tuned for a future post where I’ll summarize the remaining 24 laws.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently delved into Robert Greene’s influential book, 48 Laws of Power. While the overarching theme might not have immediately resonated with me, the intricate laws it presents have undeniably played a role in shaping power dynamics around me, knowingly or unknowingly. The book, a compilation of historical anecdotes, sheds light on how individuals have employed these laws to secure power. Below, I’ve distilled the first 24 laws into brief sentences. Throughout, I’ve used the term “enemy” interchangeably with counterparts, competitors, or opponents.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing incentives that work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing incentives that work" /><published>2023-10-05T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-10-05T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work/"><![CDATA[<p>As an entrpreneur, product and people manager, I often find myself needing to design incentives that affect people’s behaviors. If you read the last sentence and the image formed in your head was that of a dangling carrot on a stick, i’ll request you to ignore it. I am talking about creating an environment where some really smart people become open to changing their behaviour ever so slightly to achieve larger goals. I wouldn’t blame you for the image that formed in your head though, as incentives are often poorly designed and are counter productive. In his book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mixed-Signals-Incentives-Really-Work/dp/B0BT5SW1RT/ref=sr_1_4?crid=2ZKM6B767T896&amp;keywords=mixed+signals&amp;qid=1696566311&amp;sprefix=mi%2Caps%2C1005&amp;sr=8-4">Mixed Signals</a>, Uri Gneezy, describes in detail how incentives can be used to achieve desired outcomes or mixed signaling be avoided that leads to incentives that aim to improve one thing but focus on another. I have tried to summarise the key learnings from the book below.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/horsecarrot.png" alt="Horse carrot stick by Dall-E" srcset="    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-320x320.png 320w,    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-480x480.png 480w,    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-800x800.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/10/horsecarrot.png 1024w" /> 
<em>Not the image you should have when you think of incentives</em></p>

<h3 id="what-is-signaling">What is signaling?</h3>

<p>Signaling in this context refers to the social cues that we send out to others. Signals are a credible way to indicate your values, abilities, aspirations and preferences. We all indulge in one or the other type of signaling but if the signal is easy to adapt it can be copied and if it is too loud it can come across as inauthentic. A rich person may not want people to know that they want them to know they are rich. Thus enter, Rolexes. The real Biker culture has strong signals like conspicuous tattoos on the neck and arms. This is to identify real bikers and eliminate casual bikers who can also buy bikes &amp; riding gear which are, in comparison, cheap signals.</p>

<p>Through policies we can force a person to send a very strong signal or a weak signal for specific things. Disney World, for example, allows free tickets for kids under 3. People often lie about their kids’ age but if DW began asking children their age directly, two things can happen</p>

<ol>
  <li>Kids will tell their true age and DW will eliminate the problem</li>
  <li>Parents will instruct their kids in advance on lying about their age which will sort of persist the problem to some extent.</li>
</ol>

<p>Notice what is really happening with the second point. Parents are being asked to teach lying to their kids which is a strong signal to the parents that the price of the ticket is worth teaching kids to lie. This is a very strong signal and most parents won’t do it. This is a very crude example but it illustrates the point of how one can design policies and incentives that use the signaling mechanism to achieve desired outcomes.</p>

<h3 id="avoiding-mixed-signaling">Avoiding mixed signaling</h3>

<p>Another important aspect of using signals is avoiding sending mixed signals. It is usually borne out of encouraging something but incentivising another. For instance, encouraging quality of deliverables but giving bonuses for quantity or encouraging long term goal alignment but praising short term milestones.</p>

<p>This is usually sorted out by adding more dimensions to the incentive structures. For instance, adding a rating system for the end user satisfaction along with evaluating people on quantity. This will ensure that people don’t just focus on quantity but also on quality.</p>

<h3 id="self-v-social-signals">Self v Social Signals</h3>

<p>Most signals are social in that they allow one to communicate their values to others. Driving fuel guzzling semis or choosing to go with hybrid cars is a social signal that you care about the environment. In the early days of hybrid cars, they were seen as pricier options with limited comfort and safety features. However, one shining factor set them apart – their eco-friendly nature. Consumers began embracing hybrid vehicles not just for their fuel economy but to send a powerful message to the world: “We care for the environment, and we’re willing to sacrifice some comforts for it.”</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/prius.jpeg" alt="Cool prius as a social signal" srcset="    /assets/resized/prius-320x285.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/prius-480x428.jpeg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/10/prius.jpeg 800w" /></p>

<p>Enter the Toyota Prius and the Honda Civic, both based on existing models. However, the Prius had a distinct and conspicuous look that drew consumers who wanted to stand out and signal their commitment to environmental causes. As a result, Prius won big. The importance of signaling was underscored by a 2007 survey, revealing that a remarkable 57% of Prius owners chose it to make a statement about themselves, far outweighing those who mentioned fuel economy or reduced emissions.</p>

<p>Self signals are signals that you send to yourself. Self signaling allow people to tell themselves that they are a good person or have certain values. Pay what you want coffee shops that are popping up in the US are a good example of self signaling. People readily pay more than the cost of the coffee because they want to feel good about themselves. The same people will not pay more than the cost of the coffee if they were asked to pay a specific amount. This is called the <em>warm glow effect</em>, what we feel when we help, volunteer or donate. The self signaling mechanism is very powerful and can be used to achieve desired outcomes.</p>

<h3 id="mental-accounting">Mental Accounting</h3>

<p>We all have different mental accounts for various expenses. Think about it; we might spend 20 minutes searching for parking deals to save a few bucks but don’t hesitate to splurge on dessert afterward. The money across these accounts is not interchangeable and the story we tell ourselves to justify our choices are entirely different. While saving on parking is a sound financial choice, ending a family meal with a lovely dessert is a way to elevate a moment and make it memorable. To make incentives truly appealing, we must use the right currency that shapes the narrative we want.</p>

<p>Consider the story of a car review site that offered a $450 discount on car purchases. Surprisingly, this incentive didn’t have the positive impact they expected. Why? The $450 discount on a high-value purchase like a car got lost in the documentation and seemed insignificant. However, when they began offering the same $450 discount as “prepaid gas cards” for the same amount, demand improved significantly. Why? $450 is $450. Or is it?</p>

<p>When it comes to incentives, they can often sit in different mental accounts. In the gas card scenario, buyers know they will need gas and the $450 incentive seems to come across as something extra. Moreover, every time buyers filled up their gas tanks using the free card, they felt smart for making a clever buying decision. This simple shift in the perception of value made all the difference.</p>

<h3 id="regret-minimisation">Regret Minimisation</h3>

<p>Regret is caused by comparing what we did v what we could have done. Regret can also be caused by not exploring a new option. In that sense, exploration is it’s own reward. This is related to the <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-thinking-fast-slow-part-2/">loss aversion</a> concept from Thinking Fast &amp; Slow. We love to avoid regret at all costs. This makes regret a great tool for incentives and driving behaviours.</p>

<p>A classic example of this is the case where someone keeps buying a lottery ticket with the exact same numbers cause he thinks if he stopped buying and those numbers came up as winner, he would regret it immensely 🤷. A similar interesting case was of a lottery company that picked a random postcode from where a final winner will be chosen. This forced people in that postcode to think of a scenario in which someone from their address won the lottery but they didn’t. To avoid that regret, people flocked to buy lottery tickets.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As an entrpreneur, product and people manager, I often find myself needing to design incentives that affect people’s behaviors. If you read the last sentence and the image formed in your head was that of a dangling carrot on a stick, i’ll request you to ignore it. I am talking about creating an environment where some really smart people become open to changing their behaviour ever so slightly to achieve larger goals. I wouldn’t blame you for the image that formed in your head though, as incentives are often poorly designed and are counter productive. In his book Mixed Signals, Uri Gneezy, describes in detail how incentives can be used to achieve desired outcomes or mixed signaling be avoided that leads to incentives that aim to improve one thing but focus on another. I have tried to summarise the key learnings from the book below.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How not to argue</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How not to argue" /><published>2023-08-28T12:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-08-28T12:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue/"><![CDATA[<p>I previously wrote <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/how-to-argue/">How to Argue</a> which was a collection of tips on how to have fruitful discussions. This post is a follow up to that post and is inspired by the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Whats-Our-Problem-Self-Help-Societies/dp/B0BVGH6T1Q/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=whats+our+problem&amp;qid=1693216187&amp;sr=8-1">Whats our problem</a> by Tim Urban. My previous post talked about how to get the best out of a discussion by keeping an open mind, this post describes some common pitfalls that can derail a discussion. Before we can jump into what to avoid, it makes sense to understand the higher and the lower mind thesis and the different ways we defend our opinions.</p>

<h3 id="the-higher-mind-and-the-lower-mind">The higher mind and the lower mind</h3>

<p>Tim Urban describes the concept of higher mind (conscious, wise, knows what we should do, etc) and the lower mind (controls our primal behaviours and what we can do). These don’t map exactly to System 1 and 2 of <a href="/lessons-from-thinking-fast-slow-part-1/">Thinking fast and slow</a> but can be thought of as abstractions of them.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/thinking-scales.jpg" alt="Thinking scales by Tim Urban" srcset="    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-320x255.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-480x382.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-800x637.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/thinking-scales.jpg 1740w" /></p>

<p>This high v low terminology segues into the vertical thinking which is an often forgotten dimension of discussions. for ex when we discuss politics, we just think of a linear scale from left to right that describe what you believe in but there is a vertical axis as that describes, how you believe. Higher mind thinks like a scientist (constantly looking to be proven wrong in the short term to get it right in the long term) and often times like a fan (motivated reasoning). The lower mind thinks like an attorney (vehemently defending their beliefs) or a zealot (consider the world as a simple black and white).</p>

<h3 id="framing-a-weak-counterargument-or-strawman">Framing a weak Counterargument or Strawman</h3>

<p>The sign of a weak argument is a weak counterargument. Greatly authored papers always come with a great counter argument. It shows the authors have thought through the problem and have considered the other side of the argument. If people cannot come up with a good counterargument it means their own arguments are flimsy and weak.</p>

<p>A strawman argument is a misrepresentation of an opponent’s argument that is easy to defeat. It is a fallacy because it fails to address the actual arguments that the opponent is making. It is a form of argument that is aims to give the impression of refuting an opponent’s argument, while actually refuting an argument that was not presented by that opponent. One can easily spot a strawman argument when the counterargument is a caricature of the original argument.</p>

<p>Always steelman your counterpart, i.e. address the core issue being discussed and not a caricature of it. This is the only way to have an intellectually honest discussion.</p>

<h3 id="motte-and-bailey">Motte and Bailey</h3>

<p>In ancient times, Bailey was the flat land used for living and cultivation while the Motte was a fortress atop the adjoining hill. When under attack, people living in Bailey ran up to the Mott and held the fort which was far more defensible. This is what people do when their arguments come under fire. They run to the Motte which is easy to defend and has similarities with the original argument however is a different argument.</p>

<p>A simple example would be you defending a specific idea like gun control and you run to the Motte and say something like “I am for protection of freedom at all costs”. This is a classic motte and bailey. The motte is easy to defend and is a weaker version of the original argument.</p>

<p>Always defend your original and exact position, not an abstraction or dilution of it that is obviously easy to defend or not even a point of contention.</p>

<h3 id="discrediting-the-speaker">Discrediting the speaker</h3>

<p>Discrediting the speaker is the easiest way to not address the arguments posed by the speaker. This is also known as ad hominem. When you hear arguments formed in a way that are directed against a person rather than the position they are maintaining, you know they are indulging in ad hominem.</p>

<p>Apart from being unproductive, ad hominem is also a logical fallacy. It is a fallacy because the character, circumstances, or actions of a person do not (in most cases) have a bearing on the truth or falsity of the claim being made (or the quality of the argument being made). Needless to say calling someone names or attacking their character is not a good way to have a fruitful discussion.</p>

<h3 id="esteem-protectiveness">Esteem protectiveness</h3>

<p>The final point is not too get too entangled with your opinions. We all have a tendency to protect our self esteem and our opinions are a part of our identity. When our opinions are challenged, we feel threatened and our lower mind takes over that pushes us to become closed minded. We use the tactics described above because of our confirmation bias and esteem protectiveness. We twist observations into stories we want to hear that validate our already formed beliefs. Nobody wants to look like an idiot who was brainwashed, so we defend our positions like a zealot.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I previously wrote How to Argue which was a collection of tips on how to have fruitful discussions. This post is a follow up to that post and is inspired by the book Whats our problem by Tim Urban. My previous post talked about how to get the best out of a discussion by keeping an open mind, this post describes some common pitfalls that can derail a discussion. Before we can jump into what to avoid, it makes sense to understand the higher and the lower mind thesis and the different ways we defend our opinions.]]></summary></entry></feed>