<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-10-14T12:09:36+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Infermuse</title><subtitle>Practical wisdom from studies, experiments and books</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the 48 Laws of Power: Part 1" /><published>2023-10-14T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-10-14T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/48-laws-of-power-summarised-1/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently delved into Robert Greene’s influential book, 48 Laws of Power. While the overarching theme might not have immediately resonated with me, the intricate laws it presents have undeniably played a role in shaping power dynamics around me, knowingly or unknowingly. The book, a compilation of historical anecdotes, sheds light on how individuals have employed these laws to secure power. Below, I’ve distilled the first 24 laws into brief sentences. Throughout, I’ve used the term “enemy” interchangeably with counterparts, competitors, or opponents.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Never outshine the master: Show respect and adoration, recognizing the insecurities of superiors. Strive to make them feel powerful while subtly asserting your competence.</li>
  <li>Don’t trust friends too much: Be cautious with favors, as friendship can cloud judgment; turn enemies into passive allies. Maintain a strategic distance to preserve objectivity in decision-making.</li>
  <li>Conceal your true intentions: Keep motives hidden to avoid manipulation; Bismark’s support of Austria illustrates this. Strategic ambiguity allows you to control the narrative and adapt as circumstances change.</li>
  <li>Say less than necessary: Speaking sparingly avoids revealing secrets or turning people off; Andy Warhol mastered this art. Cultivate a sense of mystery to keep others intrigued and engaged.</li>
  <li>Reputation is everything: Strengthen your reputation while poking holes in your enemies’ reputations. Craft an image that is both unassailable and strategically aligns with your goals.</li>
  <li>Court attention at every cost: Stand out, be conspicuous, and maintain an air of mystery. Cultivate a personal brand that captures attention and sets you apart in the minds of others.</li>
  <li>Never do what others can do for you: Delegate, hire talent, and build on the knowledge and insights of others. Recognize the power of collaboration and surround yourself with a team that complements your strengths.</li>
  <li>Make other people come to you: Keep others on the defensive by laying traps and avoiding acting in anger. Strategic patience and the ability to make others come to you give you the upper hand in negotiations.</li>
  <li>Win through actions and not arguments: Yield in arguments, but let actions speak louder to gain respect and followers. Demonstrate competence through tangible results, allowing your accomplishments to be your most persuasive argument.</li>
  <li>Avoid the unhappy and unlucky: Misery attracts misery, and these individuals can bring you down; steer clear. Surround yourself with positive influences to foster a mindset of growth and success.</li>
  <li>Never become redundant: Keep some knowledge exclusive to yourself; side with the weak to become their backbone. Position yourself as indispensable by offering unique skills that others can depend on.</li>
  <li>Use sincere and honest moves strategically: First impressions of honesty and sincerity can be powerful. Leverage authenticity to build trust but strategically reveal vulnerability to create deeper connections.</li>
  <li>Ask for help by appealing to their self-interest: Align your interests with theirs, avoiding direct charity requests. Forge alliances by making others see the mutual benefits of assisting you.</li>
  <li>Ask indirect questions to find out their true nature: Conceal your own personality while encouraging others to talk about themselves. Uncover hidden motivations by creating an environment where people willingly reveal their true selves.</li>
  <li>Crush your enemy totally: Showing mercy can backfire; commit to your course of action to its conclusion. Understand that half measures can lead to future challenges, so decisively eliminate threats when necessary.</li>
  <li>Absence can lead to exclusivity: Scarcity enhances value; make yourself scarce to be more desirable. Balance presence and absence strategically to increase your perceived value.</li>
  <li>Cultivate an air of unpredictability: Keep those around you guessing, making them expend energy trying to understand you. Harness the psychological advantage of being unpredictable to control situations.</li>
  <li>Isolation is dangerous: Circulate to gather necessary information; avoid building a fortress. Strategic networking and information gathering are vital components of effective decision-making. I guess there’s a sweet spot between rule 16 and this one.</li>
  <li>Do not offend the wrong person: Understand who holds real power; keep tabs on decision-makers. Navigate relationships with discernment, recognizing the key players and influencers in any given situation.</li>
  <li>Don’t commit to a side: Remaining neutral prevents loss in conflicts; strong demands, and the weak wears you down. Preserve flexibility by avoiding premature commitments in dynamic situations.</li>
  <li>Play sucker to catch a sucker: Acting less knowledgeable than you are can work to your advantage. Use the perception of naivety strategically to extract valuable information and gain a psychological edge.</li>
  <li>Make surrender a tool of power: Surrender congenially to those who seek a display of authority. Strategic concessions can be a powerful tool, allowing you to control the terms of surrender.</li>
  <li>Concentrate your power: Focus on long-term gains; don’t waste energy on insignificant matters. Identify the areas where your efforts yield the greatest impact and concentrate your resources accordingly.</li>
  <li>Play the perfect courtier: Act as if you have a king to please; avoid boasting about achievements. Adopt a humble demeanor, focusing on serving others and building relationships rather than self-promotion.</li>
</ol>

<p>While some of these rules may seem Machiavellian, adapting them to your personality and setting requires thoughtful consideration. Stay tuned for a future post where I’ll summarize the remaining 24 laws.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently delved into Robert Greene’s influential book, 48 Laws of Power. While the overarching theme might not have immediately resonated with me, the intricate laws it presents have undeniably played a role in shaping power dynamics around me, knowingly or unknowingly. The book, a compilation of historical anecdotes, sheds light on how individuals have employed these laws to secure power. Below, I’ve distilled the first 24 laws into brief sentences. Throughout, I’ve used the term “enemy” interchangeably with counterparts, competitors, or opponents.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing incentives that work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing incentives that work" /><published>2023-10-05T09:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-10-05T09:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/designing-incentives-that-work/"><![CDATA[<p>As an entrpreneur, product and people manager, I often find myself needing to design incentives that affect people’s behaviors. If you read the last sentence and the image formed in your head was that of a dangling carrot on a stick, i’ll request you to ignore it. I am talking about creating an environment where some really smart people become open to changing their behaviour ever so slightly to achieve larger goals. I wouldn’t blame you for the image that formed in your head though, as incentives are often poorly designed and are counter productive. In his book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mixed-Signals-Incentives-Really-Work/dp/B0BT5SW1RT/ref=sr_1_4?crid=2ZKM6B767T896&amp;keywords=mixed+signals&amp;qid=1696566311&amp;sprefix=mi%2Caps%2C1005&amp;sr=8-4">Mixed Signals</a>, Uri Gneezy, describes in detail how incentives can be used to achieve desired outcomes or mixed signaling be avoided that leads to incentives that aim to improve one thing but focus on another. I have tried to summarise the key learnings from the book below.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/horsecarrot.png" alt="Horse carrot stick by Dall-E" srcset="    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-320x320.png 320w,    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-480x480.png 480w,    /assets/resized/horsecarrot-800x800.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/10/horsecarrot.png 1024w" /> 
<em>Not the image you should have when you think of incentives</em></p>

<h3 id="what-is-signaling">What is signaling?</h3>

<p>Signaling in this context refers to the social cues that we send out to others. Signals are a credible way to indicate your values, abilities, aspirations and preferences. We all indulge in one or the other type of signaling but if the signal is easy to adapt it can be copied and if it is too loud it can come across as inauthentic. A rich person may not want people to know that they want them to know they are rich. Thus enter, Rolexes. The real Biker culture has strong signals like conspicuous tattoos on the neck and arms. This is to identify real bikers and eliminate casual bikers who can also buy bikes &amp; riding gear which are, in comparison, cheap signals.</p>

<p>Through policies we can force a person to send a very strong signal or a weak signal for specific things. Disney World, for example, allows free tickets for kids under 3. People often lie about their kids’ age but if DW began asking children their age directly, two things can happen</p>

<ol>
  <li>Kids will tell their true age and DW will eliminate the problem</li>
  <li>Parents will instruct their kids in advance on lying about their age which will sort of persist the problem to some extent.</li>
</ol>

<p>Notice what is really happening with the second point. Parents are being asked to teach lying to their kids which is a strong signal to the parents that the price of the ticket is worth teaching kids to lie. This is a very strong signal and most parents won’t do it. This is a very crude example but it illustrates the point of how one can design policies and incentives that use the signaling mechanism to achieve desired outcomes.</p>

<h3 id="avoiding-mixed-signaling">Avoiding mixed signaling</h3>

<p>Another important aspect of using signals is avoiding sending mixed signals. It is usually borne out of encouraging something but incentivising another. For instance, encouraging quality of deliverables but giving bonuses for quantity or encouraging long term goal alignment but praising short term milestones.</p>

<p>This is usually sorted out by adding more dimensions to the incentive structures. For instance, adding a rating system for the end user satisfaction along with evaluating people on quantity. This will ensure that people don’t just focus on quantity but also on quality.</p>

<h3 id="self-v-social-signals">Self v Social Signals</h3>

<p>Most signals are social in that they allow one to communicate their values to others. Driving fuel guzzling semis or choosing to go with hybrid cars is a social signal that you care about the environment. In the early days of hybrid cars, they were seen as pricier options with limited comfort and safety features. However, one shining factor set them apart – their eco-friendly nature. Consumers began embracing hybrid vehicles not just for their fuel economy but to send a powerful message to the world: “We care for the environment, and we’re willing to sacrifice some comforts for it.”</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/prius.jpeg" alt="Cool prius as a social signal" srcset="    /assets/resized/prius-320x285.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/prius-480x428.jpeg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/10/prius.jpeg 800w" /></p>

<p>Enter the Toyota Prius and the Honda Civic, both based on existing models. However, the Prius had a distinct and conspicuous look that drew consumers who wanted to stand out and signal their commitment to environmental causes. As a result, Prius won big. The importance of signaling was underscored by a 2007 survey, revealing that a remarkable 57% of Prius owners chose it to make a statement about themselves, far outweighing those who mentioned fuel economy or reduced emissions.</p>

<p>Self signals are signals that you send to yourself. Self signaling allow people to tell themselves that they are a good person or have certain values. Pay what you want coffee shops that are popping up in the US are a good example of self signaling. People readily pay more than the cost of the coffee because they want to feel good about themselves. The same people will not pay more than the cost of the coffee if they were asked to pay a specific amount. This is called the <em>warm glow effect</em>, what we feel when we help, volunteer or donate. The self signaling mechanism is very powerful and can be used to achieve desired outcomes.</p>

<h3 id="mental-accounting">Mental Accounting</h3>

<p>We all have different mental accounts for various expenses. Think about it; we might spend 20 minutes searching for parking deals to save a few bucks but don’t hesitate to splurge on dessert afterward. The money across these accounts is not interchangeable and the story we tell ourselves to justify our choices are entirely different. While saving on parking is a sound financial choice, ending a family meal with a lovely dessert is a way to elevate a moment and make it memorable. To make incentives truly appealing, we must use the right currency that shapes the narrative we want.</p>

<p>Consider the story of a car review site that offered a $450 discount on car purchases. Surprisingly, this incentive didn’t have the positive impact they expected. Why? The $450 discount on a high-value purchase like a car got lost in the documentation and seemed insignificant. However, when they began offering the same $450 discount as “prepaid gas cards” for the same amount, demand improved significantly. Why? $450 is $450. Or is it?</p>

<p>When it comes to incentives, they can often sit in different mental accounts. In the gas card scenario, buyers know they will need gas and the $450 incentive seems to come across as something extra. Moreover, every time buyers filled up their gas tanks using the free card, they felt smart for making a clever buying decision. This simple shift in the perception of value made all the difference.</p>

<h3 id="regret-minimisation">Regret Minimisation</h3>

<p>Regret is caused by comparing what we did v what we could have done. Regret can also be caused by not exploring a new option. In that sense, exploration is it’s own reward. This is related to the <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/lessons-from-thinking-fast-slow-part-2/">loss aversion</a> concept from Thinking Fast &amp; Slow. We love to avoid regret at all costs. This makes regret a great tool for incentives and driving behaviours.</p>

<p>A classic example of this is the case where someone keeps buying a lottery ticket with the exact same numbers cause he thinks if he stopped buying and those numbers came up as winner, he would regret it immensely 🤷. A similar interesting case was of a lottery company that picked a random postcode from where a final winner will be chosen. This forced people in that postcode to think of a scenario in which someone from their address won the lottery but they didn’t. To avoid that regret, people flocked to buy lottery tickets.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As an entrpreneur, product and people manager, I often find myself needing to design incentives that affect people’s behaviors. If you read the last sentence and the image formed in your head was that of a dangling carrot on a stick, i’ll request you to ignore it. I am talking about creating an environment where some really smart people become open to changing their behaviour ever so slightly to achieve larger goals. I wouldn’t blame you for the image that formed in your head though, as incentives are often poorly designed and are counter productive. In his book Mixed Signals, Uri Gneezy, describes in detail how incentives can be used to achieve desired outcomes or mixed signaling be avoided that leads to incentives that aim to improve one thing but focus on another. I have tried to summarise the key learnings from the book below.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How not to argue</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How not to argue" /><published>2023-08-28T12:28:27+05:30</published><updated>2023-08-28T12:28:27+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-not-to-argue/"><![CDATA[<p>I previously wrote <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/how-to-argue/">How to Argue</a> which was a collection of tips on how to have fruitful discussions. This post is a follow up to that post and is inspired by the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Whats-Our-Problem-Self-Help-Societies/dp/B0BVGH6T1Q/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=whats+our+problem&amp;qid=1693216187&amp;sr=8-1">Whats our problem</a> by Tim Urban. My previous post talked about how to get the best out of a discussion by keeping an open mind, this post describes some common pitfalls that can derail a discussion. Before we can jump into what to avoid, it makes sense to understand the higher and the lower mind thesis and the different ways we defend our opinions.</p>

<h3 id="the-higher-mind-and-the-lower-mind">The higher mind and the lower mind</h3>

<p>Tim Urban describes the concept of higher mind (conscious, wise, knows what we should do, etc) and the lower mind (controls our primal behaviours and what we can do). These don’t map exactly to System 1 and 2 of <a href="/lessons-from-thinking-fast-slow-part-1/">Thinking fast and slow</a> but can be thought of as abstractions of them.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/thinking-scales.jpg" alt="Thinking scales by Tim Urban" srcset="    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-320x255.jpg 320w,    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-480x382.jpg 480w,    /assets/resized/thinking-scales-800x637.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/08/thinking-scales.jpg 1740w" /></p>

<p>This high v low terminology segues into the vertical thinking which is an often forgotten dimension of discussions. for ex when we discuss politics, we just think of a linear scale from left to right that describe what you believe in but there is a vertical axis as that describes, how you believe. Higher mind thinks like a scientist (constantly looking to be proven wrong in the short term to get it right in the long term) and often times like a fan (motivated reasoning). The lower mind thinks like an attorney (vehemently defending their beliefs) or a zealot (consider the world as a simple black and white).</p>

<h3 id="framing-a-weak-counterargument-or-strawman">Framing a weak Counterargument or Strawman</h3>

<p>The sign of a weak argument is a weak counterargument. Greatly authored papers always come with a great counter argument. It shows the authors have thought through the problem and have considered the other side of the argument. If people cannot come up with a good counterargument it means their own arguments are flimsy and weak.</p>

<p>A strawman argument is a misrepresentation of an opponent’s argument that is easy to defeat. It is a fallacy because it fails to address the actual arguments that the opponent is making. It is a form of argument that is aims to give the impression of refuting an opponent’s argument, while actually refuting an argument that was not presented by that opponent. One can easily spot a strawman argument when the counterargument is a caricature of the original argument.</p>

<p>Always steelman your counterpart, i.e. address the core issue being discussed and not a caricature of it. This is the only way to have an intellectually honest discussion.</p>

<h3 id="motte-and-bailey">Motte and Bailey</h3>

<p>In ancient times, Bailey was the flat land used for living and cultivation while the Motte was a fortress atop the adjoining hill. When under attack, people living in Bailey ran up to the Mott and held the fort which was far more defensible. This is what people do when their arguments come under fire. They run to the Motte which is easy to defend and has similarities with the original argument however is a different argument.</p>

<p>A simple example would be you defending a specific idea like gun control and you run to the Motte and say something like “I am for protection of freedom at all costs”. This is a classic motte and bailey. The motte is easy to defend and is a weaker version of the original argument.</p>

<p>Always defend your original and exact position, not an abstraction or dilution of it that is obviously easy to defend or not even a point of contention.</p>

<h3 id="discrediting-the-speaker">Discrediting the speaker</h3>

<p>Discrediting the speaker is the easiest way to not address the arguments posed by the speaker. This is also known as ad hominem. When you hear arguments formed in a way that are directed against a person rather than the position they are maintaining, you know they are indulging in ad hominem.</p>

<p>Apart from being unproductive, ad hominem is also a logical fallacy. It is a fallacy because the character, circumstances, or actions of a person do not (in most cases) have a bearing on the truth or falsity of the claim being made (or the quality of the argument being made). Needless to say calling someone names or attacking their character is not a good way to have a fruitful discussion.</p>

<h3 id="esteem-protectiveness">Esteem protectiveness</h3>

<p>The final point is not too get too entangled with your opinions. We all have a tendency to protect our self esteem and our opinions are a part of our identity. When our opinions are challenged, we feel threatened and our lower mind takes over that pushes us to become closed minded. We use the tactics described above because of our confirmation bias and esteem protectiveness. We twist observations into stories we want to hear that validate our already formed beliefs. Nobody wants to look like an idiot who was brainwashed, so we defend our positions like a zealot.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Human Psychology" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I previously wrote How to Argue which was a collection of tips on how to have fruitful discussions. This post is a follow up to that post and is inspired by the book Whats our problem by Tim Urban. My previous post talked about how to get the best out of a discussion by keeping an open mind, this post describes some common pitfalls that can derail a discussion. Before we can jump into what to avoid, it makes sense to understand the higher and the lower mind thesis and the different ways we defend our opinions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How consumption defines us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-consumption-defines-us/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How consumption defines us" /><published>2023-07-29T09:10:02+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-29T09:10:02+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-consumption-defines-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-consumption-defines-us/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Sum-Small-Things-Theory-Aspirational/dp/0691183171/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2POPBLCGLHVNL&amp;keywords=the+sum+of+small+things&amp;qid=1690606979&amp;sprefix=the+sum+of+small+thi%2Caps%2C349&amp;sr=8-1">The Sum of Small Things</a>, by Elizabeth Currid-Halkett is one of the most thought provoking books i’ve read in a while. It defines the new aspiration class that is defined by a different kind of consumption. The book challenged my understanding of why I consume what I consume and how it defines me. I’ve tried to summarize the book in this post.</p>

<h3 id="what-we-think-consumption-is-v-what-it-really-is">What we think consumption is V what it really is</h3>

<p>We think consumption is always linked to needs or desires but in reality it is a signalling device. It is a way to show others who we are and what we stand for. It is a way to show our identity, values, status, beliefs, personality, aspirations, political leanings, and so much more. It helps us create an idea of us and thereby create an other.</p>

<p>The book talks about conspicuous and inconsipcuous consumption. Conspicuous consumption is the consumption of goods and services that are meant to be seen and noticed by others. Inconspicuous consumption is the consumption of basic goods that are private. The book explains how conspicuous consumption goes beyond the traditional definition of luxury goods and services. Good table manners, for example, are also a type of conspicuous consumption because it takes time to build those habits and is a way to signal your social standing. Same goes for going to a specific school, or having a specific accent, or having a specific taste in music, books, art, fitness, etc.</p>

<p>How or why we consume something is also largely out of our conscious control. The city we live in, the peer group we move about in, our job, our education levels, etc, all play a larger than life role in our consumption patterns. For example, people in New York City spend almost 50% more on fashion than any other city in the US. This is driven by the fact that New York is the fashion capital of the US and people in the city are more likely to be influenced by fashion trends. Similarly, people in San Francisco spend more on fitness than any other city in the US. This is driven by the fact that San Francisco is the tech capital of the US and people in the city are more likely to be influenced by fitness trends than fashion.</p>

<h3 id="aspirational-class">Aspirational class</h3>

<p>The consumer class was defined by conspicuous consumption, generally propelled by economic mobility and income. People in the consumer class showed their wellbeing by consuming specific goods and services (branded luxury goods and memberships to exclusive clubs, etc). These affluent elite were marked by consumption of Veblen goods, goods for which demand increases as the price increases. Veblen goods are typically high-quality goods that are well made, exclusive, and act as status symbols.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The new aspirational class is marked by knowledge and specific societal behaviors like veganism, volunteerism, reading the NY Times, etc, in their attempts to become better humans</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Aspirational class consumption may often be more expensive like buying from the farmers market but it is ultimately not a requirement but rather a means to signal social belonging. The new age conspicuous consumption doesn’t always shy away from capitalism. It in fact, focuses on bringing the production process front and center and allow people to show their status by consumption. In short, the story of the good becomes more important than its quality or price. This is why the aspirational class is happy to pay a dollar for an egg provided they like the way the farmer treats his chicken.</p>

<p>One of the intricacies of the aspirational class or <em>the new elite</em>, is their greed to have a return on their leisure time. When people choose to go to a specific fitness class or buy expensive fitness wear like lululemon, they make a commitment to use their leisure time in a certain way. When they watch a specific show or film or attend an opera, they are signalling a certain taste.</p>

<h3 id="cultural-capital">Cultural Capital</h3>

<p>The rise of the aspirational class is mostly a function of what the author calls <em>post scarcity</em>. The consumption of eco friendly goods and practices are a result of post scarcity environment. The fact that we have the luxury of choice is what allows people to signal their status. In terms of Maslow’s hierarchy of needs, it is in today’s world of plenty that we can self actualise. The aspirational class is not fueled by economic mobility but rather by cultural capital.</p>

<p>Cultural capital is the knowledge and skills required to navigate the world. It is the ability to understand and appreciate the nuances of the world. It is the ability to understand the difference between a $10 wine and a $100 wine, between a $1000 handbag and a $100 handbag, between a handcrafted artisanal product and a mass produced factory item and so on. It is having the wherewithall to both, understand the need to care about the environment and to show that you do.</p>

<p>Going into hole-in-the-wall restaurants or buying tomatoes at the farmers market are both types of cultural capital acquired by reading a specific newspaper or belonging to a certain interest group. The cultural capital is used by the elite to distribute opportunities just as regular capital was used before. What nail polish color to wear, how many books to carry to the classroom, which newspapers to read and discuss are all examples of cultural capital of the form of knowledge acquired by staying in touch with ones peer group or behaving in a certain way. These behaviours appear costless but are actually a result of slugging it out in a certain peer group.</p>

<h3 id="why-judging-others-is-stupid">Why judging others is stupid</h3>

<p>We assume every decision a person makes (esp when it comes to health or parenting) is a moral choice (why is that person fat, why aren’t they culturally more aware, why are they feeding fast food to their kids, etc) but often times these decisions emanate from constraints either financial or time or awareness; which itself is borne out of a lack of investment of time. A working class person cannot afford healthy food for their children who often waste most of the food given to them. They cannot spend time to attend pilate classes or read the new yorker either.  Often times working mothers don’t have the time or energy to breastfeed their children after a 14 hour workdays and so they choose to use formula.</p>

<p>We look up to women taking time off from work to breast feed their children or pursue “attachment therapy”, with sympathy but we look down on an expensive hermes bag, but the reality is that both these actions are,</p>

<ol>
  <li>enabled by resources like time or affluence</li>
  <li>a product of the cultural milieu to which one belongs and in a sense aimed at fitting in or belonging</li>
</ol>

<p>Judging others on the basis of their actions or inactions, but remaining ignorant of their constraints, is therefore stupid.</p>

<p>This books introduced me to the term <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobo_(socio-economic_group)?useskin=vector">Bobos</a> - Bohemian Bourgeois, which probably perfectly sums up quite a lot of my consumption patterns. The term was introduced into the English language by the cultural commentator #DavidBrooks to describe the 1990s descendants of the yuppies in the book Bobos in Paradise (2000). Brooks describes Bobos as “highly educated folk who have one foot in the bohemian world of creativity and another foot in the bourgeois realm of ambition and worldly success. People who spend money to look simple can also be termed as Bobos.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehack" /><category term="Human Psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Sum of Small Things, by Elizabeth Currid-Halkett is one of the most thought provoking books i’ve read in a while. It defines the new aspiration class that is defined by a different kind of consumption. The book challenged my understanding of why I consume what I consume and how it defines me. I’ve tried to summarize the book in this post.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How beliefs are formed and reinforced</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-beliefs-are-formed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How beliefs are formed and reinforced" /><published>2023-07-21T00:00:02+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-21T00:00:02+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-beliefs-are-formed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-beliefs-are-formed/"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s how beliefs are formed -&gt; we believe in certain things based on our genetic disposition to certain personality traits, our upbringing, our parents’ political leanings, our friends’ opinions, our own experiences, our biases, prejudices, fears, desires, hopes, aspirations, goals, etc. In other words a lot of factors, that are not rational or anasytical. What happens after forming a belief is more interesting. The hippocampus, our brain’s storyteller, connects separate, distant events into a single narrative around the belief and why it is true. The purpose is not accuracy but coherency. This is the reason why we can’t change someone’s mind by presenting them with facts as their mind has already weaved a story that reinforces the belief.</p>

<p>In his book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/The-Believing-Brain-Michael-Shermer-audio/dp/B0052FX3XE/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=the+believing+brain+-+michael+shermer&amp;qid=1689916387&amp;sprefix=the+believing+brain%2Caps%2C455&amp;sr=8-1">The Believing Brain</a>, Michael Shermer explains how beliefs are formed and how they are reinforced. In the following sections, I describe the key ideas from the book.</p>

<h3 id="what-you-believe-is-what-you-see">What you believe is what you see</h3>

<p>In an experiment conducted to understand the effectiveness of mental health prognosis, Rosenhan, a senior psychologist conducted several studies that showed the hospital environment can modify our understanding of a specific behaviour which can or cannot be considered abnormal. He said to his students he will be sending a faking patient and that they had to spot him. In reality he sent no fakers but still 40 patients were flagged to be faking out of 200. In a similar study he had 7 faking psychology majors go to the hospital who were never found to be faking and were in fact diagnosed with serious mental illnesses. These experiments showed that the underlying belief system manipulates what we see and how we interpret it.</p>

<h3 id="patternicity-and-agenticity">Patternicity and Agenticity</h3>

<p>We believe things because we see patterns. Patternicity and Agenticity are our evolutionary abilities to spot patterns in noise and assigning them meanings that aren’t really there. Shermer explains how anecdotal learning comes naturally, while science takes effort. We are the descendents of those who could find patterns to survive the dangers that lurked near them. We don’t have a system that overlooks this pattern recognition. Our brain simply runs a cost heuristic - cost of making a false positive error (the bush moving is a tiger) Vs that of the false negative error (its just wind). This is why we make superstitious beliefs, because we cannot distinguish between bad learning and learning.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People believe weird things because of our ability to believe things.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Superstitions are nothing but a type of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operant_conditioning_chamber">B.F. Skinner’s bird box scenario</a>, where we believe a point or a reward comes to us because of something we did but it happened on its own.</p>

<h3 id="goldilocks-zone-of-open-mindedness">Goldilocks zone of open mindedness</h3>

<p>There is a just right amount of “open mindedness” that is healthy. There are thin boundaries between Creativity, which is borne out of the perfect use of patternicity and agenticity; and madness, that comes from an extremely active use of both. If we’re too open to capturing patterns, we see one where there is none, if we too little, we miss out on important observations. Scientists also walk this tightrope of spotting patterns. The author talks about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kary_Mullis">Kary Mullis</a>, a scientist who won the Nobel prize for inventing polymerase chain reaction (<em>PCR</em>), in which a small amount of DNA can be copied in large quantities. He was a creative genius but also had some weird beliefs like his belief in astrology and having witnessed an extra terrestrial glowing racoon.</p>

<p>The point the author makes is that Mullis had a wide angle lens for spotting patterns which ensured many weird and creative ideas got through and made its seat in his head but only a small proportion of these ideas were useful (in the modern day sense of the word).</p>

<h3 id="we-all-differ-so-much">We all differ so much</h3>

<p>Genetics also indirectly play a role in us believing certain things. While genes dont directly contribute to political leanings or religious beliefs, they do play a role in shaping personality traits that in turn make it easy or hard for us to believe certain things.</p>

<p>It is because of these differences that we all have the potential to believe so many different things and make up stories that explain the same observation entirely differently. A realistic vision of the world involves understanding that there are moral constraints. People have potential to be moral as well as amoral. Believing this is important to understand why people do what they do and then creating policies and systems that work with this reality.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehack" /><category term="Human Psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s how beliefs are formed -&gt; we believe in certain things based on our genetic disposition to certain personality traits, our upbringing, our parents’ political leanings, our friends’ opinions, our own experiences, our biases, prejudices, fears, desires, hopes, aspirations, goals, etc. In other words a lot of factors, that are not rational or anasytical. What happens after forming a belief is more interesting. The hippocampus, our brain’s storyteller, connects separate, distant events into a single narrative around the belief and why it is true. The purpose is not accuracy but coherency. This is the reason why we can’t change someone’s mind by presenting them with facts as their mind has already weaved a story that reinforces the belief.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What constitues play and having fun?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/play-and-having-fun/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What constitues play and having fun?" /><published>2023-06-20T00:00:02+05:30</published><updated>2023-06-20T00:00:02+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/play-and-having-fun</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/play-and-having-fun/"><![CDATA[<p>In his book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Play-Anything-Ian-Bogost-audiobook/dp/B01KP45MMG/ref=sr_1_1?crid=26CSPFTJK2GU9&amp;keywords=play+anything&amp;qid=1687667435&amp;sprefix=pla%2Caps%2C1306&amp;sr=8-1">Play Anything</a>, Ian Bogost aims to explain how fun and play are not the same thing. He claims that “fun” is not pleasure but rather the aftereffect of play. This book challenges almost all notions of play, fun, pleasure, boredom and happiness. In this post I try to summarise the key ideas from the book.</p>

<h5 id="what-is-play-and-fun">What is play and fun</h5>

<p>Misery gives way to fun when you take the constraints that aren’t designed for you and then treat it if it were a source of fun. Do something particular with the material you have is playing. The example that Bogost begins with is his trip to the mall with his daughter. He treats this visit to the mall as a chore and is frantically running around to finish the shopping. His daughter, on the other hand, is having fun. He is walking faster than is comfortable for his daughter but she makes the best of it by designing a game of trying to land her feet in tiles in a certain pattern. She is playing with the constraints of the mall.</p>

<p>This is the essence of play. Play is hard and needs work. Playing requires more attention, generosity, ingenuity and creativity than real life does. Play mostly lies on the other side of the disgust that is associated with boredom and in that way boredom is essential to concoct play.</p>

<p>Fun is the aftermath of taking an existing and well defined structure and making it do something different. It requires effort. Golf, for ex is not a good walk spoiled as the old aphorism goes, it is a purposeful manipulation of landscape to provide us fun. Things that usually make life hard are what make it fun. Mary Poppin’s spoonful of sugar is not the right way to derive fun but to accept things as they are and working with them.</p>

<p>It is often taking something visible and making it invisible and taking something omnipresent but not visible and making it conspicuous. Pleasure doesn’t always sneak up on us. Sometimes we seek out repetition of the known.  The “experience of expertise” is also related. The joy of mastery is a type of pleasure that doesn’t surprise but rather offers something recognisable and predictable.</p>

<h5 id="worldfulness-and-everyday-play">Worldfulness and everyday play</h5>

<p>An interesting point that Bogost makes is that, while mindfulness is being comfortable with oneself, “worldfullness” is being comfortable with ourself and the world around us. This allows us to create play. We ignore things around us as we are “busy” and we seek “better things”. The Japanese Shinto philosophy that states every object has a living spirit.</p>

<p>Frustration with everyday things comes from the gap between expectations and reality. When we don’t internalise the world around us, we don’t get frustrated and realise that the world is outside our head and then open ourselves up to embracing the constraints to give life new meanings.</p>

<p>We treat people and objects based on how they make us feel about ourselves. A better way to interact with the world is to work with things around us and appreciate them for what they are. We think of a playground (real one or the one in our mind) as a way to fulfil some objective or exert some control, we drain it of its real fun. This is related to the Buddhist philosophy of expectations/desires being the root of all sorrows and Sikh philosophy that one should yield oneself completely to the one force that flows through all of us. In that sense, real play begins when we compel ourselves to the desires of the swings and slides and the see-saws and do what they need of us.</p>

<p>When you deliberately explore the depths of a boring activity, something magical happens, that magic is what we call “fun”. Bogost also calls it the “solemn appreciation” of something. I run a boring SaaS business and often lose sight of how much fun it really is.</p>

<p>My key takeaway from this book is how solemn appreciation of everyday things like an accounting software or Cheetos can make them as much “fun” as say, an acoustic guitar or a cheese plate.</p>

<h5 id="ironoia">Ironoia</h5>

<p>Irony is saying something while meaning something totally different. Its a sort of get out of jail card that we use to never truly interact with the world. It’s like a sofa cover that at the same time protects the sofa upholstery from damage but also prevents us from ever really experiencing the sofa in the first place. When we walk into a big box retail outlet like Walmart, a bunch of negative emotions greet us - our own consumerist attitude, degradation of aesthetics, encouraging the death of the small mom and pop store and so on. At the same time it is an oasis for those who can afford a certain lifestyle thanks to their prices.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/large-store.jpeg" alt="Walmart can also be thought of as a museum" srcset="    /assets/resized/large-store-320x240.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/large-store-480x360.jpeg 480w,    /assets/resized/large-store-800x600.jpeg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/06/large-store.jpeg 1200w" /></p>

<p>The irony blinds us from seeing Walmart as what it also is, a modern day Cathedral of the various artefacts of human effort like the dora the explorer cherry berry bubble bath, white weed healthy white bread, hard candy nail polish jars, optimus prime pinata, <a href="https://supercenter.tumblr.com/">etc</a> Ironoia, as the author defines, is keeping everything we see around us at an arm’s length in case something better comes along. It is the metaphorical sofa cover that prevents us from ever experiencing the sofa.</p>

<p>Finding play and intrigue in everyday things like a vacuum or going grocery shopping is a good way to live. Randomly browsing things in a Walmart can also be enriching and fun. We musn’t let ironia prevent us from experiencing the world around us.</p>

<h5 id="the-power-of-constraints">The power of constraints</h5>

<p>Bringing the number of available options down makes satisficing easy and can lead to overall satisfaction. Schwartz called this the paradox of choice. In theory, choice makes us happy but too much choice adds cognitive load that can take away the joy from pursuing anything. 
Suppression of choice can also lead to a more meaningful interaction with the environment. When we silent our phones while eating, we are suppressing a choice which makes the meal more enjoyable. There are pleasures in both having too many choices and having fewer choices.</p>

<p>Limitations create playgrounds within which exploration can take place. Poetry with its meter, everyday things like the door knob with its rotation mechanism, our business goals with the constraints, are all examples of everyday games that make life fun. Dr Zeuss’s Cat and Hat and Green Eggs and Ham books use less than 50 words and have sold millions of copies. This is also an example of how constraints, that are often hidden from us, create wonderful experiences.</p>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehack" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In his book, Play Anything, Ian Bogost aims to explain how fun and play are not the same thing. He claims that “fun” is not pleasure but rather the aftereffect of play. This book challenges almost all notions of play, fun, pleasure, boredom and happiness. In this post I try to summarise the key ideas from the book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Practical lessons from The Mom Test</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/practical-insights-from-the-mom-test/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Practical lessons from The Mom Test" /><published>2023-05-14T00:00:02+05:30</published><updated>2023-05-14T00:00:02+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/practical-insights-the-mom-test</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/practical-insights-from-the-mom-test/"><![CDATA[<p>The Mom Test is a short book on how to ask questions about your product. It is a must read for anyone who is building a product or a startup. The book is full of practical advice and is a great reference book to keep coming back to. I have tried to summarize the key points below. The key takeaway for me was the attitude shift that is needed to ask questions. We must seek understanding our users and their life and not validation of our ideas. All the advise in the book stands on this key mental shift.</p>

<h5 id="switching-from-pitching-to-learning">Switching from pitching to learning</h5>

<p>When we go in pitch mode, we sound desperate and people can smell it. Since most people are uncomfortable in offering bad news or criticism, they will often say things like “that’s a great idea” or “I would totally use it” or “I know someone who would love this”. These are all lies and they are not born out of malice but by our poor questions and behaviors. The zeroth law of user research is to be in the learning frame of mind.</p>

<p>According to Fitzpatrick, a good conversation process has the following steps</p>

<ol>
  <li>Slice your customer base into as thin segments as possible - so you can answer who they are and where you can find them</li>
  <li>Write down your goals - what can be good possible next steps</li>
  <li>Vision-Framing-Weakness-Pedestal-Ask - this is a framing tactic. You must frame the conversation to discuss your vision about a particular problem and explain what stage you’re in. Show them your weaknesses or vulnerability about your solution and put them on a pedestal and say why you think their opinion matters. Finally, ask for help.</li>
  <li>Set up commital next steps - discussed in the last section</li>
  <li>Ask good questions - described in the next section</li>
  <li>Go through notes with team - all your learnings from the customers are relevant only if they are transmitted throughout your team</li>
</ol>

<h5 id="there-are-good-questions-and-bad-questions">There are good questions and bad questions</h5>

<p>While most of us can do with more user disussions than we already do, there are indeed some questions that we can avoid asking.</p>

<p>These are some bad questions.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Do you think its a good idea? - this is loaded and makes you want to hear self indulgent noise which you can do without.</li>
  <li>Would you ever buy something that lets you do X? - forces them to wax lyrical about a hypothetical future.</li>
  <li>How much you pay for X/would you pay X for Y? - this has some benefits but it should never be framed this way.</li>
</ol>

<p>These questions below are absolutely worth trying out.</p>

<ol>
  <li>How do you do X or can you show me? Another version would be “talk me through the last time x happened”.</li>
  <li>How much does it cost you? or how much does that matter (implications) - this is a better way to understand their willingness to pay.</li>
  <li>Why do you care about this problem or why does it even matter? Helps understand actual customer goals and not their idea of what it solves.</li>
  <li>What else have you tried?</li>
  <li>Who else should I talk to?</li>
  <li>Did I miss anything or should I have asked you to anything specific?</li>
</ol>

<p>Some things to keep in mind while coming up questions</p>

<ol>
  <li>Ask questions that can potentially break or make the business. Don’t be afraid of scary questions or shrinking from legal issues.</li>
  <li>Welcome bad news. In fact seek out information that can kill your idea. The sooner you get to that, the faster you will be able to fix it or move on to the next idea.</li>
  <li>Spot the lukewarm response and dig deeper. Don’t let people get away with vague answers. Ask them to be specific and give examples.</li>
  <li>Don’t zoom in too quickly. Don’t get too feature oriented or get into stack ranking needs before you’ve mapped the overall landscape through the customer lens.</li>
</ol>

<p>The bottom line is to keep them talking and helping you understand them well enough to build something they will love.</p>

<h5 id="spotting-bad-data">Spotting bad data</h5>

<p>Conversations, especially the ones that are not run with care, can lead to bad data that makes us wrongly confident. This is how bad data comes to us.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Complements - if any complements come your way deflect and come back on track. get suspicious as soon as you hear a complement.</li>
  <li>Fluff - generic ramblings. Ignore and get to specifics.</li>
  <li>“I always or generally do X” - ask them what/how they did last X.</li>
  <li>“I would definitely buy that in the future” - don’t ask would you ever instead ask “do you see yourself doing..”</li>
  <li>Hypothetical maybes - people generally describe who they want to be and not who they are. They also complain unnecessarily. Asking for specifics on how they deal with X, can reveal if they are indeed being honest. Be wary of “someone should definitely build X” cause more often than not, X’s exist and people don’t necessarily care about it enough to find it.</li>
  <li>Their ideas - handle feature requests by understanding the true motivation behind it. It can either be a generic request of the type “this seems like a killer feature” but with no way to back it up with why its so important or crucial. Or it can be based on them having employed a workaround and knowing what it costs them in time/money. The latter is a good signal to build something.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="stop-fishing-for-compliments-fish-for-committments">Stop fishing for compliments, fish for committments</h5>

<p>The best way to get people to commit to something is to ask them to do something small and low risk. This is called the foot in the door technique. Once they have committed to something small, they are more likely to commit to something bigger. This is called the consistency bias. This was a key insight in the book <a href="https://www.infermuse.com/handling-objections">Objections</a> as well.</p>

<p>A good customer meeting or a fruitful conversation ends in clear next steps. The best meetings end in committments which can include</p>

<ol>
  <li>Pre-orders, paid pilot, deposits, etc.</li>
  <li>Introductions to other people - peers, friends, bosses.</li>
  <li>A public testimonal - they are ready to put their name on it</li>
  <li>A pilot</li>
</ol>

<p>Poor conversations or meetings end in a vague committment and compliment. “This is great, keep me posted” or “drop me a note when you launch”. If you receive any of these, ask them what else would they like to see for you to move to next steps.</p>

<h5 id="how-to-get-conversations-going">How to get conversations going</h5>

<p>There are several ways to get busy with customer conversations.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Organise events - become the centre of attention (“Office Mangers Happy Hour”)</li>
  <li>Teaching - free one on one consulting/webinars</li>
  <li>Blogging - write about your industry and get people to comment</li>
  <li>I am writing a book/PhD dissertation - people will always talk to you (related to the pedestal point)</li>
  <li>Advisory Board - get people to join your advisory board (everyone wants to help someone else, few know how to do it)</li>
</ol>

<p>You can even cold email people to help but cold emails are tricky. You can use the same <em>Vision-Framing-Weakness-Pedestal-Ask</em> framework.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Establish you’re an entrepreneur - state your high level vision (not the specific idea)</li>
  <li>Frame the expectations - tell them you’re not going to sell</li>
  <li>Show weakness - how you’re looking to get some questions answered</li>
  <li>Put them on a pedestal - why you think their experience matters to you</li>
  <li>Ask them for help - ask the “good questions” like the ones discussed above.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet </a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Business" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Mom Test is a short book on how to ask questions about your product. It is a must read for anyone who is building a product or a startup. The book is full of practical advice and is a great reference book to keep coming back to. I have tried to summarize the key points below. The key takeaway for me was the attitude shift that is needed to ask questions. We must seek understanding our users and their life and not validation of our ideas. All the advise in the book stands on this key mental shift.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Handling Objections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/handling-objections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Handling Objections" /><published>2023-04-08T08:00:05+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-08T08:00:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/handling-objections</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/handling-objections/"><![CDATA[<p>The book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Objections-audiobook/dp/B07RQVYZQZ/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=objections+jeb+blount&amp;qid=1682825855&amp;sprefix=objections+je%2Caps%2C447&amp;sr=8-1">Objections</a>, by Jeb Blount, a seasoned sales expert, is a fantastic book on handling objections in sales. It is a must-read for anyone who is in sales or is building a startup. The book is full of practical advice and is a great reference book to keep coming back to. According to Blount, effective sales is essentially about two things</p>

<ol>
  <li>Snapping the buyer out of their habitual responses to your questions, and</li>
  <li>Keeping your (the sellers) emotions under check</li>
</ol>

<p>These two may sound intuitive but there’s a lot of layers to how we go about executing them, especially in pressure cooker situations when we are too heavily invested in the outcomes. I have tried to summarize the key points below.</p>

<h5 id="asking-is-everything">Asking is everything</h5>

<p>Asking gets you everything in sales. According to the author, ask for what you want and don’t be afraid of hearing a No. Be assumptive and confident and not passive or desperate. Don’t use passive language like ‘i was wondering if you’re free..’ and instead ‘I am visiting a client not far from you and how about I pick you for lunch’. People can smell desperation a mile away and it’s a turn off.</p>

<p>The whole idea of asking is to give your buyer a chance to say yes. This is why after making the ask you need to shut up and don’t feel compelled to fill the silence. The buyer needs time to think and you need to give them that time. Bringing objections to the surface is super important (we discuss the different types of objections in the next section) and for that you must keep the buyer talking.</p>

<p>An interesting aspect of asking questions is letting the buyer indulge in self disclosure. The brain rewards self disclosure so keeping them talking about themselves has a higher chance of them bringing up real objections as you build rapport and trust.</p>

<p>The self disclosure goes something like this.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Ask open ended questions</li>
  <li>Offer full attention and listen actively</li>
  <li>Don’t interrupt or talk over</li>
  <li>Pause 3-5 seconds before speaking</li>
  <li>Center your questions on self disclosures with questions like “i noticed from your linkedin you’ve spent almost 10 years here..what are some of the changes that you have seen in your industry”.</li>
</ol>

<h5 id="types-of-objections">Types of objections</h5>

<p>There are 4 main types of objections</p>

<ol>
  <li>Prospecting objections - the kind you face when you’re trying to qualify leads. Everyone is busy and has little time so these are often reflexive or brush-offs objections (RBOs).</li>
  <li>Red Herrings - intentional or unintentional statements buyers spew out. Sometimes are totally irrelevant and are said to divert attention. They can distract you so you need to spot them and avoid chasing these. Pause and acknowledge that you heard them and say ‘let me make a note of that’. don’t bring it up later unless they do it.</li>
  <li>Microcommittment objections - Asking for tiny committments (like a hard date for the next call or pilot kickoff or specific data) keeps the deal moving forward. These need to be low risk actions that the buyer can take. We discuss these in detail later in the post.</li>
  <li>Buying committment objections - things like pricing, timing, need to talk to my boss, competitors, conditions, terms, etc.</li>
</ol>

<h5 id="handling-objections">Handling objections</h5>

<p>There are several frameworks mentioned in the book you can employ to handle objections but these are all based on the fundamental idea of being prepared and practicing.</p>

<p>The Ledge-disrupt-ask loop for managing RBOs.</p>

<ol>
  <li>A ledge is an auto response that you dont have to think about. It gives you a few seconds to bring your conscious mind in and not let your emotions run afoul. This is where the preparation and practice comes in. It could be things like ‘that makes sense’ or ‘can you please explain how so’ or ‘sounds like you’re really..’, etc.</li>
  <li>Disrupt the flow of the conversation and give them something new so they can’t pattern match. It could be a statement or a question - “awesome, you should not think about changing but we’ll still like to show you cool stuff”. “can you send me something specific you want to see”, etc.</li>
  <li>Ask for exactly what you want assertively.</li>
</ol>

<p>Another important aspect of sales is developing a strategy for getting microcommittments. Getting buyers to make small committments makes them amenable to larger ones (this is based on the principle of consistency and committment bias that we all suffer from).</p>

<ol>
  <li>Relate  - Step into their shoes and undertand where they are coming from as a person and don’t discount their actions (“its ok to do what you are doing”). This is also a type of ledge and slows the conversation down.</li>
  <li>Isolate - Get all the objections and then try to gauge which ones are most consequential. Don’t start handling them one by one as they crop up.</li>
  <li>Minimise - don’t talk down but minimise the objections and reestablish the values of your solution. One way to do this is to bring back all the previous yesses they have given and then start addressing the most consequential objections one by one.</li>
  <li>Ask - Ask for a committment assertively and confidently. Don’t be afraid of hearing a No. If you get a No, ask why and then go back to step 3 and minimise the objection. If you get a Yes, then ask for the next committment.</li>
  <li>Fallback to an alternative committment - Use your previous collected yesses to show far they have come and keep them going. If they say No, then fallback to a smaller committment and keep going.</li>
</ol>

<h5 id="7-disruptive-emotions">7 Disruptive emotions</h5>

<p>Emotions derail sales conversations and you need to be aware of them and keep them in check. Objections feel like rejections which trigger flight or fight responses that leads to us losing our emotional control. This often appears in one of the 7 disruptive emotions</p>

<ol>
  <li>Fear - clouds objectivity</li>
  <li>Desperation - needy and weak, unlikeable</li>
  <li>Insecurity - drowns assertiveness, makes us feel lonely</li>
  <li>Need for significance - feel unimportant, egocentricity causes irrational beahavior</li>
  <li>Attachment - lose perspective due to wanting to be right</li>
  <li>Eagerness - lose sight of sales objective by trying to please buyers</li>
  <li>Worry - leads to procrastination caused by negative thinking. focus on what could go right not the other way around.</li>
</ol>

<p>The book really underscores the importance of keeping our own emotions under control. Recognising what you’re feeling is the step one, being prepared to deal with it is another and finally practicing your ledges and asks, is the last step.</p>

<h5 id="emotional-control">Emotional control</h5>

<p>The final takeaway from this book, and for me the most important one, was the idea of emotional control. The author talks about emotional control in the following ways but you’ll notice the core idea is based on “we suffer more in the head”.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Develop self awareness - Tune in and become aware. Don’t let your flight or fight response suspend your conscious thought process. Modulate emotions to make them congruent with your objectives. Can be developed with practice.</li>
  <li>Positive visualisation - Why will I succeed vs why will I fail. Slow down your breating and actualise your success. Materialise you getting what you want.</li>
  <li>Manage self talk - Take control of your mental chatter and don’t let your emotions be projected outward. People are rude to you but then they forget about you, however you can continue to feel rejected for a whole lot longer.</li>
  <li>Change your physical posture - How we stand or sit shapes how we feel and think. Physically standing makes us feel more confident and assertive.</li>
  <li>Stay fit - Regulating disruptive emotions is draining and you need to be fit to tackle them.</li>
  <li>Managing flight or fight - Give your rational brain a few seconds to catch up. Take a pause. This is where practiced ledges can help you. Using filler words like ‘interesting, can you tell me more’ or “could you tell me why is that important to you”, etc can often prevent you from reacting poorly to a situation or comment.</li>
  <li>This or that - when you find yourself digging in, you need to ask if what you’re doing is in line with your overall objectives, this helps avoid reactance</li>
  <li>Immunity for the fear of rejection - don’t be afraid of facing obstacles. practice getting rejections and you’ll find that they are not that bad. you’ll also find that you’ll get better at handling them.</li>
  <li>High self esteem - developing a high self esteem helps in getting over rejection and also help you become more likeable and less desperate.</li>
</ol>

<p>To summarise, rejection avoidance is hardwired into our biology. We learn to fear it and thus avoid it making us emotionally vulnerable and opens us upto losing control of our emotions and goofing up our situations. The most effective sales people know that objections are a part of the decision making process and instead of not seeking them or fearing them, theytry to get them out on the table earlier and handle them in a prepared fashion.</p>
<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="Business" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The book Objections, by Jeb Blount, a seasoned sales expert, is a fantastic book on handling objections in sales. It is a must-read for anyone who is in sales or is building a startup. The book is full of practical advice and is a great reference book to keep coming back to. According to Blount, effective sales is essentially about two things]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from the book New Power</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-the-book-new-power/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from the book New Power" /><published>2023-04-08T08:00:05+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-08T08:00:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-new-power</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/lessons-from-the-book-new-power/"><![CDATA[<p>The book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/New-Power-audiobook/dp/B0731GZPWP/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2HPMGN20RYGA1&amp;keywords=new+power+book&amp;qid=1680928858&amp;sprefix=new+power+bo%2Caps%2C580&amp;sr=8-1">New Power</a>, by Jeremy Heimans and Henry Timms, explores the new power structures that are emerging in the world and how they are changing the way we live, work and play. The book is a great read for anyone who is interested in learning how we can leverage these changes to build movements and brands that matter. I’ll try and summarise my key takeaways from the book in this post.</p>

<h5 id="new-power-models-and-new-power-values">New power models and new power values</h5>

<p>The book talks about the new power models that are emerging in the world and how they are entirely different from old power models. The old power models rely on authority, commands and ownership while the new power models relies on values of openness, collaboration, transparency, and participation. The new power emerges from activities of the crowd. The MeToo movement, ISIS recruitment using social media, opatients using platforms like <em>patientslikeme</em> to discuss and learn from other patients on managing their similar diseases, etc, are all examples of new power models. A nice analogy to think about the old and new power models is look at the classic game Tetris in which you get tiles decided by the computer and then it overwhlems you eventually. Minecraft, on the other hand, is participatory. Other players create worlds for you and the game is about building on top of what others have created.</p>

<p>Old power values are managerism, institutionalism, top down governance, confidientiality, discretion, expertise, professionalism, loyalty, etc. New power values are informal networked governance, collaboration, crowd wisdom, short term conditional affiliation, part time participation, openness, radical transparency, etc. Here’s a neat graphic to think about how the old power models and values can mix and match in a 2x2 quadrant.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/old-new-power.png" alt="Old and new power models and values" srcset="    /assets/resized/old-new-power-320x215.png 320w,    /assets/resized/old-new-power-480x323.png 480w,    /assets/resized/old-new-power-800x539.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/04/old-new-power.png 1200w" /></p>

<h5 id="how-ideas-spread">How ideas spread</h5>

<p>There are some common aspects about ideas that spread (or movements that go viral). One example that is referenced in the book and that I also happen to recall from a few years ago was the ALS Ice Bucket Challenge. The challenge was to pour a bucket of ice water on your head and then nominate 3 other people to do the same. The challenge went viral and raised millions of dollars for ALS research. The book talks about the acronym ACE that spells out the three main aspects of the challenge that made it go viral.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/als-ice-bucket.jpeg" alt="ALS Ice Bucket challenge" srcset="    /assets/resized/als-ice-bucket-320x483.jpeg 320w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/04/als-ice-bucket.jpeg 440w" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>Action - they make us act in a certain way. The ALS ice bucket challenge, challenges us to pour ice water on your head. It is important to be less cynical about the actions, no matter how small they are. Gladwell defined “weak ties activism” or “clicktivism” as tiny irrelevant acts done on the internet that have weak or no correlation with the end objective but in reality, movements like blacklivesmatter, have shown that you can always move people from low participation to high participation. The challenge is to find the right action that will move people from low to high participation.</li>
  <li>Connected - promote peer connection with people who share common values. A key part of the ALS challenge was to nominate others to do the same. This kickstarts a network effect. Social media platforms like Facebook and Twitter are great at promoting connectedness. The book talks about how the ALS challenge was able to leverage the power of social media to spread the challenge virally.</li>
  <li>Extensible - can be altered or extended by people on their own while keeping the core idea safe. People innovated on their videos while still feeling they were joined to a common cause. This is based on the optimal distinctiveness theory. An ideal new power group should make its members feel like a part of a larger group and yet have potential for individual expression.</li>
</ol>

<h5 id="how-to-build-new-power-communities">How to build new power communities</h5>

<p>New power communities can be thought of as a triangle. This new power triangle is composed of the owners of the platform (and overarching rules), second are its participants (consumers and ordinary creators) and final side is the super participants, those who produce or consume a whole lot more than ordinary participants and keep the platform humming. Around this triangle are other factors like the following.</p>

<ol>
  <li>How much power or agency to give to participants - The Occupy movement became so democratic that they lost steam as they kept debating within each other and the right way to come to decisions. While top down bureaucratic decisions also don’t work, the right balance is to give participants enough power to make decisions but not too much that they lose focus.</li>
  <li>Feedback loops from participants - what works, what doesn’t and to what extent.</li>
  <li>How to manage super participants - so that they keep producing and consuming more and more.</li>
  <li>Incentives and rewards - keep bringing the users back for more. Etsy’s 3.5% fees, Lyft returning the full commission post a driver crossing a weekly hour number, meetup upfront fees to host events, etc</li>
  <li>Recognition and statuses - karma points, blue tick, superadmins, etc. Perhaps this is linked to incentives but it is important to distinguish between the two. Recognition and status is about how you are perceived by others. Incentives are about how you are rewarded by the platform.</li>
  <li>Participation premium - think of it like this equation <em>something you’re selling + higher purpose * participation</em>.  Decouples the value of the product from the price paid by the participants. The example of Starcitizens comes to mind. Starcitizens are a community formed around a space travel game that is in design. It’s members have already enjoyed benefits of a community of a niche shared interest even before the game is launched. Xiaomi also first created community of cellphone design enthusiasts that leverages the <em>ikea effect</em> as participants pay more for stuff for which they played a role to build.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><category term="Business" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The book New Power, by Jeremy Heimans and Henry Timms, explores the new power structures that are emerging in the world and how they are changing the way we live, work and play. The book is a great read for anyone who is interested in learning how we can leverage these changes to build movements and brands that matter. I’ll try and summarise my key takeaways from the book in this post.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bringing awe into our lives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bringing-awe-into-to-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bringing awe into our lives" /><published>2023-03-12T08:00:05+05:30</published><updated>2023-03-12T08:00:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bringing-awe-into-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bringing-awe-into-to-life/"><![CDATA[<p>Awe is a type of emotion that has many affable qualities. Dacher Keltner’s book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Awe-Science-Everyday-Wonder-Transform/dp/B09YMNCBQD/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=awe+the+new+science+of+everyday+wonder&amp;qid=1678590561&amp;sprefix=AWE+%2Caps%2C664&amp;sr=8-1">Awe</a> talks about the role of awe in our lives and how it can inspire creativity, bring down stress and help us lead the good life. It lists down 8 simple ways we can find awe in our daily life.</p>

<h5 id="the-cool-thing-about-awe">The cool thing about awe</h5>

<p>The most common definition of Awe is the feeling of vastness that we experience when we encounter something that is bigger than us. Music, art, religion, nature, sports are some common conduits of awe. It is usually felt in the presence of something vast that transcends our current understanding of the world. Vastness can be physical, temporal, semantic, about ideas, challenging, destablising, etc.</p>

<p>Awe is contextual. Where we come from affects how we experience awe. For example, how we conceptualise virtue based on our upbriging, cultural experience, religious beliefs, etc affects how we experience moral beauty which in turn affects how we experience awe. Cultural preferences can also affect how we feel awe. Hierarchical cultures like Japan, experience awe in front of an inspiring personality with some element of fear. Cultures and religions that don’t believe in a judgemental God philosophy, experience bliss in encounter with the divine.</p>

<p>Experiencing awe, for example by looking at the skeleton of a T Rex, helps quite down our hyper individualistic self and opens us for collaboration. Our default mode network or DMN - the part of our brain network that is associated with the excesses of our ego, is known quiten down when in presence of something vast. It also helps us make peace with the fact that we are not a 100% control of our lives.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid" src="/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/museum.jpeg" alt="Art is one of the ways we can experience awe" srcset="    /assets/resized/museum-320x213.jpeg 320w,    /assets/resized/museum-480x320.jpeg 480w,    /assets/resized/museum-800x533.jpeg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2023/03/museum.jpeg 1200w" /></p>

<p>Awe can also amplify our thinking faculties. Einstein is said to have been awe struck by rainbows and much of the work around refraction and perception was triggered by it.</p>

<h5 id="8-ways-you-can-welcome-awe-into-your-life">8 ways you can welcome awe into your life</h5>

<p>The author calls this section 8 wonders of life. Here are the 8 ways you can experience awe in your life.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Moral beauty - Watching, experiencing or reading about other people’s acts of courage, justice, generosity, etc</li>
  <li>Collective effervescence - moving in unison or participating in shared attention. It is the force people feel when in a collective (sporting events, dance classes, rituals and ceremonies)</li>
  <li>Nature - hikes, spending time in the wild, rock climbing, rafting, etc. merely listening to flowing water is known to improve our attention and provide better ability to discern between urgent and important matters.</li>
  <li>Music - specific musical notes make us feel specific emotions and these emotions are universally similar across cultures. if you like listening to music, you can easily get your daily dose of awe from it.</li>
  <li>Visual design - paintings, buildings, machines, etc. Appreciating actual contours of the geometry can incite certain feelings in us. In visual design, we like familiarity of form and design and it makes us feel comforted.</li>
  <li>Spiritual or religious stories - there are over 4200 active religions in the world today and the mystical awe that originates from it can cause feelings of “vanishing self” or “ego death” that bring awe and are known to make us more curious, creative and altruistic.</li>
  <li>Stories of life and death - thinking about or experiencing birth or death of a close one, can cause us to appreciate the ephemeral nature of life and leave us awestruck.</li>
  <li>Epiphanies - sudden understandings of truths about life. when systems thinking exposes us how the world around us works, awe overtakes us (think Darwin’s voyage to the Galapagos)</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>I run a startup called <a href="http://www.harmonizehq.com/">Harmonize</a>. We are hiring and if you’re looking for an exciting startup journey, please write to jobs@harmonizehq.com. Apart from this blog, <a href="https://twitter.com/dillisingh">I tweet</a>about startup life and practical wisdom in books.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ujjwal</name></author><category term="Book Reviews" /><category term="Lifehacks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Awe is a type of emotion that has many affable qualities. Dacher Keltner’s book Awe talks about the role of awe in our lives and how it can inspire creativity, bring down stress and help us lead the good life. It lists down 8 simple ways we can find awe in our daily life.]]></summary></entry></feed>